<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-21T16:34:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Great Company]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/22/building-a-great-company/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T11:34:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/22/building-a-great-company</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/good_to_great_blackbox.png' width='' height='' alt='What happens inside the black box?' title='What happens inside the black box?'><span class='caption-text'>What happens inside the black box?</span></span></p>

<p>Good is the enemy of great. If a company faces dire circumstances, managers must change because the alternative is death. But if circumstances are good (or even <em>okay</em>) managers can coast along indefinitely. A good company can be lulled into a state of complacency instead of achieving greatness.</p>

<p>So how does a good company become great?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Good to Great</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/good_to_great.jpg' width='' height='' alt='' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span>
A team led by author <a href="http://www.jimcollins.com/">Jim Collins</a> spent five years examining publicly traded companies to determine why some companies make the leap to greatness while others remain simply good. Collins and his team published their findings in the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Good-Great-Social-Sectors-Monograph-ebook/dp/B0058DRTGC/">Good to Great</a>.</p>

<h3>Greatness Defined</h3>

<p>The study only focused on publicly traded companies since their financial data is readily available. The team defined great companies as those that beat the general stock market by an average of seven times (7x) over fifteen years. This is better than double the results delivered by some of the world’s greatest companies, including Intel, Coca-Cola, and General Electric.</p>

<p>Special attention was paid to companies that delivered average or poor results for fifteen years, followed by a sudden shift to great results. The team’s driving question: What are the universal distinguishing characteristics that cause a company to go from good to great? Or, in the diagram at the top of this article: What’s inside the black box?</p>

<h3>￼What Great Companies Do</h3>

<p>Collins and his team observed that great companies are great because of the way they think and act. This newsletter will deal with two findings unveiled in the study:
• The Hedgehog Concept
• The Stockdale Paradox</p>

<h3>The Fox and the Hedgehog</h3>

<p>The hedgehog concept comes from an ancient fable about a fox and a hedgehog. The fox is hungry for a hedgehog dinner. Cunning and skillful, the fox has several clever attack (hedgehog dinner) plans to choose from.</p>

<p>The hedgehog is less clever, but it has one (and only one) very effective plan: To roll itself into a ball, exposing its needles and giving the fox a powerful incentive to look elsewhere for food.</p>

<p>The fox has many clever plans, and the hedgehog has one very effective plan. In the fable, simplicity triumphs over cleverness. The hedgehog wins.</p>

<h3>Hedgehogs and Business</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/hedgehog_concept.png' width='' height='' alt='' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span>
The Good to Great team discovered that great companies are like the hedgehog. Great companies focus on the one thing that they are good at. Further, great companies only fix their focus after an honest and serious examination of their strengths &amp; weaknesses. The best focal point lies at the intersection of three interlocking rings:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Deep Passion</strong>. What does the company feel deeply passionate about? What gives them that “I can’t believe I get paid to do this” feeling?</li>
<li><strong>Sound Economics</strong>. What will customers pay the company to do or provide? What drives the economic engine?</li>
<li><strong>Best in the World</strong>. What can the company do better than any other company in the world?</li>
</ul>


<h3>Deep Passion</h3>

<p>Gillette was cited as a great company where employees were excited about the advanced technology in their razors. They decided on advanced-technology razors largely because they couldn’t get excited about competing in the price-sensitive disposable market.</p>

<p>Employees of the Federal National Mortgage Association (Fannie Mae) could never get excited about crunching numbers, but the idea of helping people buy homes proved exciting. Fannie Mae employees are on a heroic quest to democratize home ownership.</p>

<p>The Good to Great team observed that passion cannot be forced, it can only be discovered. Forcing your company to be passionate about an idea is like forcing yourself to like a particular flavor of ice cream. You either like it or you don’t.</p>

<h3>Sound Economics</h3>

<p>What will customers pay for? And what is the best way to measure progress toward greatness? The great companies found one metric (like profit per store or profit per employee) that every person in the company could focus on during the march to greatness.</p>

<p>One great company, Walgreens, chose profit per customer visit as the best economic measuring stick for their business. The decision was driven by their discovery that customers will pay for convenience, and the most convenient store locations are also the most expensive to lease &amp; maintain. The only way to justify expensive locations: Make every customer visit as profitable as possible.</p>

<h3>Best in the World</h3>

<p>Investor Warren Buffett says this about Wells Fargo: &ldquo;They stick with what they understand and let their abilities, not their egos, determine what they attempt.&rdquo; At one point the bank decided to shut down its international operations and focus on the Western United States. Other banks, notably Bank of America, pursued every possible opportunity regardless of its fit with their skill set. The result: Wells Fargo outperformed and outgrew the much larger competitor. Wells Fargo played fox to the BofA hedgehog.</p>

<h3>The Stockdale Paradox</h3>

<p>Admiral Jim Stockdale was the highest ranking U.S. military officer captured during the Vietnam War. During eight years of imprisonment, he and his fellow soldiers were tortured repeatedly and forced to participate in propaganda films as “well treated” prisoners. The prisoners had no idea whether they would survive to see their families again. Stockdale survived, and after his release, the Admiral and his wife co-authored an account of his ordeal in the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Love-War-Familys-Sacrifice-Vietnam/dp/0060153180/">In Love and War</a>.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper center'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/stockdale_paradox.png' width='' height='' alt='' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span></p>

<h3>Optimism and Discouragement</h3>

<p>Imprisonment is far more serious than anything most business execs will ever face. Still, the Good to Great team and Admiral Stockdale were able to draw parallels between growing a company and surviving life as a POW. For example, the Admiral observed that optimists had the hardest time in prison. Optimistic prisoners always believed “we’ll be released next Christmas” only to be discouraged year after year. Many optimists eventually died heartbroken in prison.</p>

<p>Stockdale’s policy was to be brutally honest about the situation he was facing and to deal with it directly day to day. At the same time, he maintained faith that he would prevail in the end. During the pain of the ordeal, he decided to turn the experience into the defining event of his life. Thus the paradox: He brutally confronted his reality, yet he maintained faith that he would prevail in the end.</p>

<h3>Great Companies Respond Differently to Adversity</h3>

<p>Collins and his team observed that companies, being made up of people, behave like people. What separates the good from the great is not whether they have difficulties, but how they deal with those difficulties. Every company faces obstacles of one type or another. But the great companies face those obstacles directly, recognizing them for what they are, while at the same time maintaining faith that they will prevail.</p>

<h3>Stockdale Paradox Example</h3>

<p>The banking industry became commoditized during the 1980s period of de-
regulation. Some banks left the industry (voluntarily or otherwise). Wells Fargo, however, thrived and grew during the upheaval. They confronted the brutal reality of deregulation and commoditization by focusing on one region of the United States and moving more of their operations to small branches and ATMs, thereby increasing profit per employee. Other banks, that did not confront changing reality, were either dissolved or acquired.</p>

<h3>Does Technology Matter?</h3>

<p>What about technology? Great companies are not necessarily those that spent the most on technology. This makes sense when you consider that technology is only a tool; only a bus that a company chooses to ride. If the bus is headed in the wrong direction, a faster bus will only make things worse. But if the bus is headed in the right direction, then a faster bus might accelerate the move to greatness.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this article was originally posted at <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup.com</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Muhammad Ali and the Hightower Brothers]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/20/muhammad-ali-and-the-hightower-brothers/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-20T12:40:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/20/muhammad-ali-and-the-hightower-brothers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/muhammad_ali_hightower_brothers.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Muhammad Ali and the Hightower Brothers, circa 1972.' title='Muhammad Ali and the Hightower Brothers, circa 1972.'><span class='caption-text'>Muhammad Ali and the Hightower Brothers, circa 1972.</span></span></p>

<p>These photos were taken in 1972 or &lsquo;73 with an old Polaroid camera. During a family road trip, my parents arranged a visit to <a href="http://muhammadali.com/">Muhammad Ali</a>’s training camp in Deer Lake, Pennsylvania. Dad was a big boxing fan. Mom&hellip; tolerated the three males in our household.</p>

<p>How fast was Ali in his prime? Very fast. One photo shows him evading a punch from my brother, Edward, who was about seven at the time. I distracted the Champ with a handshake. Hightowers always work together.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Our family didn’t receive any special treatment from the Champ. As I recall (through the eyes of my eight-year-old self) Ali interacted with everyone in the training camp that day. And I hear that he enjoys people just as much today.</p>

<p>There are many reasons to admire Ali. Among them are his discipline, courage, and effective marketing.</p>

<h3>Discipline</h3>

<blockquote><p>The fight is won or lost far away from witnesses, long before I dance under those lights.<br/>~Muhammad Ali</p></blockquote>

<p>A professional athlete cannot fake preparation. Sometimes the training feels endless. Road work, weights, sparring, and drills are designed to condition the mind and body for combat. Fakers are eliminated early; they never make it to the national stage. Champions have the discipline to train even when they don&rsquo;t feel like it.</p>

<p>Every profession has the equivalent of athletic training. For example, software developers are constantly reading blogs, experimenting with algorithms, and practicing kata. The best entrepreneurs are those who observe human behavior, and they build products and a team to meet customer needs. Sometimes the work feels endless. But champions do it anyway.</p>

<p>Champions, in athletics and in business, have the discipline to do what needs to be done even when they don&rsquo;t feel like doing it.</p>

<h3>Courage</h3>

<blockquote><p>I ain’t got no quarrel with those Vietcong.<br/>~Ali</p></blockquote>

<p>Ali was stripped of his boxing title when he refused to fight in the Vietnam war. He was a conscientious objector. He was arrested and found guilty of draft evasion. Four years after the title was taken, the Supreme Court of the United States overturned the conviction. Ali stuck with his values in spite of the professional cost. His view of the war in Vietnam was ahead of its time.</p>

<p>As professionals, how often are we asked to take a stand in the face of personal cost?</p>

<p>Ali currently suffers from Parkinson&rsquo;s disease. It would have been easy for him to lock himself in a room full of money and never interact with people again. However, he chose a different path. Through the <a href="http://www.thebarrow.org/Neurological_Services/Muhammad_Ali_Parkinson_Center/index.htm">Muhammad Ali Parkinson Center</a> he fights for a cure for himself and others. Ali continues to fight.</p>

<h3>Effective Marketing</h3>

<p>Ali talked trash before and after every fight, taunting his opponents with ridicule and poetry.</p>

<blockquote><p>Float like a butterfly, sting like a bee.<br/>
The hands can’t hit what the eyes can’t see.<br/>~Ali</p></blockquote>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/ali_eth_2011.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ali with Edward Hightower in 2011.' title='Ali with Edward Hightower in 2011.'><span class='caption-text'>Ali with Edward Hightower in 2011.</span></span>
Ali’s boasting was all about marketing. My father used to say “people like to see a braggart get whupped.” The more Ali boasted, the more tickets the fight promoters could sell and the more Ali could justify big fees for boxing. Privately, Ali shared that he would never let his boasting interfere with his training.</p>

<p>In 2011, Ali and my brother met again at the <a href="https://alicenter.org/">Muhammad Ali Center</a> in Louisville, KY. Edward keeps copies of the 1972 photos on his phone; the Champ enjoyed seeing himself from long ago. Check out Ali’s t-shirt and the photos on the conference room walls. Ali is always marketing and he loves to interact with people. What a remarkable role model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solar and Tesla]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/08/solar-and-tesla/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-08T18:33:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/08/solar-and-tesla</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>We have this handy fusion reactor in the sky called the sun. We don’t have to do anything. It just works.
<br/>&nbsp;
~Elon Musk</p></blockquote>

<p>Elon Musk shared some interesting thoughts during the April 30th announcement for <a href="http://www.teslamotors.com/powerwall">Tesla Energy</a>. Two charts stood out in particular.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Solar Panels Required</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/tesla_blue_square_energy.png' width='' height='' alt='From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.' title='From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.'><span class='caption-text'>From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.</span></span></p>

<p>Take a look at the map of the United States, above. A blue square has been drawn in the northwest corner of Texas. At map scale, solar panels with combined surface area equal to the blue square could meet all of the electricity needs of the USA. And we’re the most power hungry country on the planet!</p>

<h3>Batteries Required</h3>

<p>Solar panels are useless at night and on cloudy days. Fortunately, we can store excess energy on sunny days if we have the right kind of batteries. Tesla happens to make those batteries, hence the Tesla Energy announcement.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/tesla_batteries.png' width='' height='' alt='From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.' title='From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.'><span class='caption-text'>From the Tesla Energy announcement on 30Apr2015.</span></span></p>

<p>The second map is drawn at a larger scale than the first one. For reference, the blue square covers the same surface area as before. At map scale, all of the batteries required to store reserve solar energy would fit inside the red dot.</p>

<p>What are we waiting for?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Berkshire Hathaway's 50th]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/06/berkshire-hathaway-50th/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-06T18:41:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/06/berkshire-hathaway-50th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/berkshire_hathaway_50th.jpg' width='' height='' alt='40,000 shareholders in Omaha.' title='40,000 shareholders in Omaha.'><span class='caption-text'>40,000 shareholders in Omaha.</span></span></p>

<blockquote><p>Hi, I&rsquo;m Warren. He&rsquo;s Charlie. He can hear, I can see. We work well together.
<br/>&nbsp;<br/>
~Warren Buffett,<br/>at the start of the 2015<br/>Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://berkshirehathaway.com">Berkshire Hathaway</a> held its 50th annual shareholder meeting on May 2, 2015. The company is a lesson in successful capitalism. Chairman Warren Buffett and vice chairman Charlie Munger have built the most successful investment partnership in human history. The list of wholly-owned Berkshire subsidiaries includes GEICO, Fruit of the Loom, Brooks Shoes, and See&rsquo;s Candies. The company also owns large percentages of Coca Cola (9.16%), American Express (14.9%), IBM (7.82%), and Wells Fargo (9.01%).</p>

<p>Over 40,000 shareholders attended Saturday&rsquo;s annual meeting. What draws so many shareholders to Omaha every year? The opportunity to learn.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>The Meeting, In a Nutshell</h3>

<p>The formal shareholders meeting only lasts fifteen minutes, from 3:30pm to 3:45pm. For the rest of the day (excluding an hour for lunch) Buffett (age 84) and Munger (age 91) answer questions from journalists, financial analysts, and randomly selected members of the audience.</p>

<p>The day starts at 8:30am with a movie.</p>

<h3>Morning Movie</h3>

<p>Each Berkshire meeting starts with a short movie. One year, the movie included information about a recent acquisition, a deal that had been completed just hours before the meeting. This year&rsquo;s movie was a humorous montage of skits worthy of Saturday Night Live, woven with ads for Berkshire products. Berkshire brought in Hollywood director John Landis to direct this year&rsquo;s opening movie. One skit included a boxing match between Buffett and Floyd Mayweather. Charlie Rose interviewed the pugilists before their bout. Mayweather and Rose played themselves in the skit.</p>

<h3>Questions and Answers</h3>

<p>Buffest and Munger answer questions from the stage while sipping Coke and munching See&rsquo;s candy. Their answers tend to be short and direct, laced with wit. Snippets of wisdom from the Q &amp; A session:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Buffett: Investing is easy if you can control your emotions.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger: I quit practicing law. Law firms are like a pie eating contest where if you win, you get to eat a lot more pie.</p></li>
<li><p>Buffett: When it comes to investing, I prefer to be 100x too cautious, rather than 1x un-cautious.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger: Both of us hate the idea of losing someone else&rsquo;s money. It drives our caution.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger: People want value when they buy something. But when they invest, they go for the quick fix. I don&rsquo;t understand that.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger (When asked if he would have preferred to be born in 2015 instead of 1924): I don&rsquo;t like these overly theoretical questions. I&rsquo;d rather answer questions where I can actively help somebody.</p></li>
<li><p>Buffett (summarizing capitalism): Do what you&rsquo;re best at. Let other people do what they&rsquo;re best at.</p></li>
<li><p>Buffett (on his long term perspective): I get monthly reports from all our companies and I read them with great interest. We don&rsquo;t ignore monthly or yearly results. We just don&rsquo;t live by them.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger (When asked about Berkshire&rsquo;s interest in investing in Germany): Germans work fewer hours and produce a lot more. We&rsquo;d like to invest in Germany, but it&rsquo;s difficult to penetrate family company ownership structure.</p></li>
<li><p>Buffett (When asked about the NetJets pilots picketing outside the annual meeting): We have hundreds of labor unions in BRK. Three strikes in fifty years. Employees and employers sometimes disagree regarding pay. That&rsquo;s human nature. We will resolve this disagreement.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger (Predicting why the Euro will eventually fail): You can&rsquo;t form a business partnership with your thriftless, drunken brother in law.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger (On BRK borrowing money): We haven&rsquo;t felt cash constrained in a long time. We would love to have an acquisition large enough to require us to borrow.</p></li>
<li><p>Buffett (On giving up his private jet vs quitting the Internet): If I had to give up my plane or the Internet, I&rsquo;d give up the plane.</p></li>
<li><p>Munger (On why he and Buffett are so successful): We owe a considerable amount to the families we were raised in. We had great role models.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Giving Credit for Success</h3>

<p>Throughout the Q &amp; A period, Buffett praised several of the Berkshire managers by name. When a questioner said something good about American Express, Buffett praised Ken Chenault. When someone had positive words about Berkshire&rsquo;s insurance holdings, Buffett credited Ajit Jain. Buffett and Munger share the credit for Berkshire&rsquo;s performance. That&rsquo;s a big reason why the companies perform so well.</p>

<h3>Meeting People</h3>

<p>When 40,000 investment-minded people gather, rich conversations will happen. After the meeting, I ended up having dinner with an asset manager from Brazil. Both of us arrived solo at Gorat&rsquo;s, Buffett&rsquo;s favorite steakhouse in Omaha. We decided to share a table when we realized that Gorat&rsquo;s would seat a table for two faster than two tables for one. Capitalism, properly practiced, is about cooperation.</p>

<h3>5k Run</h3>

<p>About 1,000 people gathered for the 5k <em>Invest in Yourself</em> run on Sunday morning. The weather was perfect.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/berkshire_hathaway_5k.jpg' width='' height='' alt='5k runners gather at the start.' title='5k runners gather at the start.'><span class='caption-text'>5k runners gather at the start.</span></span></p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/berkshire_hathaway_5k_finishers.jpg' width='' height='' alt='5k finishers queue up for swag.' title='5k finishers queue up for swag.'><span class='caption-text'>5k finishers queue up for swag.</span></span></p>

<h3>Looking Forward to the Next One</h3>

<p>The Berkshire Hathaway annual meeting offers an inspiring, powerful learning experience each year. I look forward to the next one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[pgcli - Command Line Interface for PostgreSQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/28/pgcli-command-line-interface-for-postgresql/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-28T11:59:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/28/pgcli-command-line-interface-for-postgresql</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Debugging is a fact of life when building apps with Rails or any other set of tools. All troubleshooting is easier when we can see what’s going on inside.</p>

<p><a href="http://pgcli.com/">pgcli</a> is a command line tool that lets devs examine PostgreSQL databases from the command line. <code>pgcli</code> offers more powerful features than <code>psql</code> (the default terminal front-end for PostgreSQL) such as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Autocompletion. In fact, <code>pgcli</code> autocompletion is smart enough to only show table names after <code>FROM</code> in a SQL statement.</li>
<li>Syntax highlighting. Find gotchas quicker, just like you would in a text editor.</li>
</ul>


<p>Debugging is easier when you can look inside the black box.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Installation</h3>

<p>To install <code>pgcli</code> on Mac OS X, use <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/12/homebrew-fundamentals/">Homebrew</a>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>brew install <span class="nv">pgcli</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Installing dependencies <span class="k">for </span>pgcli: openssl, <span class="nv">postgresql</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Installing pgcli dependency: <span class="nv">openssl</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Downloading https://homebrew.bintray.com/bottles/openssl-1.0.2a-1.yosemite.b
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">######################################################################## 100.0%</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c"># Homebrew installs dependencies as required...</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Installing <span class="nv">pgcli</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Downloading https://homebrew.bintray.com/bottles/pgcli-0.16.3.yosemite.bottl
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">######################################################################## 100.0%</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Pouring pgcli-0.16.3.yosemite.bottle.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>🍺  /usr/local/Cellar/pgcli/0.16.3: 423 files, 5.2M
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Verify installation as follows:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>which pgcli
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/bin/pgcli
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>pgcli --version
</span><span class='line'>Version: 0.16.3
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Using pgcli</h3>

<p>To view a list of available <code>pgcli</code> commands:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>pgcli --help
</span><span class='line'>Usage: pgcli <span class="o">[</span>OPTIONS<span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">[</span>DATABASE<span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">[</span>USERNAME<span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Options:
</span><span class='line'>  -h, --host TEXT     Host address of the postgres database.
</span><span class='line'>  -p, --port INTEGER  Port number at which the postgres instance is listening.
</span><span class='line'>  -U, --user TEXT     User name to connect to the postgres database.
</span><span class='line'>  -W, --password      Force password prompt.
</span><span class='line'>  -w, --no-password   Never prompt <span class="k">for </span>password.
</span><span class='line'>  -v, --version       Version of pgcli.
</span><span class='line'>  -d, --dbname TEXT   database name to connect to.
</span><span class='line'>  --help              Show this message and exit.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>To use <code>pgcli</code>:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>pgcli
</span><span class='line'>Version: 0.16.3
</span><span class='line'>Chat: https://gitter.im/amjith/pgcli
</span><span class='line'>Mail: https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/pgcli
</span><span class='line'>Home: http://pgcli.com
</span><span class='line'>rth&gt; <span class="se">\l</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><code>\l</code> will list the databases available to this installation of PostgreSQL. Note that the <code>pgcli</code> command prompt shows the currently logged in username. To discover other commands, use <code>\?</code>.</p>

<p>As you experiment with <code>pgcli</code>, notice the command completion and the syntax highlighting. Big time savers relative to <code>psql</code>.</p>

<h3>Acknowledgements</h3>

<p>Thanks <a href="https://twitter.com/adomokos">Attila Domokos</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/lostghost">Ken Walters</a> for the tweets that led to this <code>pgcli</code> blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to BLUE1647 and 1871]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T17:41:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When smart people<br/>
challenge each other to grow,<br/>
great things happen.<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
~The ChicagoRuby Motto</p></blockquote>

<p>If you’re a developer itchin’ to ramp up your Ruby skills, Chicago is a great place to be. The local Ruby user group, <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a>, continues to expand in time, space, expertise, and numbers. The group is over 3,200 strong, with six events each month <em>plus</em> the annual <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> conference.</p>

<p>The newest locations on ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s monthly list are BLUE1647 and 1871.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/blue1647.jpg' width='' height='' alt='BLUE1647' title='BLUE1647'><span class='caption-text'>BLUE1647</span></span>
<a href="http://www.blue1647.com/">BLUE 1647</a> is an amazing maker space on Chicago’s South Side, in the Pilsen neighborhood. The leadership of BLUE1647 invited ChicagoRuby to host our first meeting in the space on March 19, 2015. The presenter, <a href="https://twitter.com/johnnycon">John Contreras</a> of <a href="http://matchup.io">Matchup</a>, took us through the nuances of Rails background processing.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/rmillerwebster">Rebecca Miller-Webster</a> of <a href="http://thoughtbot.com">thoughtbot</a> will present at our next BLUE1647 meeting on April 17, 2015.</p>

<p>Check the <a href="http://meetup.com/chicagoruby">ChicagoRuby calendar</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<h3>ChicagoRuby: 1871</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/1871.jpg' width='' height='' alt='1871' title='1871'><span class='caption-text'>1871</span></span>
<a href="http://www.1871.com">1871</a> was an early player in Chicago&rsquo;s startup incubator industry. Community leaders at 1871 invited ChicagoRuby to lead some Ruby-oriented sessions at the incubator. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> will lead our first 1871 event on April 30, 2015.</p>

<h3>Organizer Team</h3>

<p>Eleven (yes, eleven!) organizers work in concert to make ChicagoRuby run well. Current members of the organizer team are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> &ndash; Started and co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/wondible">Justin Love</a> &ndash; Started in Elmhurst, acts as our liaison with the JavaScript community.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/themccreefiles">Alonda McCree</a> &ndash; Manages downtown video and logistics overall.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> &ndash; Runs Elmhurst and leads intro sessions at 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13059934/">Sarah Cnota</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker, manages the downtown meetups.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/HashtagLaToya">LaToya Allen</a> &ndash; Co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/bobbyreys">Bobby Reyes</a> &ndash; Driving force behind ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s activities at BLUE1647 and 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/185776457/">Dexter Teng</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker and newest member of the organizer team.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/rayhightower">Ray Hightower</a> &ndash; author of this article.</li>
</ul>


<p>ChicagoRuby excels because the work is shared amongst many people. Hats off to our <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org/about/organizers/">Organizer Alumni</a> too!</p>

<h3>Something For You</h3>

<p>As of this writing, ChicagoRuby manages six events per month. You are certain to find something that fits you.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Elmhurst</strong> &ndash; The first ChicagoRuby location. Meeting space provided by one of our members, Lee DeForest of DeForest Group.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Downtown</strong> &ndash; Currently at ThoughtWorks. Added when we merged with Chirb.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Hack Night</strong> &ndash; Currently at Enova. Added when Ginny Hendry said &ldquo;we should have hack nights&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: North Shore</strong> &ndash; Added when Doug Harman and Stu Gerstein said &ldquo;we should be on the North Shore&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</strong> &ndash; Added when Bobby Reyes formed relationships at the BLUE1647 maker space.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: 1871</strong> &ndash; Added when 1871 members asked ChicagoRuby to run some beginner-oriented sessions.</li>
</ul>


<p>Exact dates and locations are on the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/">ChicagoRuby calendar</a>. Come out and collaborate with your fellow learning enthusiasts. You&rsquo;ll be glad that you did.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon Dash and Instant Gratification]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/31/amazon-dash-and-instant-gratification/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-31T15:44:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/31/amazon-dash-and-instant-gratification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/amazon_dash_combo_cc_600.png' width='' height='' alt='Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.' title='Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.'><span class='caption-text'>Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.</span></span></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/oc/dash-button">Amazon Dash Button</a> is for customers who crave instant gratification. We might think of Dash as a brilliant blend of the Staples Easy Button, WiFi, and Amazon&rsquo;s existing database of credit card numbers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>When a customer runs out of a consumable item, they press a button. The order is sent immediately via WiFi to Amazon, where the customer&rsquo;s credit card number is on file. Delivery can happen within 24 hours, depending on the item. No more standing in line at the store. In fact, no more walking a few feet to a computer to type in an order. Instant gratification, satisfied.</p>

<h3>Video Summary</h3>

<p>This 1-minute video explains the service with just a few words, and plenty of images.</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NMacTuHPWFI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Innovation for You</h3>

<p>Kudos to Amazon for combining some existing pieces to create something new. Most inspiring for anyone who needs to innovate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bloom's Taxonomy for Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/20/blooms-taxonomy-for-learning/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/20/blooms-taxonomy-for-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://RayHightower.com/images/blooms_taxonomy_thumb.png" onclick="window.open('/images/blooms_taxonomy.png','popup','width=770,height=548,scrollbars=no,resizable=yes,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0'); return false"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/blooms_taxonomy_thumb.png" border="0" alt="Bloom's Taxonomy" name="image" class="right" width="250" height="162" title="Bloom's Taxonomy" /></a></p>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy is a framework that breaks the learning process into stages. According to Bloom, learning begins with rote memorization and the process progresses upward until we can apply what we&rsquo;ve learned in creative new ways.</p>

<h3>Youthful Bias</h3>

<p>Most of my formal education was science or engineering oriented. I regarded science and engineering as the pinnacle of learning. The extreme position of my youth: All logic fell within math and science, while history, language arts, and other non-science areas were just memorization.</p>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s research pushed me beyond my original thinking. Memorization and creativity are vital to all areas of knowledge. Here&rsquo;s how.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Learning Only Starts With Memorization</h3>

<p>All learning, at the very beginning, is memorization. For example, when we first learn mathematics, we start by memorizing the counting numbers (1, 2, 3, &hellip;) and we eventually figure out that we can&rsquo;t count to infinity. Later we learn the four basic math operations (addition, subtraction, multiplication, division) and we learn how to apply these operations to word problems. Fast forward a few years, and we learn to apply differential equations to a skydiver falling to earth via parachute. Or we may create a mathematical spreadsheet model to decide whether to invest in a business.</p>

<p>Learning math starts with with memorization. As we advance, we eventually absorb enough to apply what we&rsquo;ve learned in creative ways.</p>

<h3>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy, Summarized</h3>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy can be summarized (from <em>lowest</em> level to <em>highest</em>) as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Remembering</strong> (<em>Lowest Level</em>) &ndash; All learning starts with memorization. For example, before we can learn how to read and write the English language, we need to memorize the English alphabet.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Understanding</strong> &ndash;  After we memorize the alphabet, we need to understand how the letters come together to form words.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Applying</strong> &ndash;  Can we combine words in different ways to form sentences and express thoughts?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Analyzing</strong> &ndash;  Spotting differences. Comparing and contrasting. For example, can we take something written by others and express it in our own words while maintaining accuracy?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Evaluating</strong> &ndash;  Arguing and appraising. Having completed an analysis, can we justify our conclusions?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Creating</strong> (<em>Highest Level</em>) &ndash;  Having achieved at the previous levels, can we move the body of knowledge forward? Can we express entirely new points of view?</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>More Resources</h3>

<p>Google lists <a href="https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;ion=1&amp;espv=2&amp;ie=UTF-8#q=bloom%27s%20taxonomy">tons of articles on Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy</a> if you would like to know more.</p>

<h3>Attribution Note</h3>

<p>The graphic at the top of this post is from an Oregon State University web site. The original author was not cited. If you know who the original author is, please <a href="http://RayHightower.com/contact">share the info</a> so that a proper citation can be included here. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using rlwrap with MIT's Scheme REPL]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/19/using-rlwrap-with-mit-scheme-repl/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-19T17:02:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/19/using-rlwrap-with-mit-scheme-repl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Users of the Linux or OS X command line know that they can hit the up arrow to view the previously executed command. However, this behavior is missing from the <code>mit-scheme</code> read-evaluate-print-loop (REPL). <code>mit-scheme</code> is the language used in <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group/">SICP</a>.</p>

<p>For example, hitting the up arrow in the Scheme REPL gives us this non-useful result: <code>^[[A</code>. The previous command is not repeated.</p>

<p>How do we add up-arrow functionality to the <code>mit-scheme</code> REPL? By using <code>rlwrap</code>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Installing rlwrap</h3>

<p>On Mac OS X with <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/12/homebrew-fundamentals/">Homebrew</a>, first update Homebrew with <code>$ brew update</code>.</p>

<p>Then install <code>rlwrap</code>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>brew install <span class="nv">rlwrap</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Downloading https://homebrew.bintray.com/bottles/rlwrap-0.42.yosemite.bottle.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'><span class="c">######################################################################## 100.0%</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">==</span>&gt; Pouring rlwrap-0.42.yosemite.bottle.tar.gz
</span><span class='line'>🍺  /usr/local/Cellar/rlwrap/0.42: 29 files, 312K
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You can verify the <code>rlwrap</code> installation as follows.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>which rlwrap
</span><span class='line'>/usr/local/bin/rlwrap
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Using rlwrap</h3>

<p>To use <code>rlwrap</code> with <code>scheme</code> do the following.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>rlwrap scheme
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Add an Alias to ~/.bash_profile</h3>

<p>To speed things up a bit, we can add an <code>alias</code> to <code>~/.bash_profile</code>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="c"># for rlwrap &amp; scheme support. Details: http://rayhightower.com/blog/2015/03/19/using-rlwrap-with-mit-scheme-repl/</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">alias </span><span class="nv">sicp</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s1">&#39;rlwrap scheme&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>So now when we type <code>sicp</code> at the command line&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sicp
</span><span class='line'>MIT/GNU Scheme running under OS X
</span><span class='line'>Type <span class="sb">`</span>^C<span class="s1">&#39; (control-C) followed by `H&#39;</span> to obtain information about interrupts.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Copyright <span class="o">(</span>C<span class="o">)</span> 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
</span><span class='line'>This is free software<span class="p">;</span> see the <span class="nb">source </span><span class="k">for </span>copying conditions. There is NO warranty<span class="p">;</span> not even <span class="k">for </span>MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
</span><span class='line'>  Release 9.2 <span class="o">||</span> Microcode 15.3 <span class="o">||</span> Runtime 15.7 <span class="o">||</span> SF 4.41 <span class="o">||</span> LIAR/x86-64 4.118 <span class="o">||</span> Edwin 3.116
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>1 <span class="o">]=</span>&gt;
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Exactly what we expect.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>And now we have it. The up-arrow behavior that we enjoy at the command line is now in the Scheme REPL. Big savings in time, and better for learning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apple Car? Not Likely.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/12/apple-car-not-likely/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-12T16:42:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/12/apple-car-not-likely</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>You have to figure out what your own aptitudes are. If you play games where other people have the aptitudes and you don’t, you’re going to lose. And that’s as close to certain as any prediction that you can make. You have to figure out where you’ve got an edge. And you’ve got to play within your own circle of competence.
<br/>~Charlie Munger, Vice Chairman, Berkshire Hathaway</p></blockquote>

<p>Some journalists speculate that <a href="http://9to5mac.com/2015/02/19/apple-electric-car-team/">Apple is building a car</a> because they recently hired some automotive engineers away from Tesla. My prediction: Apple is <em>not</em> building a car. Apple might build a device that plays a major role in the automotive marketplace. But a fully assembled automobile is too far outside the company&rsquo;s <em>circle of competence</em>, as Charlie Munger might say. Apple succeeds because the company maintains disciplined focus within its circle of competence.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>AppleTV as an Example</h3>

<p>Case in point: AppleTV. Pundits predicted an AppleTV with a large LCD display, in a form factor that might be built by Samsung or Sony. But instead, Apple created a black set-top box about the size of a hockey puck. Apple focused on those parts of the television ecosystem that are most closely tied to their circle of competence:</p>

<ul>
<li>User experience</li>
<li>Internet connectivity</li>
<li>Content delivery</li>
</ul>


<p>Apple entered the television marketplace while remaining within its circle of competence. Even better: Content delivery is a cash flow engine that generates revenue for as long as Apple can push bits down the wire.</p>

<h3>iPhone Example</h3>

<p>When Apple entered the mobile phone market, they focused within their circle of competence.</p>

<ul>
<li>User experience for computing devices, using a subset of Mac OS X.</li>
<li>Internet connectivity via WiFi.</li>
<li>Content delivery (iTunes).</li>
</ul>


<p>In the area where Apple lacked experience, mobile network management, they partnered with an industry veteran (initially AT&amp;T). By focusing within its circle of competence, Apple was able to negotiate aggressive terms with AT&amp;T, terms which included <em>no carrier branding on the physical device</em>. Later, Verizon, T-Mobile, Sprint, and all of the other major players begged for the same deal as AT&amp;T.</p>

<p>And, as with AppleTV, content delivery is an engine that prints money for as long as Apple can push bits over the radio waves.</p>

<h3>Apple&rsquo;s Automotive Entry</h3>

<p>Apple will not build a fully assembled automobile. They&rsquo;re more likely to create an auto-related device that leverages their existing circle of competence. Something that shows off their skills with user experience, Internet connectivity, and content delivery.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s automotive content delivery offering will be interesting. The company currently offers maps and directions. What&rsquo;s next&hellip; maintenance data? Entertainment? How about a &ldquo;find my car&rdquo; serivce for those of us who forget where we park at the shopping mall.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s automotive device will fit well within the company&rsquo;s circle of competence. And Apple fans will line up around the block to buy it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTML5 & CSS3: The Complete Manual]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/06/html5-and-css3-the-complete-manual/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T13:02:53-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/06/html5-and-css3-the-complete-manual</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/html5_css3_imagineshop.jpg' width='' height='' alt='HTML5 & CSS3' title='HTML5 & CSS3'><span class='caption-text'>HTML5 &amp; CSS3</span></span>
The biggest challenge for a software developer: Absorbing the latest knowledge while simultaneously keeping clients happy. Where does the time go?</p>

<p>Fortunately, when it comes to HTML5 and CSS3, a UK-based publisher has released a just-the-facts guide that may help. At 127 pages, the entire publication (they call it a <em>bookazine</em>) can be devoured in a single day. Imagine Publishing&rsquo;s <em>HTML5 &amp; CSS3: The Complete Manual</em> is well worth the time investment.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this article also appears in the <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org/book-reviews/archives/2015/03/06/html5-css3-the-complete-manual/">Book Reviews section of ChicagoRuby.org</a></em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>This Book&rsquo;s Best Feature</h3>

<p>One thing I like about this book: Nothing is assumed. All explanations are clearly presented from square one. The introduction even defines the terms <em>hypertext</em> and <em>responsive design</em> in words that could easily be hijacked for your next presentation to non-technical management.</p>

<p>Personally, I appreciate the don&rsquo;t-assume-anything definitions. I completed all of my formal computer science training in the last century, before we knew how far this Internet thing might go. Books like this help to fill in the gaps. Well done, authors!</p>

<h3>Working the Examples</h3>

<p>If you’re already current on HTML &amp; CSS, the examples in the beginning of the book will be too easy for you. Skip ahead to the examples toward the end and work on those. The sections on responsive design, <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap</a>, and <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Foundation</a> are especially useful.</p>

<h3>Spelling Differences</h3>

<p>My British-speaking friends and I sometimes tease each other about variations in American vs UK spelling for certain words. &ldquo;Colour&rdquo; vs &ldquo;color&rdquo; and that sort of thing. This book uses UK conventions.</p>

<p>I spotted a fair number of typos in the book&rsquo;s code examples. Typos in human-readable text are no big deal. But a missing <code>&gt;</code> or <code>=</code> in a book about HTML and CSS can make or break an example. Of course, we’re all human and typos are simply a fact of life.</p>

<p>Suggestion for the publishers: Setup a <a href="http://github.com">GitHub</a> repo with the code samples. That way, if typos in code are discovered (always certain because we&rsquo;re human) the typos can be corrected and shared immediately.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>The bottom line: <em>HTML5 &amp; CSS3: The Complete Manual</em> is worth reading, especially if you need a quick way to keep up with web trends.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JRuby 9000 on Mac OS X]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/03/jruby-9000-on-mac-os-x/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T14:42:57-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/03/jruby-9000-on-mac-os-x</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/jruby_on_jvm.png' width='' height='' alt='JRuby. Ruby on the JVM.' title='JRuby. Ruby on the JVM.'><span class='caption-text'>JRuby. Ruby on the JVM.</span></span>
Moore’s Law is about to run into a wall. Therefore, anything that software developers can learn about concurrency will be critical in coming years. Enter <a href="http://www.jruby.org/">JRuby 9000</a>.</p>

<h3>What is JRuby?</h3>

<p>JRuby is an implementation of the Ruby programming language that runs on the Java virtual machine (JVM). Advantages of running on the JVM include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reaping the performance benefits that come from decades of JVM tuning.</li>
<li>The ability to call time-tested Java libraries from Ruby programs.</li>
<li>The performance benefits that come from concurrency, built into the JVM.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h3>Installing JRuby 9000 on OS X</h3>

<p>Grab the latest <code>.tar</code> file from <a href="http://jruby.org/download">JRuby Downloads</a> and extract it by double-clicking on it. As of this writing, the latest version was <code>jruby-bin-9.0.0.0.pre1.tar.gz</code>.</p>

<p>Next, move the extracted files to <code>/opt/jruby/</code>. For example, if you downloaded the <code>.tar</code> file to your <code>~/Downloads</code> directory, this command will rename the extracted directory to <code>jruby/</code> in the process.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo mv ~/Downloads/jruby-9.0.0.0.pre1/ /opt/jruby/
</span><span class='line'>Password:
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And finally, add the following line to <code>~/.bash_profile</code> (or where ever you choose to set your <code>$PATH</code> variable).</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nb">export </span><span class="nv">PATH</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">&quot;/opt/jruby/bin:$PATH&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Testing the JRuby 9000 installation</h3>

<p>To test the JRuby 9000 installation, re-start your terminal or use <code>$ source ~/.bash_profile</code>. And then</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>jruby --version
</span><span class='line'>jruby 9.0.0.0.pre1 <span class="o">(</span>2.2.0p0<span class="o">)</span> 2015-01-20 d537cab Java HotSpot<span class="o">(</span>TM<span class="o">)</span> 64-Bit Server VM 25.25-b02 on 1.8.0_25-b17 +jit <span class="o">[</span>darwin-x86_64<span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>which jruby
</span><span class='line'>/opt/jruby/bin/jruby
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Why not RVM?</h3>

<p>Given that <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/05/16/upgrading-ruby-with-rvm/">I like RVM</a>, why didn’t I simply use RVM to install JRuby 9000? Answer: The instructions for installing <em>a pre-release version</em> of JRuby via RVM were unclear to me. Extracting the executables and adding the directory to the <code>$PATH</code> was more grok-able. If your experience is different from mine, feel free to share in the comments below.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>Next steps include experiments with concurrency. JRuby concurrency experiments with the <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/07/parallella-quick-start-guide-with-gotchas/">18-core Parallella</a> look especially interesting. More to come.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi 2 Model B Quad Core]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/27/raspberry-pi-2-model-b-quad-core/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-27T21:04:11-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/27/raspberry-pi-2-model-b-quad-core</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/raspberry_pi_2_model_b.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Raspberry Pi 2 Model B' title='Raspberry Pi 2 Model B'><span class='caption-text'>Raspberry Pi 2 Model B</span></span>
The <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/">Raspberry Pi Foundation</a> has upped their entry in the single-board computer competition. Raspberry Pi 2 Model B boasts a quad core ARM CPU and 1GB of RAM. More important: Benchmarks show that the board is 6x faster than the previous model. And the performance bump has been achieved while the price remains low: Roughly $45.</p>

<p>Getting the board up and running is easier, too. You can buy a pre-built Linux image on micro SD. Or you can <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/">download the New Out Of the Box (NOOBS) image</a> yourself. Depending on the speed of your internet connection, you can be up in running in less than an hour.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Easier Than Before</h3>

<p>Special note about the NOOBS image: You don&rsquo;t need a special utility to burn an SD card like before. The steps are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Download the <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/">NOOBS image</a> and unzip it.</li>
<li>Format a micro SD card that&rsquo;s at lease 4GB in size.</li>
<li>Drag the unzipped NOOBS files to the micro SD card.</li>
<li>Insert the micro SD card into the Raspeberry Pi, apply power, and watch it boot.</li>
</ul>


<p>Having done things <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">the old way</a>, I was surprised that the process was so simple this time. Hats off to the Raspberry Pi Foundation for a great installation experience.</p>

<h3>Login Information</h3>

<p>After the device boots, you will need login credentials. These have not changed from the previous version:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>raspberripi login: pi
</span><span class='line'>Password: raspberry
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Note that the cursor will not move while you type the password.</p>

<p>Next, start the X Window environment.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>startx
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And your desktop will look something like this.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/raspberry_pi_2_model_b_ruby.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Screenshot: Raspberry Pi 2 Model B' title='Screenshot: Raspberry Pi 2 Model B'><span class='caption-text'>Screenshot: Raspberry Pi 2 Model B</span></span></p>

<h3>Running Ruby, Rails</h3>

<p>This incarnation of Raspberry Pi comes with Ruby 1.9.3 pre-installed. Of course, if you want to manage multiple versions of Ruby, <a href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/05/16/upgrading-ruby-with-rvm/">RVM is a great way to go</a>.</p>

<p>To install RVM, first run <code>gpg</code> to verify that you will get an uncorrupted (or un-tampored with) version of RVM.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>gpg --keyserver hkp://keys.gnupg.net --recv-keys 409B6B1796C275462A1703113804BB82D39DC0E3
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Next, install RVM.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="se">\c</span>url -sSL https://get.rvm.io <span class="p">|</span> bash -s stable
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And finally, let the current terminal session know that RVM is installed
by typing the following at the command line.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span><span class="nb">source</span> /home/pi/.rvm/scripts/rvm
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You can verify that RVM is installed by checking its version number like so&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>rvm --version
</span><span class='line'>rvm 1.26.10 <span class="o">(</span>master<span class="o">)</span> by Wayne E. Seguin &lt;wayneeseguin@gmail.com&gt;, Michal Papis &lt;mpapis@gmail.com&gt; <span class="o">[</span>https://rvm.io/<span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Installing Ruby Versions</h3>

<p>To install the latest stable version of Ruby&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>rvm install ruby
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>RVM will download dependencies as part of the installation process. From there, you can create RVM gemsets and <code>gem install rails</code> or any other libraries you may need. More documentation can be found at <a href="http://rvm.io">http://rvm.io</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep the Fun in Computing]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T20:12:17-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;I think that it’s extraordinarily important that we in computer science keep fun in computing&hellip; What’s in your hands, I think and hope, is intelligence: the ability to see the machine as more than when you were first led up to it, that you can make it more.&rdquo;
<br/>&nbsp;
~ Alan J. Perlis,
from the Dedication page in SICP</p></blockquote>

<p>Enrolling in the <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Chicago SICP study group</a>, I expected to dive into Lisp. I expected to be challenged. What I didn’t expect: The fun, somewhat irreverent attitude of the SICP authors. And why not? Software development is one of our newest professions. Other professionals are made more effective through our work. Everybody benefits from the increase in productivity.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>If you are a software developer in the Chicago area, be sure to check out <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">the SICP group</a>. As the SICP authors say, you don’t need to know Lisp to embark on this path; you’ll learn Lisp as we travel along. And our brains will be stretched in new and interesting ways.</p>

<p>What an exciting time to be alive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SICP Study Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-18T15:15:25-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/sicp.jpg' width='' height='' alt='SICP' title='SICP'><span class='caption-text'>SICP</span></span>
Veteran developer <a href="http://twitter.com/dastels">Dave Astels</a> is leading a <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs (SICP) study group</a> for the next ten months. The Massachusetts Institute of Technology uses SICP as the text for one of its early computer science courses. Session one of Dave’s group starts today at 6pm. For any developer who wants to ramp up in skill, the SICP study group is an excellent opportunity to do so.</p>

<p>MIT makes the <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">entire text of SICP</a> available online for free. Or you can buy a paper version of the book at Amazon.</p>

<p>Thank you <a href="http://www.bradsdeals.com/">Brad’s Deals</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/lostghost">Ken Walters</a> for hosting the SICP group.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Installing Scheme on Mac OS X</h3>

<p>Examples and exercises in SICP are written in Scheme, a dialect of the LISP programming language. As of this writing, installing <code>mit-scheme</code> via Homebrew <em>did not work for me</em>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>~<span class="nv">$ </span>brew install mit-scheme
</span><span class='line'>Error: No available formula <span class="k">for </span>mit-scheme
</span><span class='line'>Searching formulae...
</span><span class='line'>Searching taps...
</span><span class='line'>homebrew/x11/mit-scheme
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>~<span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><em>Update: Some members of the SICP study group had success installing <code>mit-scheme</code> with Homebrew, while others (like me) did not. We did not determine why some of the Homebrew installations were successful. However, the non-Homebrew method described in this article seems to work across-the-board.</em></p>

<p>Alternative solution: Grab a pre-compiled binary from the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/mit-scheme/">MIT/GNU Scheme</a> site. The <code>mit-scheme-9.2-x86-64.dmg</code> disk image was the right one for my early 2013 MacBook Pro. Your system may be different.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/gnu_float.png' width='' height='' alt='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.' title='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.'><span class='caption-text'>Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.</span></span></p>

<p>To install, drag the <code>MIT/GNU Scheme.app</code> icon into the Applications folder on the Mac.</p>

<h3>Setting Up Symlinks</h3>

<p>Scheme is run from the command line. In order to make that work, we need to setup two symbolic links.</p>

<p>First, create a symbolic link called <code>mit-scheme-x86-64</code> in your home directory that links to the appropriate executable in the <code>/Applications</code> directory. In other words&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo ln -s /Applications/MIT<span class="se">\:</span>GNU<span class="se">\ </span>Scheme.app/Contents/Resources /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64
</span><span class='line'>Password:
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Next, setup a symlink that will let us simply type <code>scheme</code> when we want to use this version of the language&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo ln -s /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64/mit-scheme /usr/bin/scheme
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Confirm that the links are in place by checking the <code>scheme</code> version number.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>scheme --version
</span><span class='line'>MIT/GNU Scheme microcode 15.3
</span><span class='line'>Copyright <span class="o">(</span>C<span class="o">)</span> 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
</span><span class='line'>This is free software<span class="p">;</span> see the <span class="nb">source </span><span class="k">for </span>copying conditions. There is NO warranty<span class="p">;</span> not even <span class="k">for</span>
</span><span class='line'>MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
</span><span class='line'>  Release 9.2 <span class="o">||</span> Microcode 15.3 <span class="o">||</span> Runtime 15.7 <span class="o">||</span> SF 4.41 <span class="o">||</span> LIAR/x86-64 4.118 <span class="o">||</span> Edwin 3.116
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Moriturus te saluto.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If you are like me, you will laugh at the gladiator message at the end of the version info.</p>

<h3>Better Way to Symlink?</h3>

<p>Why not create a single symbolic link directly from the <code>Resources</code> directory to the <code>scheme</code> command in <code>/usr/bin</code>? I am not certain, but I suspect it has something to do with expectations within the Scheme interpreter. The interpreter may be expecting certain files to be in certain directories. I’ll update this article when I learn more.</p>

<h3>Running Scheme</h3>

<p>To start the Scheme read-evaluate-print-loop (REPL)&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>scheme
</span><span class='line'>MIT/GNU Scheme running under OS X
</span><span class='line'>Type <span class="sb">`</span>^C<span class="s1">&#39; (control-C) followed by `H&#39;</span> to obtain information about interrupts.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Copyright <span class="o">(</span>C<span class="o">)</span> 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
</span><span class='line'>This is free software<span class="p">;</span> see the <span class="nb">source </span><span class="k">for </span>copying conditions. There is NO warranty<span class="p">;</span> not even <span class="k">for</span>
</span><span class='line'>MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
</span><span class='line'>  Release 9.2 <span class="o">||</span> Microcode 15.3 <span class="o">||</span> Runtime 15.7 <span class="o">||</span> SF 4.41 <span class="o">||</span> LIAR/x86-64 4.118 <span class="o">||</span> Edwin 3.116
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>1 <span class="o">]=</span>&gt;
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Exit the REPL by typing <code>CTRL-D</code>.</p>

<p>Looking forward to SICP tonight!</p>

<h3>Acknowledgement</h3>

<p>Thanks <a href="https://jacksonisaac.wordpress.com/2014/03/25/installing-scheme-on-mac-os-x/">Jackson Isaac</a> for the information about symlinks as used with this version of scheme.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WindyCityRails and You]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/31/windycityrails-and-you/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T06:11:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/31/windycityrails-and-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have ever attended <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>: Thank you for helping to make the event more exciting every year. Organizers strive to give developers actionable technical information in a conference format. So far, it&rsquo;s working!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>2015 marks our first year with a pre-conference survey. Length: Four questions. Answer as many as you like via the quick <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/XHF85YN">online form</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li>What web-related technologies are you most excited about this year?</li>
<li>What web-related technology is giving you the biggest headaches right now?</li>
<li>Are there any particular speakers you&rsquo;d like to see at WindyCityRails 2015?</li>
<li>What social networks do you actively use?</li>
</ol>


<p>Please <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/XHF85YN">stop by and fill out the survey</a> when you can.</p>

<p>We look forward to hearing from you. And we look forward to delivering another strong year at WindyCityRails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Context Changes Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T17:48:08-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some cases where time zone information is absolutely critical. For example: When scheduling a video conference that crosses national boundaries.</p>

<p>A few hours ago, Google sent me a reminder about today&rsquo;s <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> meeting. The group meets via video conferencing software over the web. Google&rsquo;s reminder was confusing because it showed the time without the time zone (screenshot below). LinuxBarbados is based in the Caribbean, and some of the members participate from other time zones.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/GH_time_zone_arrow.png' width='' height='' alt='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?' title='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?'><span class='caption-text'>What time is it when the time zone is unknown?</span></span></p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s automated reminder said <code>3pm - 4pm</code> with no time zone reference. How confusing! Members of the group received the same automated reminder with the same information, regardless of time zone. A small change, displaying the time as <code>3pm - 4pm (CST)</code> would solve the problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Other Context Examples</h3>

<p>When people speak with each other directly, context is implied. But when communication happens in printed form, it&rsquo;s helpful to have the context in print, too. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Walking down the street, you see a poster advertising a concert on January 29th. No year is shown. Is this an old poster for a concert that happened last year on Jan 29th? Or is the event happening next week?</li>
<li>A restaurant menu offers delivery service. Just call the number, and order your food. The phone number is seven digits long, with no area code. Most customers would abandon the menu in favor of a restaurant with more complete information.</li>
<li>Following the train of thought in the previous example: Since phone service has fallen in price, many people call internationally on a more regular basis. A complete phone number should include the country code.</li>
</ul>


<p>Context changes everything. Something all of us need to remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicago Node.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/20/chicago-node-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-20T17:23:30-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/20/chicago-node-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='http://RayHightower.com/images/openrov_at_groupon.png' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.' title='OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.</span></span>
The <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Chicago-Nodejs/events/203711262/">Chicago Node.js</a> user group invited me to present <em>Node.js Under Water</em>, an overview of the <a href="http://openrov.com">OpenROV</a> underwater robot, this evening. Slides appear below.</p>

<p>Every version of this talk is tailored to the audience. This version focuses on OpenROV hardware components since this group certainly knows Node.js. Information has been added on hardware gotchas and tether management.</p>

<p>Thank you Chicago Node.js organizers and members for having me.</p>

<!--more-->




<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="b51c86f083270132a7cc1ade27531f87" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Windows. Stronger Planes.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/02/no-windows-stronger-planes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T23:34:04-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/02/no-windows-stronger-planes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is always good to start the new year with something inspirational. <a href="http://www.technicondesign.com/">Technicon Design</a> created a 3-minute video to demonstrate their IXION Windowless Jet Concept. Worth watching full screen.</p>

<center><iframe name="windowlessjet" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/78458486" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<p>How can a plane with no windows offer better views for passengers?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Windows vs Fuselage Strength</h3>

<p>When we add a window to the fuselage of an airplane, we reduce the strength of the fuselage. Glass is weaker than aluminum. So aircraft engineers need to make up for the lost strength. The engineers might add a support structure, thicken the aluminum, or try a different alloy.</p>

<p>But when windows are eliminated, structural integrity is maintained. And the weight of the plane can be reduced because we can eliminate the extra supports.</p>

<h3>How Do We See Without Windows</h3>

<p>As shown in the Technicon video, views can be better without windows!  Cameras are mounted at strategic points on the outside of the plane. And the inner surface of the plane, the part that passengers can see, is covered with a display material. Computers take the images captured by the external cameras, and they translate that into images for display on the inner walls of the plane.</p>

<p>The result: Passengers feel like they&rsquo;re flying in a glass plane. That&rsquo;s an idea best communicated through the Technicon video.</p>

<h3>Applying Tech Across Industries</h3>

<p>Processing power continues to fall in price. Flat panel monitors get less expensive each day. The window-less plane shows us what can happen when advances in one industry are applied to another. Blend these advances with a high-speed internet connection delivered via satellite, and the Internet of Things (IoT) takes a great leap forward. Cross-discipline engineering is exciting.</p>

<p>Happy New Year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Looking Inside the Pygments Plugin]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/31/looking-inside-pygments/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-31T16:18:29-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/31/looking-inside-pygments</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog uses <a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/pygments.rb">pygments.rb</a> for syntax highlighting. Recently <code>pygments.rb</code> stopped working, so I had to dig inside to determine the problem and apply a solution.</p>

<p>Full disclosure: Pygments didn&rsquo;t simply stop working. I applied updates related to Octopress and Lunr.js, and then it stopped working. So the root cause is me! Rather than back-out the updates, I decided to push forward because Lunr.js will improve the search experience for visitors. Search options will be discussed in a future post.</p>

<h3>Starting With the Error Message</h3>

<p>As with all <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> based blogs, the <code>$ rake generate</code> command creates a new set of static pages every time the command gets run. Normally the process is smooth. Here&rsquo;s the error message that resulted this morning.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>~<span class="nv">$ </span>rake generate
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>...
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>jekyll 2.0.3 <span class="p">|</span> Error:  Pygments can<span class="err">&#39;</span>t parse unknown language: &lt;/p&gt;.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>What unknown language? Something was fishy. Fortunately, <code>pygments</code> is an open source plugin. Solving the problem was non-trivial, but doable.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Exploring Pygments Internals</h3>

<p>Google, Stack Overflow, and the Octopress documentation gave clues on where to explore. Adding a few lines to <code>source/plugins/pygments_code.rb</code> provided insights on what <code>pygments</code> was &ldquo;thinking&rdquo;.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="nb">require</span> <span class="s1">&#39;pygments&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">require</span> <span class="s1">&#39;fileutils&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">require</span> <span class="s1">&#39;digest/md5&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="no">PYGMENTS_CACHE_DIR</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">File</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">expand_path</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;../../.pygments-cache&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="bp">__FILE__</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="no">FileUtils</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">mkdir_p</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="no">PYGMENTS_CACHE_DIR</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">module</span> <span class="nn">HighlightCode</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nc">self</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="nf">highlight</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">str</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">lang</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># Next three lines let us see what pygments &quot;thinks&quot;.</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">print</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="se">\n\n</span><span class="s2">rth_str = </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">str</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">print</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s2">rth_lang = </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="n">lang</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">print</span> <span class="s2">&quot;</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="s2">rth_file = </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="bp">__FILE__</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="se">\n\n</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">.</span><span class="n">.</span><span class="o">.</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Observing the Results, Applying a Solution</h3>

<p>Next step: Run <code>$ rake generate</code> and see what happens. Turns out that the lastest version of <code>pygments</code> halted for two reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Some of my older blog posts did not contain a space between the triple-backtick characters and the name of the language being highlighted. Earlier versions of <code>pygments</code> did not care, but the current version is a stickler.</li>
<li><code>pygments</code> appears to want a blank line between any triple-backtick line and any other text in the blog post.</li>
</ul>


<p>Vim-fu allowed me to apply solutions with minimal manual work. And now <code>pygments</code> works well.</p>

<p>On to search, to be discussed in a future blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
