<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: BeagleBone Black | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/beaglebone-black/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-22T08:10:42-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Portable Hack for Parallella]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/10/a-portable-hack-for-parallella/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-10T23:05:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/10/a-portable-hack-for-parallella</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper left'><img class='caption' src='/images/parallella-portable.png' width='' height='' alt='Portability for Parallella-sized devices.' title='Portability for Parallella-sized devices.'><span class='caption-text'>Portability for Parallella-sized devices.</span></span>
<a href="/blog/2013/05/22/beaglebone-black-running-ruby-on-rails/">Beaglebone Black</a>, <a href="/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">Raspberry Pi</a>, and <a href="/blog/2013/06/22/preparing-for-parallella-64-cores-installing-go-on-mac-os-x/">Parallella</a> are three small, powerful Linux-based computers. But in order to make these devices truly portable, we need a way to carry a monitor and keyboard along. This article describes one hack that works.</p>

<h3>Inspiration in a Suitcase</h3>

<p>The HP 5036 Microprocessor Lab gave me my first exposure to assembler language. I was eighteen, working my first software internship, and loving every minute of it. When I devised ways to complete my <em>regular work</em> faster than management expected, I had some time on my hands. So I spent time learning assembler with the HP 5036.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/hp-5036.png' width='' height='' alt='HP 5036 Microprocessor Lab' title='HP 5036 Microprocessor Lab'><span class='caption-text'>HP 5036 Microprocessor Lab</span></span></p>

<p>The entire 5036 fits in a suitcase&hellip; how cool is that! Here&rsquo;s how the 5036 works:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start by writing assembler-level code by hand on paper.</li>
<li>Grab the reference book for the microprocessor running on the
board, Intel 8080.</li>
<li>For each assembler-level command, find the corresponding 2-digit
hexidecimal operation code.</li>
<li>Key the op code into the 5036 by hand.</li>
<li>Run the program.</li>
</ol>


<p>Working with the 5036 was addictive in a positive way. In a subsequent job, where I wrote assembler to drive hardware devices, I was ready.</p>

<h3>Portability Needed</h3>

<p>Fast forward a few decades. We now have the Raspberry Pi, BeagleBone Black, and Parallella. Wonderful devices with one flaw in common: No portability. That&rsquo;s when I had a flashback to my days with the 5036.</p>

<p>I bought a $35 technician box from Home Depot and I ripped out the insides. Micro Center had 720p LCD monitors on sale for $90, so I bought one of those. I didn&rsquo;t want to spend the extra bucks for a 1080p LCD because you never know how something like this might work out! Finally, I topped everything off with a $25 keyboard/trackpad combo from Amazon.  The result appears in the photo at the top of this article.</p>

<h3>Why?</h3>

<p>Why did I spend the time and money to assemble this kit? It&rsquo;s all about learning. Devs learn more when we interact with other devs &ndash; people who are learning some of the same things that we&rsquo;re wrestling with. And sometimes the things we need to learn are too new for books.</p>

<p>By carrying my Raspberry Pi, BeagleBone Black, and Parallella with me in a portable unit, I can share my experiences with other devs and learn more in the process. Everybody wins when that happens.</p>

<h3>Thanks SCNA!</h3>

<p>The organizers of <a href="http://scna.softwarecraftsmanship.org/">Software Craftsmanship North America (SCNA)</a> gave me the opportunity to present this story as a lightning talk at the conference. Slides are here:</p>

<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="b3558fd02cac0131cfc62a9baba32394" data-ratio="1.29456384323641" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>Thank you SCNA! As I shared with the other devs at SCNA, I will gladly post my mistakes and <em>gotchas</em> here for people who want to build a unit like this. Let&rsquo;s build!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PechaKucha: Developer Education at TableXI]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/06/27/pechakucha-developer-education-at-tablexi/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T15:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/06/27/pechakucha-developer-education-at-tablexi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://pechakucha.org">PechaKucha</a> is a concise presentation style developed in Japan. The PechaKucha format is 20x20: The presenter must share an idea in twenty slides, each displayed for exactly twenty seconds, advancing automatically. Total presentation time = six minutues, forty seconds.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.tablexi.com/blog/2013/06/practice-begins-with-play-a-table-talk/developers/">TableXI</a> hosted a PechaKucha on June 13th with the theme <em>Developer Education</em>. I was one of six presenters invited to speak. Video:</p>

<center><iframe width='460' height='345' src="http://www.pechakucha.org/presentations/51b92936dbdd200cbc000011/embed" frameborder="0"></iframe></center>


<p>One highlight from the PechaKucha presentation: This year&rsquo;s <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> will include a youth program on Thursday afternoon. Details will be announced in July. Follow <a href="http://twitter.com/windycityrails">@WindyCityRails</a> for the latest news on the program.</p>

<p>Thanks TableXI for the PechaKucha invitation, and for sponsoring WindyCityRails 2013!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BeagleBone Black, Up & Running]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/05/22/beaglebone-black-running-ruby-on-rails/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T22:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/05/22/beaglebone-black-running-ruby-on-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/BeagleBoneBlack.jpg" width="372" height="600" title="BeagleBone Black" alt="BeagleBone Black" align="right">
<a href="http://beagleboard.org/Products/BeagleBone%20Black">BeagleBone Black</a>, like the <a href="/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">Raspberry Pi</a>, is a small, inexpensive computer that runs Linux. It&rsquo;s smaller than a deck of cards and you can buy one for about forty-five dollars ($45.00). The device is made by <a href="http://circuitco.com">CircuitCo</a> in Richardson, TX, USA.</p>

<h3>It Just Works</h3>

<p>BeagleBone Black runs Linux right out of the box. Steps required:</p>

<ul>
<li>Plug in the micro-HDMI cable for the monitor. See the &ldquo;Gotchas&rdquo;
section about micro-HDMI below.</li>
<li>Plug in the keyboard &amp; mouse via the USB port. You might need a USB hub because the board only has one USB port.</li>
<li>Add power via the mini-USB port or the 5v power connection.</li>
</ul>


<p>After a few minutes of boot time, we have a fully-functioning Linux computer with a GUI, Firefox browser, and other tools.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The BeagleBone Black has 2GB of flash storage on the board, and part
of that is used for Linux. Here&rsquo;s a screenshot after just a few minutes of ownership.</p>

<center><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/BeagleBoneBlack-WindyCityRails.png" width="600" height="338" title="BeagleBone Black Firefox WindyCityRails" alt="BeagleBone Black Firefox WindyCityRails" align="center"></center>


<h3>Documentation</h3>

<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/BeagleBoneBlack-USB.png" width="250" height="200" title="BeagleBone Black USB" alt="BeagleBone Black USB" align="right">
All of the paper documentation for the BeagleBone Black fits on a slip of paper roughly the size of two business cards. The meat of the documentation resides on the device itself. To reach the electronic documentation:</p>

<ol>
<li>Plug the BeagleBone Black into a USB port on your laptop.</li>
<li>The board will appear as a USB storage device. One of the files at the
root of the storage device, <code>START.htm</code>, contains the documentation. It
can be viewed in a web browser.</li>
</ol>


<p>The documentation recommends against <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Explorer">MSIE</a>.</p>

<h3>Gotchas</h3>

<p><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/micro-HDMI-home-depot.jpg" width="400" height="300" title="Micro HDMI Home Depot" alt="Micro HDMI Home Depot" align="right">
The manufacturer included a mini-USB cable with the device, so you can power it up right after you rip open the package. Gotcha: You need a micro-HDMI cable (or adapter) if you want to attach a monitor. I would have preferred a micro-HDMI-to-HDMI adapater in the box instead of the mini-USB cable. That&rsquo;s a little nit-picky on my part since micro-HDMI cables are easy to find at Home Depot.</p>

<p>A quick shout-out to Home Depot: Their store-brand cables let you test the cable end without opening the package, right in the store. Excellent package design by Home Depot.</p>

<p>My second &ldquo;gotcha&rdquo; is more important: The <code>curl</code> command did not behave as flawlessly as it did with the Raspberry Pi, so I was not able to install Ruby as quickly as planned. Details below.</p>

<h3>Installing Rails</h3>

<p>I will have to cover Ruby and Rails installation in a future blog post because my initial attempts were not successful. <a href="/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">RVM, Ruby, and Rails installed easily with Raspberry Pi</a>, even though the compilation time was long. With the BeagleBone Black, I received the following in response to the <code>curl</code> command:</p>

<p>```bash
sh-4.2# curl -L <a href="https://get.rvm.io">https://get.rvm.io</a> | bash -s stable &mdash;ruby
  % Total    % Received % Xferd  Average Speed   Time    Time     Time  Current</p>

<pre><code>                             Dload  Upload   Total   Spent    Left  Speed
</code></pre>

<p>  0     0    0     0    0     0      0      0 &mdash;:&mdash;:&mdash; &mdash;:&mdash;:&mdash; &mdash;:&mdash;:&mdash;     0
curl: (77) Problem with the SSL CA cert (path? access rights?)
sh-4.2#
```</p>

<p>Maybe it&rsquo;s time to try <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">RBEnv</a>? I&rsquo;ll post a solution when I find it. Or&hellip; if a reader of this blog already has a solution for the BeagleBone Black Rails installation challenge, please post in the comments below and I&rsquo;ll credit you here.</p>

<h4>BeagleBone Black vs. Raspberry Pi</h4>

<p>Which is better, BeagleBone Black or Raspberry Pi? There&rsquo;s no clear winner in my opinion. It&rsquo;s a matter of trade-offs:</p>

<ul>
<li>The &lsquo;Bone runs Linux right out of the box, while it takes some time to get Linux running on the Pi, unless you buy a card pre-configured for the Pi.</li>
<li>RVM, Ruby, and Rails installation was painless on the Pi even though compilation time was long. The jury is still out w/r/t RVM on the &lsquo;Bone.</li>
<li>Cost-wise, they&rsquo;re within ten bucks of each other. That&rsquo;s a wash.</li>
<li>The &lsquo;Bone has more Ardunio-like provisions for digital projects.</li>
<li>The Pi includes an RCA output for older TVs. Plus the Pi uses standard HDMI, so there&rsquo;s no need to get a special micro-HDMI cable.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve owned my &lsquo;Bone for just over 24 hours. Lots more to learn. Looking forward to it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
