<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: education | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/education/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-22T10:01:55-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unleash Your Awesomeness at WindyCityRails]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/02/unleash-your-awesomeness-at-windycityrails/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-02T15:09:06-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/02/unleash-your-awesomeness-at-windycityrails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/sphere_question.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Do you see yourself?' title='Do you see yourself?'><span class='caption-text'>Do you see yourself?</span></span>
Are you driven to excel? Do you see yourself here?</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>You have already built a successful Rails app</strong>. Now that you&rsquo;re &ldquo;done&rdquo;, you know you can make it better, but you&rsquo;re not sure how. You want to take your skills to the next level.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You recently graduated</strong> from <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">Dev Bootcamp</a>, <a href="http://thestarterleague.com">Starter League</a>, <a href="http://www.mobilemakers.co/">Mobile Makers</a> or another school. You&rsquo;re ready to meet and interact with your next generation of mentors.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You are no longer a beginner</strong>. You have seen <em>advanced</em> developers in action, and you are determined to get there yourself.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You are a beginner who learns quickly</strong>. Maybe you&rsquo;re a seasoned professional with a track record in another field. You want to meet people (perhaps mentors?) who can help you accelerate through the beginner phase so you can launch something useful on the web.</p></li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Common thread: It&rsquo;s time to unleash the awesomeness in your bones. You want to take your skills to the next level, and you are ready to tackle <em>Big League Problems</em>. <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> is for you.</p>

<h3>What is a Big League Problem?</h3>

<p>Growth-oriented people view big league problems as <em>good</em> problems. For example, the Rails app you built is pulling in customers, and you&rsquo;re bumping into the limits of your software architecture. Who knew that so many people would buy from you!</p>

<p>Now&hellip; How do you scale? Do you buy more hardware, change your architecture, choose a new platform, or some combination of these? The presenters at this year&rsquo;s WindyCityRails have dealt with scaling problems. Scaling an app, scaling a team, scaling a management structure&hellip; If you expect to encounter challenges, it makes sense to learn from the mistakes (and triumphs) of others. Put their experience to work for you.</p>

<h3>Awesome Speakers. Awesome Audience.</h3>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/">complete list of WindyCityRails speakers</a> and ask yourself what you can learn from each one.</p>

<p>Remember that only 300 WindyCityRails tickets will be sold. Our speakers enjoy interacting with audience members throughout the conference. As professionals, they are always learning, too! So if you want some face time with people who understand Big League Problems (and more importantly, Big League <em>Solutions</em>) WindyCityRails is the place for you to be.</p>

<h3>Get Tickets Now</h3>

<p>Tickets for WindyCityRails always sell fast. <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/register/">Get yours now</a>. We look forward to seeing you at WindyCityRails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bloom's Taxonomy for Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/20/blooms-taxonomy-for-learning/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/20/blooms-taxonomy-for-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://RayHightower.com/images/blooms_taxonomy_thumb.png" onclick="window.open('/images/blooms_taxonomy.png','popup','width=770,height=548,scrollbars=no,resizable=yes,toolbar=no,directories=no,location=no,menubar=no,status=no,left=0,top=0'); return false"><img src="http://RayHightower.com/images/blooms_taxonomy_thumb.png" border="0" alt="Bloom's Taxonomy" name="image" class="right" width="250" height="162" title="Bloom's Taxonomy" /></a></p>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy is a framework that breaks the learning process into stages. According to Bloom, learning begins with rote memorization and the process progresses upward until we can apply what we&rsquo;ve learned in creative new ways.</p>

<h3>Youthful Bias</h3>

<p>Most of my formal education was science or engineering oriented. I regarded science and engineering as the pinnacle of learning. The extreme position of my youth: All logic fell within math and science, while history, language arts, and other non-science areas were just memorization.</p>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s research pushed me beyond my original thinking. Memorization and creativity are vital to all areas of knowledge. Here&rsquo;s how.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Learning Only Starts With Memorization</h3>

<p>All learning, at the very beginning, is memorization. For example, when we first learn mathematics, we start by memorizing the counting numbers (1, 2, 3, &hellip;) and we eventually figure out that we can&rsquo;t count to infinity. Later we learn the four basic math operations (addition, subtraction, multiplication, division) and we learn how to apply these operations to word problems. Fast forward a few years, and we learn to apply differential equations to a skydiver falling to earth via parachute. Or we may create a mathematical spreadsheet model to decide whether to invest in a business.</p>

<p>Learning math starts with with memorization. As we advance, we eventually absorb enough to apply what we&rsquo;ve learned in creative ways.</p>

<h3>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy, Summarized</h3>

<p>Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy can be summarized (from <em>lowest</em> level to <em>highest</em>) as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Remembering</strong> (<em>Lowest Level</em>) &ndash; All learning starts with memorization. For example, before we can learn how to read and write the English language, we need to memorize the English alphabet.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Understanding</strong> &ndash;  After we memorize the alphabet, we need to understand how the letters come together to form words.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Applying</strong> &ndash;  Can we combine words in different ways to form sentences and express thoughts?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Analyzing</strong> &ndash;  Spotting differences. Comparing and contrasting. For example, can we take something written by others and express it in our own words while maintaining accuracy?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Evaluating</strong> &ndash;  Arguing and appraising. Having completed an analysis, can we justify our conclusions?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Creating</strong> (<em>Highest Level</em>) &ndash;  Having achieved at the previous levels, can we move the body of knowledge forward? Can we express entirely new points of view?</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>More Resources</h3>

<p>Google lists <a href="https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;ion=1&amp;espv=2&amp;ie=UTF-8#q=bloom%27s%20taxonomy">tons of articles on Bloom&rsquo;s Taxonomy</a> if you would like to know more.</p>

<h3>Attribution Note</h3>

<p>The graphic at the top of this post is from an Oregon State University web site. The original author was not cited. If you know who the original author is, please <a href="/contact">share the info</a> so that a proper citation can be included here. Thanks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTML5 & CSS3: The Complete Manual]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/06/html5-and-css3-the-complete-manual/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T13:02:53-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/06/html5-and-css3-the-complete-manual</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/html5_css3_imagineshop.jpg' width='' height='' alt='HTML5 &amp; CSS3' title='HTML5 &amp; CSS3'><span class='caption-text'>HTML5 &amp; CSS3</span></span>
The biggest challenge for a software developer: Absorbing the latest knowledge while simultaneously keeping clients happy. Where does the time go?</p>

<p>Fortunately, when it comes to HTML5 and CSS3, a UK-based publisher has released a just-the-facts guide that may help. At 127 pages, the entire publication (they call it a <em>bookazine</em>) can be devoured in a single day. Imagine Publishing&rsquo;s <em>HTML5 &amp; CSS3: The Complete Manual</em> is well worth the time investment.</p>

<p><em>Note: A version of this article also appears in the <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org/book-reviews/archives/2015/03/06/html5-css3-the-complete-manual/">Book Reviews section of ChicagoRuby.org</a></em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>This Book&rsquo;s Best Feature</h3>

<p>One thing I like about this book: Nothing is assumed. All explanations are clearly presented from square one. The introduction even defines the terms <em>hypertext</em> and <em>responsive design</em> in words that could easily be hijacked for your next presentation to non-technical management.</p>

<p>Personally, I appreciate the don&rsquo;t-assume-anything definitions. I completed all of my formal computer science training in the last century, before we knew how far this Internet thing might go. Books like this help to fill in the gaps. Well done, authors!</p>

<h3>Working the Examples</h3>

<p>If you’re already current on HTML &amp; CSS, the examples in the beginning of the book will be too easy for you. Skip ahead to the examples toward the end and work on those. The sections on responsive design, <a href="http://getbootstrap.com/">Bootstrap</a>, and <a href="http://foundation.zurb.com/">Foundation</a> are especially useful.</p>

<h3>Spelling Differences</h3>

<p>My British-speaking friends and I sometimes tease each other about variations in American vs UK spelling for certain words. &ldquo;Colour&rdquo; vs &ldquo;color&rdquo; and that sort of thing. This book uses UK conventions.</p>

<p>I spotted a fair number of typos in the book&rsquo;s code examples. Typos in human-readable text are no big deal. But a missing <code>&gt;</code> or <code>=</code> in a book about HTML and CSS can make or break an example. Of course, we’re all human and typos are simply a fact of life.</p>

<p>Suggestion for the publishers: Setup a <a href="http://github.com">GitHub</a> repo with the code samples. That way, if typos in code are discovered (always certain because we&rsquo;re human) the typos can be corrected and shared immediately.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>The bottom line: <em>HTML5 &amp; CSS3: The Complete Manual</em> is worth reading, especially if you need a quick way to keep up with web trends.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep the Fun in Computing]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T20:12:17-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;I think that it’s extraordinarily important that we in computer science keep fun in computing&hellip; What’s in your hands, I think and hope, is intelligence: the ability to see the machine as more than when you were first led up to it, that you can make it more.&rdquo;
<br/>&nbsp;
~ Alan J. Perlis,
from the Dedication page in SICP</p></blockquote>

<p>Enrolling in the <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Chicago SICP study group</a>, I expected to dive into Lisp. I expected to be challenged. What I didn’t expect: The fun, somewhat irreverent attitude of the SICP authors. And why not? Software development is one of our newest professions. Other professionals are made more effective through our work. Everybody benefits from the increase in productivity.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>If you are a software developer in the Chicago area, be sure to check out <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">the SICP group</a>. As the SICP authors say, you don’t need to know Lisp to embark on this path; you’ll learn Lisp as we travel along. And our brains will be stretched in new and interesting ways.</p>

<p>What an exciting time to be alive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SICP Study Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-18T15:15:25-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/sicp.jpg' width='' height='' alt='SICP' title='SICP'><span class='caption-text'>SICP</span></span>
Veteran developer <a href="http://twitter.com/dastels">Dave Astels</a> is leading a <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs (SICP) study group</a> for the next ten months. The Massachusetts Institute of Technology uses SICP as the text for one of its early computer science courses. Session one of Dave’s group starts today at 6pm. For any developer who wants to ramp up in skill, the SICP study group is an excellent opportunity to do so.</p>

<p>MIT makes the <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">entire text of SICP</a> available online for free. Or you can buy a paper version of the book at Amazon.</p>

<p>Thank you <a href="http://www.bradsdeals.com/">Brad’s Deals</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/lostghost">Ken Walters</a> for hosting the SICP group.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Installing Scheme on Mac OS X</h3>

<p>Examples and exercises in SICP are written in Scheme, a dialect of the LISP programming language. As of this writing, installing <code>mit-scheme</code> via Homebrew <em>did not work for me</em>.</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
~$ brew install mit-scheme
Error: No available formula for mit-scheme
Searching formulae&hellip;
Searching taps&hellip;
homebrew/x11/mit-scheme</p>

<p>~$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p><em>Update: Some members of the SICP study group had success installing <code>mit-scheme</code> with Homebrew, while others (like me) did not. We did not determine why some of the Homebrew installations were successful. However, the non-Homebrew method described in this article seems to work across-the-board.</em></p>

<p>Alternative solution: Grab a pre-compiled binary from the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/mit-scheme/">MIT/GNU Scheme</a> site. The <code>mit-scheme-9.2-x86-64.dmg</code> disk image was the right one for my early 2013 MacBook Pro. Your system may be different.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/gnu_float.png' width='' height='' alt='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.' title='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.'><span class='caption-text'>Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.</span></span></p>

<p>To install, drag the <code>MIT/GNU Scheme.app</code> icon into the Applications folder on the Mac.</p>

<h3>Setting Up Symlinks</h3>

<p>Scheme is run from the command line. In order to make that work, we need to setup two symbolic links.</p>

<p>First, create a symbolic link called <code>mit-scheme-x86-64</code> in your home directory that links to the appropriate executable in the <code>/Applications</code> directory. In other words&hellip;</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ sudo ln -s /Applications/MIT\:GNU\ Scheme.app/Contents/Resources /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64
Password:</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>Next, setup a symlink that will let us simply type <code>scheme</code> when we want to use this version of the language&hellip;</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ sudo ln -s /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64/mit-scheme /usr/bin/scheme</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>Confirm that the links are in place by checking the <code>scheme</code> version number.</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ scheme &mdash;version
MIT/GNU Scheme microcode 15.3
Copyright &copy; 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions. There is NO warranty; not even for
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</p>

<p>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
  Release 9.2 || Microcode 15.3 || Runtime 15.7 || SF 4.41 || LIAR/x86-64 4.118 || Edwin 3.116</p>

<p>Moriturus te saluto.</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>If you are like me, you will laugh at the gladiator message at the end of the version info.</p>

<h3>Better Way to Symlink?</h3>

<p>Why not create a single symbolic link directly from the <code>Resources</code> directory to the <code>scheme</code> command in <code>/usr/bin</code>? I am not certain, but I suspect it has something to do with expectations within the Scheme interpreter. The interpreter may be expecting certain files to be in certain directories. I’ll update this article when I learn more.</p>

<h3>Running Scheme</h3>

<p>To start the Scheme read-evaluate-print-loop (REPL)&hellip;</p>

<p><code>`` bash
$ scheme
MIT/GNU Scheme running under OS X
Type</code>^C&#8217; (control-C) followed by `H&#8217; to obtain information about interrupts.</p>

<p>Copyright &copy; 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions. There is NO warranty; not even for
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</p>

<p>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
  Release 9.2 || Microcode 15.3 || Runtime 15.7 || SF 4.41 || LIAR/x86-64 4.118 || Edwin 3.116</p>

<p>1 ]=></p>

<p><code>``
Exit the REPL by typing</code>CTRL-D`.</p>

<p>Looking forward to SICP tonight!</p>

<h3>Acknowledgement</h3>

<p>Thanks <a href="https://jacksonisaac.wordpress.com/2014/03/25/installing-scheme-on-mac-os-x/">Jackson Isaac</a> for the information about symlinks as used with this version of scheme.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
