<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OpenROV | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/openrov/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-30T18:05:55-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ignite RubyConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T15:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/ignite_logo_200.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.' title='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.'><span class='caption-text'>Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.</span></span>
<a href="http://igniteshow.com/">Ignite</a> is a presentation format where the slides advance automatically every 15 seconds whether the presenter is ready or not. Twenty slides, 15 seconds each, five minutes total. Presenters are challenged to present their ideas quickly and clearly before the time runs out.</p>

<p>Ignite is similar to <a href="http://www.pechakucha.org">Pecha Kucha</a>. The two formats differ only in slide duration (20 seconds per slide with Pecha Kucha).</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.sdruby.org/">SDRuby</a> ran an Ignite event on the day before RubyConf 2014. Slides from my OpenROV presentation at Ignite RubyConf 2014 appear below.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="573c89704e88013264a612c8f4a94aec" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>&nbsp;<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
Thanks SDRuby for hosting the Ignite event!</p>

<p>If you like the idea of hacking on Ruby <em>and</em> OpenROV, check out <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geekfest &amp; OpenROV]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T09:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/geekfest.png' width='' height='' alt='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.' title='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.'><span class='caption-text'>Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.</span></span>
<a href="http://www.meetup.com/Geekfest/events/207936312/">Geekfest</a> is a weekly event hosted by Groupon&rsquo;s engineering team. Every Tuesday at lunchtime, the company invites members of the tech community to present topics that are interesting to a technical audience.</p>

<p>I wish to express my thanks to Groupon for inviting me to present <a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> at today&rsquo;s Geekfest.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Slides appear below. Video will be posted as soon as it becomes available. Special thanks to <a href="http://chelseatroy.com/2014/10/21/geekfest-ray-hightower-dumps-a-robot-into-lake-michigan/">Chelsea Troy</a> for creating a real-time blog post about the presentation.</p>

<center><iframe src="http://RayHightower.com//player.vimeo.com/video/112204897" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>




<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="e8ed21a03b5d013274bd1297e85160ca" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Node.js Under Water]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/25/nodejs-under-water/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T22:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/25/nodejs-under-water</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.meetup.com/nodejs/events/206159562">New York City Node JS Meetup</a> asked me to speak about <a href="http://rayhightower.com/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> on September 24, 2014. About eighty developers came out for the meeting. Thank you <a href="http://shutterstock.com">Shutterstock</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/mateodelnorte">Matt Walters</a>, and all of the organizers for making it happen. Slides appear below.</p>

<!--more-->


<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="25d9158026930132408f62c99fab29cb" data-ratio="1.7777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>&nbsp;
&nbsp;</p>

<h3>Presentation Video</h3>

<p><del>The following video is a rough draft, useful if you want to hear the dialog that went along with the slides.</del> <em>Update: <a href="http://www.hakkalabs.co/articles/openrov-node-js-underwater">Hakka Labs</a> has published the official video from the event, embedded below.</em>  Lots of good questions from the audience.</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/7eUoGtPUKbw?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<p><em>Correction: Maximum OpenROV depth = 100 meters. I gave an incorrect maximum depth figure in the video.</em></p>

<p>&nbsp;
&nbsp;</p>

<h3>Next Step With OpenROV</h3>

<p>Our work with OpenROV will climax at <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a> in January 2015. If you&rsquo;re an intermediate or advanced software developer, and if you like to stretch your brain with Ruby and other languages (like Node.js) then RubyCaribe might be for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RubyCaribe: Ruby Gets Hotter in January]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/23/rubycaribe-ruby-gets-hotter-in-january/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T18:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/23/rubycaribe-ruby-gets-hotter-in-january</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a> (pronounced ka-REEB) is a conference for intermediate and advanced software developers who use Ruby. The conference will be held January 27 &ndash; 31, 2015 in Barbados. January is a beautiful time to visit the Caribbean, especially if you’re coming from a colder part of the planet.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/barbados_caribbean_map.png' width='' height='' alt='Barbados. You could be here in January.' title='Barbados. You could be here in January.'><span class='caption-text'>Barbados. You could be here in January.</span></span>
Intermediate and advanced software developers will find RubyCaribe valuable because&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Each RubyCaribe session features a 30- to 45-minute presentation followed by a <em>2-hour deep-dive lab</em>. Learning is reinforced throughout.</li>
<li>The venue, <a href="http://www.hiltonbarbadosresort.com/">Hilton Barbados Resort</a>, sits right on the ocean. Need a stretch break? Take a walk on the beach!</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<h3>Ramp Up Your Ruby Skills</h3>

<p>Each RubyCaribe lab will be led by experts in machine learning, mobile app development (iOS and Android), web development, and functional programming. The inventor of <a href="http://rubymotion.com">RubyMotion</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/lrz">Laurent Sansonetti</a>, will lead the RubyMotion lab. If you already have experience with Ruby or Rails, RubyCaribe will take your skills to the next level.</p>

<h3>Bonus: OpenROV and Node.js</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_rubycaribe.jpg' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.' title='OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.</span></span>
<a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> is an open source underwater robot running Linux and Node.js. During two evening sessions, you and your RubyCaribe colleagues will hack on OpenROV. The best developers are polyglot, right? On Friday afternoon, we will grab a boat for live ocean testing with a few OpenROV units. If you ever wanted to experiment with Node.js and IoT, RubyCaribe offers a great opportunity.</p>

<h3>University Collaboration</h3>

<p>On Saturday, the final day of RubyCaribe, we will visit the <a href="http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/">University of the West Indies at Cave Hill</a>. Faculty and students from the UWI community will demo their work with solar energy and other areas touched by software. Who knows, maybe you’ll give a lightning talk about something you learned at RubyCaribe!</p>

<h3>Make Your Brain Sweat</h3>

<p>RubyCaribe will work you hard. RubyCaribe will make your brain sweat. So be sure to schedule a few days before or after the conference for sight seeing and relaxation. Rum was invented in Barbados.</p>

<h3>Where Will You Be in January?</h3>

<p>If you had to choose between the Caribbean and the cold regions of the northern hemisphere, where would you rather be? RubyCaribe offers the chance to ramp up your skills and enjoy yourself at the same time. What an opportunity.</p>

<h3>Only One Hundred Tickets</h3>

<p>Only one hundred tickets will be sold. Be sure to get yours. <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/rubycaribe-2015-registration-10051344843">Register now</a>. See you at RubyCaribe!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Manage That OpenROV Tether, Or Else]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/10/manage-that-openrov-tether/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T18:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/10/manage-that-openrov-tether</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_tether_management_slip_ring.jpg' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV tether management, one way that works.' title='OpenROV tether management, one way that works.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV tether management, one way that works.</span></span>
<em>Note: This article has been updated with more photos and details describing slip ring installation.</em></p>

<p>Youthful exuberance drove me to pilot my <a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> before I built a good tether management system. Bad idea! It&rsquo;s better to have a tether management plan (any plan) before you pilot your OpenROV.</p>

<p>This article describes a tether management system that works for me. Other OpenROVers have devices that work, too. Take a look at a few and eventually you will find one that fits you.</p>

<h3>Off-the-Shelf Parts</h3>

<p>This tether management system is constructed entirely from off-the-shelf parts. The main component is an <a href="http://www.homedepot.com/p/KAB-Enterprise-Co-Ltd-20-ft-16-3-Cord-Reel-with-4-Outlets-CR002/100661463">extension cord reel sold by Home Depot</a> for about $14.00. Buy it, gut it, add the slip ring using three screws (also from Home Depot) and you’re good to go.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_lake_michigan.png' width='' height='' alt='Exploring Lake Michigan with OpenROV.' title='Exploring Lake Michigan with OpenROV.'><span class='caption-text'>Exploring Lake Michigan with OpenROV.</span></span></p>

<h3>Slip Ring</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/adafruit_slip_ring.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Adafruit slip ring.' title='Adafruit slip ring.'><span class='caption-text'>Adafruit slip ring.</span></span>
The slip ring is central to this solution. A slip ring allows an electrical spool to spin while electrical contacts remain intact. This slip ring was purchased from <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/products/736?gclid=CJDMiPma1cACFQoEaQod1iwAFQ">Adafruit</a> for about $18.00.</p>

<h3>How to Install the Slip Ring</h3>

<p>First, pull the entire orange cable out of the extension cord reel. It would be great to keep the whole orange cable as part of the tether, but then we wouldn’t have room for the original tether (twisted pair). Cut the orange cable so that only one meter remains attached to the reel assembly.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_tether_management_internals.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Front view, back view, internal view.' title='Front view, back view, internal view.'><span class='caption-text'>Front view, back view, internal view.</span></span></p>

<p>Next, take the extension cord reel apart. Two phillips-head screws hold the device together. Remove the two screws, and the two orange disks will fall apart.</p>

<p>Now let’s focus on the disk without the electrical plugs. You will need to cut a hole in the exact center of this disk. The hole will need to be large enough to let the thicker part of the slip ring through, while allowing enough of an edge for the flange screws. The photos give a clearer picture than the words in this paragraph.</p>

<p>After you insert the slip ring, drill holes for the three slip ring mounting screws. One way to do this: Drill one hole first, insert the screw, tighten the nut, and then measure/drill the remaining holes. You’re more likely to align all of the holes correctly this way.</p>

<h3>Loctite Threadlocker</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/slip_ring_loctite.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Loctite oozing from the screws.' title='Loctite oozing from the screws.'><span class='caption-text'>Loctite oozing from the screws.</span></span>
<a href="http://www.loctiteproducts.com/threadlockers.shtml">Loctite</a> makes a threadlocker, a gummy substance that keeps screws from jiggling loose. They also make super glue; that&rsquo;s not what you want for this project. If you use Loctite&rsquo;s threadlocker on the slip ring screws, they will remain tight until you remove them on purpose.</p>

<h3>Connecting Inside the Reel</h3>

<p>Take a look inside the reel. You’ll see black, green, and white cables inside. You won’t need to do anything with the black cable. Splice the green line from the slip ring to the green line inside the reel, and splice the white slip ring line with the white reel line. Your technique may vary, but I used a combination hook splice, solder, hot glue, and heat shrink tubing. If you wear a belt and suspenders your pants will never fall down!</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_extra_tab.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Extra tab inside the reel, before and after removal.' title='Extra tab inside the reel, before and after removal.'><span class='caption-text'>Extra tab inside the reel, before and after removal.</span></span></p>

<h3>Gotcha: Removing the Extra Tab</h3>

<p>After initial assembly, I noticed that there was an extra tab inside of the reel. I don’t know the original purpose for the tab, but since it appeared to interfere with tether operation, it had to go. Wire clippers and a dremel tool made quick work of the tab. The before &amp; after photos tell the story.</p>

<h3>Attaching the Tether &amp; Topside Adapter</h3>

<p>Now that you have a functioning reel with a slip ring, attach the twisted pair tether to the 1-meter orange extension cable. Hook splice, solder, hot glue, and heat shrink did the trick for me.</p>

<p>The topside adapter can be attached to the top of the reel with Velcro, as shown in the photos throughout this article. Plug the green and white cables from the outer slip ring into the topside adapter, and you&rsquo;re ready to test the new tether management system.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/nanuk_935_openrov.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Nanuk 935 with OpenROV.' title='Nanuk 935 with OpenROV.'><span class='caption-text'>Nanuk 935 with OpenROV.</span></span>
What should we do with the slip ring&rsquo;s extra lines? I tied mine together for future use. I may cut them if I decide that they&rsquo;re not useful. If you have other ideas, feel free to post in the comments below.</p>

<h3>Everything Fits</h3>

<p>The new tether management system is small enough to share space with an OpenROV inside a <a href="http://nanukcase.com/productdetails.asp?node=205">Nanuk 935 case</a>. The Nanuk case has wheels, a foam interior, and it is rugged and small enough to fly as an airline carry-on.</p>

<p>Whip everything out and you&rsquo;re ready to explore.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_tether_management_laptop.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ready to explore Lake Michigan.' title='Ready to explore Lake Michigan.'><span class='caption-text'>Ready to explore Lake Michigan.</span></span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
