<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-28T11:07:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Environment of Respect, 3rd Iteration]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/05/28/an-environment-of-respect-3rd-iteration/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-28T06:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/05/28/an-environment-of-respect-3rd-iteration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, <a href="https://twitter.com/bantik">Coraline Ehmke</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/feministy">Liz Abbinante</a> met with three members of the WindyCityRails organizer team: <a href="https://twitter.com/zolk">Kevin Zolkiewicz</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/themccreefiles">Alonda McCree</a>, and me. Good dialog. End result: The updated <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/code-of-conduct/">WindyCityRails Code of Conduct</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Harassment is a serious issue, and a 140-character tweet will not do the discussion justice. Therefore, the ChicagoRuby organizers have created multiple communication channels for this issue:</p>

<ul>
<li>Email: <a href="&#109;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#99;&#111;&#x64;&#x65;&#111;&#x66;&#99;&#x6f;&#110;&#x64;&#117;&#x63;&#x74;&#x40;&#x63;&#x68;&#x69;&#99;&#97;&#x67;&#x6f;&#114;&#117;&#98;&#x79;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;">&#99;&#111;&#100;&#101;&#x6f;&#x66;&#99;&#111;&#110;&#x64;&#117;&#x63;&#x74;&#64;&#99;&#104;&#x69;&#99;&#x61;&#x67;&#111;&#x72;&#x75;&#98;&#x79;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#x72;&#103;</a></li>
<li>Any of the contact names listed on the current code of conduct</li>
<li>Phone number listed on the code of conduct</li>
</ul>


<p>If you have concerns in this area, please feel free to use one of the channels. The contact list may change as responsibilities shift within ChicagoRuby. However, there will always be multiple people available to address harassment concerns.</p>

<p>Thank you Coraline and Liz for your work in making this happen. And thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/lostghost">Ken Walters</a> of <a href="http://twitter.com/bradsdeals">Brad’s Deals</a> for facilitating the meeting.</p>

<p>Now, let’s go write some code!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Managing Dotfiles]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/04/15/managing-dotfiles/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-15T17:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/04/15/managing-dotfiles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dotfiles, the configuration files used by Unix-like machines, can become disorganized over time. Entropy rules! This article describes my recent attempt to bring order to dotfile chaos. The steps can be summarized as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>Move the non-private dotfiles (dotfiles that will be viewed by others on Github) into a directory called <code>~/.dotfiles</code>.</li>
<li>From the <code>home</code> directory, create a symbolic link to each dotfile in the <code>~/.dotfiles</code> directory.</li>
<li>Use Git to manage the <code>~/.dotfiles</code> directory, and share it on GitHub.</li>
</ul>


<p>Dotfiles are normally hidden when you try to view them in the Mac OS X Finder. To view them from the command prompt, use <code>$ ls -al</code>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>```bash
~/.dotfiles[master]$ ls -al
total 40
drwxr-xr-x   8 rth  staff   272 Apr 14 01:44 .
drwxr-xr-x+ 71 rth  staff  2414 Apr 14 02:12 ..
-rwxr-xr-x   1 rth  staff  3455 Apr 13 16:01 .bash_profile
drwxr-xr-x  14 rth  staff   476 Apr 14 02:25 .git
-rw-r&mdash;r&mdash;   1 rth  staff  1649 Apr 13 16:44 .gitk
-rw-r&mdash;r&mdash;   1 rth  staff  1760 Apr 13 16:10 .irbrc
-rw-r&mdash;r&mdash;   1 rth  staff   118 Aug 22  2013 .zprofile
-rw-r&mdash;r&mdash;   1 rth  staff   375 Apr 14 01:44 README.mdown</p>

<p>~/.dotfiles[master]$
```</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/RayHightower/.dotfiles/blob/master/.bash_profile">.bash_profile</a> in this example has grown to include aliases, path specifications, and a script that shows the current Git branch as part of the command prompt. The file also contains two aliases useful for showing or hiding dotfiles in the Finder: <code>showdots</code> and <code>hidedots</code>.</p>

<h3>Putting Dotfiles in One Directory</h3>

<p>Dotfiles are normally created in the user&rsquo;s home directory. For organization purposes, I moved my non-private dotfiles into a directory called <code>.dotfiles</code>, listed above. Unix makes this easy. First, move to the home directory and create <code>~/.dotfiles</code>.</p>

<p>```bash
~$ cd ~</p>

<p>~$ mkdir .dotfiles</p>

<p>~$</p>

<p>```</p>

<p><em>Note: Dotfiles can sometimes include private information. If you don&rsquo;t want to share information in a particular dotfile, don&rsquo;t put it on GitHub!</em></p>

<p>In this example, we&rsquo;ll only move one file, <code>.bash_profile</code>.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>~$ cd .dotfiles/</p>

<p>$ mv ../.bash_profile .</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>```</p>

<h3>Symbolic Links</h3>

<p>Symbolic links ensure that executables can find our dotfiles as needed.</p>

<p>```bash</p>

<p>$ cd ~</p>

<p>$ ln -s ~/.dotfiles/.bash_profile</p>

<p>$ ls -al
total 8
drwxr-xr-x   3 rth  staff   102 Apr 14 19:48 .
drwxr-xr-x+ 73 rth  staff  2482 Apr 14 19:47 ..
lrwxr-xr-x   1 rth  staff    34 Apr 14 19:48 .bash_profile &ndash;> /Users/rth/.dotfiles/.bash_profile</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>In the above example, we created a symbolic link called <code>.bash_profile</code> to the real <code>~/.dotfiles/.bash_profile</code> located in the <code>.dotfiles</code> directory. That way, any program that&rsquo;s looking for the <code>.bash_profile</code> file in the home directory will find what it needs, even though the file is somewhere else.</p>

<h3>Why Use Git to Manage Dotfiles?</h3>

<p>Git is a great tool for managing files that change over time. Dotfiles can change as we install new software or tweak our development environment. If we make a mistake, or if an installation script makes a mistake, we can use Git to roll back in history to a pre-mistake version of the dotfile.</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t Make All Dotfiles Public</h3>

<p>There are some dotfiles that you don&rsquo;t want to share publicly. For example, <code>.bash_history</code> contains all of the commands that have been executed in the shell. Do you really want the world that you sometimes <code>$ ssh myuserid@[embarassingdomainname].com</code>? Probably not. If you think that a dotfile might contain personal or confidential information, no need to broadcast it.</p>

<h3>Learning More About Dotfiles</h3>

<p>Most of my dotfiles, like <code>.bash_profile</code>, don&rsquo;t contain anything private. In fact, most of what I know about dotfiles has come from other developers via books, user groups, blogs, and spelunking through GitHub. Dotfile collections by <a href="https://github.com/hashrocket/dotmatrix">Hashrocket</a> and <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/dotfiles">Thoughtbot</a> are  especially good. My <code>~/.dotfiles</code> directory is available for public viewing on <a href="https://github.com/RayHightower/.dotfiles">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re doing something especially cool with your dotfiles, let&rsquo;s hear about it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Open Source?]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/04/05/why-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-05T00:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/04/05/why-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As members of the open source community, we have internalized the benefits of open source. Sometimes, knowing a topic so well can hinder us from explaining it to people who need to understand our work: Clients, customers, and employers. They need to understand us because they pay us. Understanding helps to build trust.</p>

<p>The topic <a href="/blog/2014/02/22/what-is-open-source/">What is Open Source</a> is covered in earlier post by that title. This presentation covers some of the &ldquo;whys&rdquo; of open source in terms that matter to the people we serve: Clients, customers, and employers.</p>

<!--more-->


<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="e20291c09eb00131918d4a0f4a2b8270" data-ratio="1.29456384323641" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>This presentation was delivered at the <a href="http://flourishconf.com/">Flourish 2014</a> conference at the University of Illinois at Chicago. I am grateful to the Flourish organizers and to UIC for inviting me to speak.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flourish Open Source Conference at UIC]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/31/flourish-open-source-conference-at-uic/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T23:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/31/flourish-open-source-conference-at-uic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://flourishconf.com">Flourish</a> is an open source conference to be held at the University of Illinois at Chicago on Saturday, April 5, 2014. The conference is run by university students and tickets are free.</p>

<p>Why go to Flourish? Because&hellip;</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>You like open source.</li>
<li>You want to know more about open source.</li>
<li>You want to meet people who are passionate about open source.</li>
<li>All (or some combination) of the above.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Not Just Software</h3>

<p>Linux may be the best known open source project, but open source is not just about software. At Flourish 2009 a speaker mentioned a funny little circuit board called “Arduino” during one of the presentations. I turned to my neighbor in the audience, and I asked “What’s an Arduino?”</p>

<p>My neighbor pulled an Arduino out of his backpack and showed it to me. Wow. Open source extends to hardware, too! Since then, the Arduino has become part of the <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/youth/">WindyCityRails Youth Program</a>. Beyond microcontrollers, single-board Linux machines like the <a href="/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">Raspeberry Pi</a>, <a href="/blog/2014/01/02/beaglebone-black-ubuntu-part-1/">Beaglebone Black</a>, and <a href="/blog/2013/06/22/preparing-for-parallella-64-cores-installing-go-on-mac-os-x/">Parallella</a> have joined the open source hardware ranks.</p>

<h3>See You There</h3>

<p>Thank you, Flourish organizers, for inviting me to speak this year. UIC is where I first learned about open source, Linux, and the web. My appreciation for UIC extends beyond my CS degree.</p>

<p>Great things happen when like-minded people come together to exchange ideas. I look forward to seeing you at Flourish 2014!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CocoaConf Chicago Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/10/cocoaconf-chicago-recap/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T11:46:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/10/cocoaconf-chicago-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/cocoaconf-2014.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Cool stuff from CocoaConf.' title='Cool stuff from CocoaConf.'><span class='caption-text'>Cool stuff from CocoaConf.</span></span></p>

<blockquote><p>One purpose of a conference is to help you to spot trends while there&rsquo;s still time to reap the benefits of being an early adopter.
&nbsp;<br/>
~Brian Marick at <a href="http://scna.softwarecraftsmanship.org/">SCNA 2013</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Early adopters on Apple&rsquo;s Mac OS X and iOS platforms flock to <a href="http://cocoaconf.com/">CocoaConf</a>, a multi-city conference for developers. Tickets are slightly easier to get than <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wwdc">WWDC</a>; CocoaConf consistently sells out.</p>

<p>CocoaConf&rsquo;s presenters are practicing developers, actively building real software every day. They come to CocoaConf to share their experiences in a wonderful upward-spiral of technical learning. Here are a few highlights from the latest CocoaConf, held March 7-8 near Chicago.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Customers Will Pay for Services</h3>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/justin">Justin Williams</a> kicked things off with a keynote titled <em>10 Things I Think I Think</em>. Williams recently acquired <a href="http://glassboard.com/">Glassboard</a>, so his developer skills are blended with the insights of a business owner. His list of ten included one approach to making money from mobile apps: Forget about selling a million copies in the App Store. Instead, create a service, charge a monthly fee for the service, and give the app away for free so customers can engage with the service. Engaged customers will continue to pay the monthly fee. When customers are served well, they will pay.</p>

<h3>Effective iOS 7 Networking</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/afnetworking-charles.png' width='' height='' alt='Charles shows network connections.' title='Charles shows network connections.'><span class='caption-text'>Charles shows network connections.</span></span>
Customer-focused mobile apps usually communicate with other software via the web. <a href="http://twitter.com/subdigital">Ben Scheirman</a> shared his experiences in building iOS apps that communicate with web services. Several questions are raised when we build apps like this, namely:</p>

<ul>
<li>How do we include communication capabilities without sacrificing performance?</li>
<li>If the mobile app requests information from a web service, and the service is unavailable (or slow) how do we avoid frustrating the user?</li>
</ul>


<p><code>NSURLSession</code>, introduced with iOS 7, lets us upload and download in the background. Users are kept happy because the app continues to function in the foreground. Scheirman&rsquo;s <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/subdigital/effective-network-programming-in-ios-7">slides</a> and <a href="https://github.com/subdigital/mods-2013">sample code</a> give more details.</p>

<p>It is also interesting to note what tools the presenters use in their
daily work. Scheirman uses <a href="http://www.charlesproxy.com/">Charles</a>
to monitor network traffic between machines, and to track down hiccups.</p>

<h3>Xcode Walkabout</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/xcode-git-commit.png' width='' height='' alt='Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.' title='Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.'><span class='caption-text'>Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.</span></span>
Most of my iOS time is spent with <a href="/blog/2013/01/12/why-i-use-vim/">Vim</a> and <a href="/blog/2012/10/29/building-ios-apps-with-ruby-motion/">RubyMotion</a>. I use Xcode mainly to learn things that I can apply to RubyMotion. Still, <a href="http://twitter.com/savinola">Laura Savino</a>&rsquo;s exploration of Xcode proved valuable.</p>

<p>Like many developers on the Apple platforms, Savino has a love/hate relationship with Xcode. She almost titled her talk &ldquo;stupid little buttons that don&rsquo;t even look like buttons.&rdquo; Savino summarized several years of Xcode immersion and pair programming into 60 minutes of little-known tips and tricks. For example, Xcode plays nicely with Git (you can even show commit messages within the IDE). And it&rsquo;s possible to use Vim key bindings while editing files.</p>

<h3>Sprite Kit</h3>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/kognate">Josh Smith</a>&rsquo;s Sprite Kit presentation was full of gotcha-eliminating information. For example, the coordinate systems for Sprite Kit and UIKit are inverted. I&rsquo;m sure this is documented somewhere, but I didn&rsquo;t know about it! The bottom line with Sprite Kit: We can add animation to our apps without doing all of the fundamental work. Saves time.</p>

<p>Slides and code are posted in a single <a href="https://github.com/kognate/presentations">repo on GitHub</a>. Worth looking at.</p>

<h3>Parallel Computing with OpenCL</h3>

<p>The parallel computing talk by <a href="http://twitter.com/hyperjeff">Jeff Biggus</a> was the most mind-blowing session of CocoaConf, for me. The presentation was exciting because it tied our current set of tools (like <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Performance/Reference/GCD_libdispatch_Ref/Reference/reference.html">GCD</a>) with high performance computing work currently underway at universities and at corporations like NVidia. When theory blends with application, great things can be achieved.</p>

<p>Biggus shared some of the work of <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opencl/">OpenCL</a>, a standard designed for cross-platform parallel computing. We care about parallel computing because&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Moore&rsquo;s Law has just about run its course.</li>
<li>Engineers have packed transistors about as tightly as they can on silicon.</li>
</ul>


<p>Unless we can figure out how to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montgomery_Scott">rewrite the laws of physics</a>, the next advances in computing performance will come from making processors work together without stepping on each other&rsquo;s toes.</p>

<h3>The Klein Family</h3>

<p>2014 marks CocoaConf&rsquo;s third year in the Chicago area. The conference is run by Dave and Debbie Klein and their 14 children. <a href="http://cocoaconf.com/family">About The Family Behind CocoaConf</a> gives details.</p>

<p>Thank you, Klein family, for another great CocoaConf!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
