<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-10T11:10:13-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Too Soon for Alpha Centauri]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/22/too-soon-for-alpha-centauri/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T12:07:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/22/too-soon-for-alpha-centauri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bad news&#58; I have decided to cancel <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a> for 2015. Ticket sales are insufficient to cover the cost of the event. Every person who bought a ticket will receive a full refund.</p>

<p>Barbados is a beautiful island nation with welcoming people, a university that leads in multiple technical areas, and a thriving economy. The RubyCaribe (pronounced ka-REEB) organizers will make the event happen in some form at some point in the future. Just not now.</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h3>Alpha Centauri</h3>

<p>NASA has launched successful missions to the Moon, Mars, and other bodies in our solar system. NASA would like to visit Alpha Centauri, 4.4 light years away. But they will only launch an Alpha Centauri mission after key prerequisites (maybe the theoretical <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcubierre_drive">Alcubierre drive</a>) are in place.</p>

<p>It’s too soon for Alpha Centauri, right now. But one day, humans will get there.</p>

<p>The RubyCaribe team has achieved eight years of success with <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>, <a href="http://chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a>, and events focused on NoSQL and mobile technologies. With that track record, I believed that we could make RubyCaribe work in 2015. But reality disagrees with me.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s too soon for RubyCaribe, right now. But we will get there.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/LinuxBarbados-tux-logo_300.png' width='' height='' alt='LinuxBarbados.org' title='LinuxBarbados.org'><span class='caption-text'>LinuxBarbados.org</span></span></p>

<h3>Upside: LinuxBarbados</h3>

<p>While planning RubyCaribe, our team began an amazing relationship with the University of the West Indies at Cave Hill (<a href="http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/">UWI</a>). We collaborated with UWI to create <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a>. The monthly LinuxBarbados meetings are an exciting way to grow your open source software and hardware skills. Discussions cover Linux, Parallella, Raspberry Pi, Ruby, Java&hellip; and more.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re in Barbados, you can attend in person on the UWI campus. If you&rsquo;re not in Barbados, you can still participate because every LinuxBarbados meeting includes a live video conference. Sign up at <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados.org</a> if you&rsquo;d like to know more.</p>

<h3>Next Steps for RubyCaribe</h3>

<p>Moving forward, our team will take an Alpha Centauri approach to RubyCaribe. We will get there. And we invite you to enjoy the journey with us.</p>

<p>Do you have thoughts about RubyCaribe? If so, you&rsquo;re welcome to <a href="/contact">share via the contact form</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>What do you like or dislike about RubyCaribe?</li>
<li>What do you think about the content?</li>
<li>What do you think about the price?</li>
<li>What do you think about the location?</li>
<li>Is there anything else you would like to share?</li>
</ul>


<p>Anonymous feedback is fine. Just put dummy values in the appropriate fields.</p>

<p>Thanks for listening. We look forward to seeing you at  <a href="http://chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a> and <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ignite RubyConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T15:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/ignite_logo_200.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.' title='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.'><span class='caption-text'>Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.</span></span>
<a href="http://igniteshow.com/">Ignite</a> is a presentation format where the slides advance automatically every 15 seconds whether the presenter is ready or not. Twenty slides, 15 seconds each, five minutes total. Presenters are challenged to present their ideas quickly and clearly before the time runs out.</p>

<p>Ignite is similar to <a href="http://www.pechakucha.org">Pecha Kucha</a>. The two formats differ only in slide duration (20 seconds per slide with Pecha Kucha).</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.sdruby.org/">SDRuby</a> ran an Ignite event on the day before RubyConf 2014. Slides from my OpenROV presentation at Ignite RubyConf 2014 appear below.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="573c89704e88013264a612c8f4a94aec" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>&nbsp;<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
Thanks SDRuby for hosting the Ignite event!</p>

<p>If you like the idea of hacking on Ruby <em>and</em> OpenROV, check out <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to North Shore]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T14:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long-time observers of ChicagoRuby know that the group is always striving to achieve more. Latest move: ChicagoRuby is now hosting a monthly meetup on Chicago’s North Shore. The first meeting of ChicagoRuby: North Shore will be held on Saturday, December 6, 2014 at 10:30am. Visit <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/216193202/">Meetup.com</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Why the North Shore?</h3>

<p>Why expand to Chicago’s North Shore? One reason: Several ChicagoRuby members live there, and travelling to meetings downtown and in Elmhurst can be quite a haul.</p>

<p>The bigger reason: Two members have stepped up to manage the north shore operation. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> and <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> have been active in Elmhurst for a long time. They were chosen as organizers because they are vocal and they have already done the preliminary leg work.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how we roll in ChicagoRuby. Many years ago, <a href="https://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> demonstrated that if you push for a new activity in ChicagoRuby (like hack nights) you might end up running it!</p>

<h3>Exciting Year</h3>

<p>2014 has proven to be an exciting year for ChicagoRuby. So far, the group has…</p>

<ul>
<li>Collaborated with the University of the West Indies at Cave Hill, Barbados to form <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a>.</li>
<li>Built alliances with top-notch developers in multiple countries to create <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</li>
<li>Expanded the monthly Chicago-area activities to four per month.</li>
<li>Grown the organizer team to ten (10) members.</li>
</ul>


<p>Looking forward to more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geekfest &amp; OpenROV]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T09:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/geekfest.png' width='' height='' alt='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.' title='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.'><span class='caption-text'>Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.</span></span>
<a href="http://www.meetup.com/Geekfest/events/207936312/">Geekfest</a> is a weekly event hosted by Groupon&rsquo;s engineering team. Every Tuesday at lunchtime, the company invites members of the tech community to present topics that are interesting to a technical audience.</p>

<p>I wish to express my thanks to Groupon for inviting me to present <a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> at today&rsquo;s Geekfest.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Slides appear below. Video will be posted as soon as it becomes available. Special thanks to <a href="http://chelseatroy.com/2014/10/21/geekfest-ray-hightower-dumps-a-robot-into-lake-michigan/">Chelsea Troy</a> for creating a real-time blog post about the presentation.</p>

<center><iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/112204897" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>




<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="e8ed21a03b5d013274bd1297e85160ca" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UWI Computer Science Club &amp; LinuxBarbados]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/10/uwi-computer-science-club-and-linuxbarbados/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-10T03:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/10/uwi-computer-science-club-and-linuxbarbados</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Members of the <a href="http://cavehill.uwi.edu/">University of the West Indies (UWI)</a> Computer Science Club and <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> just finished a joint session this afternoon. I am grateful that the group invited me to present. Outline (prepared in advance):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>30 minutes: Overview of Ruby, Rails, and some alternatives to both. What are the advantages and disadvantages of building web apps with Ruby? Can you build a business with this stuff?</p></li>
<li><p>30 minutes: Questions and Answers. This will be a highly interactive time. Anything discussed earlier is fair game. We can explore technical specifics if you like.</p></li>
<li><p>60 minutes: Deep dive into anything the group wants to explore related to technology, business, or the combination of the two. If the group doesn&rsquo;t choose a topic, we will end early. But if the group is interested and engaged, we will continue.</p></li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Slides from the presentation are posted here.</p>

<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="ba46e5b032a001322feb4edc433df659" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>Thank you UWI for the invitation!</p>

<p>If you want to know more about these subjects, and if you would like to study this material in a hands-on lab environment with experts guiding the way, you might enjoy <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
