<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-19T17:52:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenROV Assembly Challenges]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/08/19/openrov-assembly-challenges/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T16:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/08/19/openrov-assembly-challenges</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_rth.jpg' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV fully assembled.' title='OpenROV fully assembled.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV fully assembled.</span></span>
I know this problem can be solved. I just haven’t figured it out yet, and I need help from the <a href="http://openrov.com/">OpenROV</a> community to do so.</p>

<h3>Parts That Work</h3>

<p>Software image updates on the Beaglebone Black work flawlessly thanks to scripts written by <a href="https://github.com/BrianAdams">Brian Adams</a> and <a href="https://github.com/BrianAdams">Dominick Fretz</a>. The cockpit software shows a real-time image from the camera, the LED lights are super-bright, and the lasers hold steady at 10cm apart. My fully assembled OpenROV passes the water submersion test. Yes, it’s waterproof, thanks to O-rings and silicon-based lubricant!</p>

<p>What about the motors? The motors work, almost. Could it be the
electronic speed control (ESC) settings, calibration, or less than
perfect soldering? That&rsquo;s where I need help.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Summary of Symptoms</h3>

<p>With the cockpit software running and attached to the OpenROV:</p>

<ul>
<li>If I turn on any of the three ESCs, two of the motors (vertical and port) start running at full blast. The starboard motor remains stationary.</li>
<li>While the V and P motors continue to run at full blast, the starboard motor responds to the cockpit slider controls as expected: +1 makes S run full blast on one direction, -1 sends S full blast in the other direction, and 0 stops the S motor completely. During this exercise, V and P continue at full blast.</li>
<li>Turning off the ESC stops the V and P motors.</li>
<li>When I turn on any of the ESCs, the camera servo jumps slightly, about 10 degrees. And then the V and P motors run full blast.</li>
</ul>


<p>When the cockpit software is not running (and the Google Chrome browser is completely closed):</p>

<ul>
<li>Turning on an ESC has no effect on the motors.</li>
<li>The camera servo jumps slightly, about 10 degrees, as it did with the cockpit software running. But the motors remain stationary.</li>
</ul>


<p>Interesting behavior!</p>

<h3>Double-Checking the ESC Settings</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/esc_program_card.jpg' width='' height='' alt='ESC Program Card' title='ESC Program Card'><span class='caption-text'>ESC Program Card</span></span>
During troubleshooting, my first step was to double-check the electronic speed controller (ESC) settings. Setting the ESCs with the beep-and-button-push method was time consuming. And I was concerned that I may have made a mistake in counting the beeps.</p>

<p>Solution: I bought an ESC program card. Amazon sells them for less than fifteen dollars, well worth the price when you consider the peace of mind that the card brings. The program card shows each ESC setting with a clear 7-segment LED display, much easier than counting beeps!</p>

<p>According to the program card, all of the ESC settings are correct.</p>

<h3>Using a Power Supply Instead of Batteries</h3>

<p>All of the time spent troubleshooting drained the OpenROV batteries. So I devised a way to apply power directly to the OpenROV without batteries.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_power_supply.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Directly connected to power supply.' title='Directly connected to power supply.'><span class='caption-text'>Directly connected to power supply.</span></span></p>

<p>The photo reveals the random condition of my work surface, so here&rsquo;s a verbal description of this hack:</p>

<ul>
<li>In the background, a power supply set to 12 volts</li>
<li><code>+</code> lead (red) connected to the <code>+</code> leads of the battery containers, via a wire acting as a Y-connector.</li>
<li><code>-</code> lead (black) connected to a ground terminal on the OpenROV controller board through a black jumper cable</li>
</ul>


<p>I find that this hack works best if I connect the 12 volt setup first while the Topside Adapter is powered off. Applying power (via USB) to the Topside Adapter turns the entire assembly on.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this section and you know a better way for me to connect the power supply, please advise in the comments section below.</p>

<h3>Advice Welcome</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure where to look next to solve the challenge with the motors. Maybe I skipped a step somewhere during assembly? Advice welcome!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be Awesome. Tackle Big League Problems at WindyCityRails]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/08/05/be-awesome-tackle-big-league-problems-at-windycityrails/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-05T16:21:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/08/05/be-awesome-tackle-big-league-problems-at-windycityrails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/big_league_problems_windycityrails.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Be awesome.' title='Be awesome.'><span class='caption-text'>Be awesome.</span></span>
Do you see yourself in any of these scenarios?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>You have already built a successful Rails app. Now that you&rsquo;re &ldquo;done&rdquo;, you know you can make it better, but you&rsquo;re not sure how. You want to take your skills to the next level.</p></li>
<li><p>You recently graduated from <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">Dev Bootcamp</a>, <a href="http://thestarterleague.com">Starter League</a>, <a href="http://www.mobilemakers.co/">Mobile Makers</a> or another school. You&rsquo;re ready to meet and interact with your next generation of mentors.</p></li>
<li><p>You are no longer a beginner. You have seen <em>advanced</em> developers in action, and you are determined to get there yourself.</p></li>
<li><p>Software development is relatively new to you, and you built a successful track record in another profession. You want to meet people who can help you accelerate through the beginner phase so you can launch something useful.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Common thread: It&rsquo;s time to unleash the awesomeness in your bones. You want to take your skills to the next level, and you are ready to tackle <em>Big League Problems</em>. <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> is for you.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>What are Big League Problems?</h3>

<p>You might think of a big league problem as a good problem. For example, the Rails app you built is pulling in customers, and you&rsquo;re bumping into the limits of your software architecture. Who knew that so many people would buy from you?</p>

<p>Now&hellip; How do you scale? Do you buy more hardware, change your architecture, choose a new platform, or some combination of these? <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#williams">Dr. Nic Williams</a>, <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#shirai">Brian Shirai</a>, <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#light">Evan Light</a>, <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#menard">Mark Menard</a> deal with scaling problems. Learn from them.</p>

<p>Maybe you built a gem to solve a problem for yourself, and now you want to release your gem to the world. What legal questions do you need to consider? Did Rails face similar challenges in the beginning? <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#saper">Daliah Saper</a> is an attorney who specializes in intellectual property and other open source software issues. Put her team to work for you.</p>

<p>How about security? Have you outgrown the <code>Devise</code> gem? Or do you simply need to know more about <code>Devise</code> internals so that you can use it more effectively? Maybe it&rsquo;s time to abandon username/password logins altogether and go with SQRL. <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#love">Justin Love</a> and <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/#mazza">Lucas Mazza</a> might have some ideas for you.</p>

<h3>Awesome Speakers. Awesome Audience.</h3>

<p>This year&rsquo;s WindyCityRails features the most powerful collection of speakers we&rsquo;ve ever assembled. Check out the <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/">complete list of WindyCityRails speakers</a> and ask yourself what you can learn from each one.</p>

<p>Even better: Only 300 WindyCityRails tickets will be sold. Our speakers enjoy interacting with audience members throughout the conference. As professionals, they are always learning, too! So if you want some face time with people who understand Big League Problems (and more importantly, Big League Solutions) WindyCityRails is the place for you to be.</p>

<h3>Get Tickets Now</h3>

<p>Tickets are selling fast. Get yours now at <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/register/">http://www.windycityrails.org/register/</a>. Use the promo code AWESOME to save $75.00 on the standard price.</p>

<p>We look forward to seeing you at WindyCityRails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wanted: Community Manager]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/30/wanted-community-manager/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T12:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/30/wanted-community-manager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/chicagoruby_community.png' width='' height='' alt='Jamming together. Growing together.' title='Jamming together. Growing together.'><span class='caption-text'>Jamming together. Growing together.</span></span>
WisdomGroup is hiring a Community Manager (CM) to help run our user groups and conferences. This is a part-time independent contractor position, mostly remote, with some on-site work during meetings and conferences. The position could become full-time depending on results produced and community growth.</p>

<h3>Smart People, Growing Together</h3>

<p>Our community philosophy:</p>

<blockquote><p>When smart people challenge each other to grow, great things happen.</p></blockquote>

<p>Our community track record is  covered in the article <a href="/blog/2014/05/30/how-to-grow-a-user-group/">How to Grow a User Group</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Responsibilities</h3>

<p>The CM will be responsible for the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Managing social media feeds (like Twitter) for our groups and events.</li>
<li>Writing blog posts that promote our groups and events.</li>
<li>Interacting with group members through multiple channels: Face-to-face, online video conference, social media, and email.</li>
<li>Helping WisdomGroup to determine the best way to deliver value for group members.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Ideal Candidate</h3>

<p>The ideal candidate will fit the following description:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Self Starter</strong> &ndash; Works remotely to produce outstanding results with minimal supervision. Runs through walls to get things done.</li>
<li><strong>Team Player</strong> &ndash; Works well with other members of the WisdomGroup team. Shares information with team members via Basecamp and other collaboration tools.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic Thinker</strong> &ndash; Understands how the CM position fits into WisdomGroup&rsquo;s big picture. Demonstrates understanding by personally taking action where needed.</li>
<li><strong>Aggressive Learner</strong> &ndash; Currently uses social media tools like Twitter and Facebook. Learns and creates new ways to engage the community with social media tools.</li>
</ul>


<h3>About WisdomGroup</h3>

<p>To learn more about WisdomGroup, visit:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://WisdomGroup.com">WisdomGroup.com</a> &ndash; company website.</li>
<li><a href="http://chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby.org</a> and <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados.org</a> &ndash; user group sites.</li>
<li><a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails.org</a> and <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe.com</a> &ndash; conference sites.</li>
<li><a href="http://rayhightower.com">RayHightower.com</a> &ndash; president&rsquo;s personal blog.</li>
</ul>


<h3>To Apply</h3>

<p>To apply for the position, email a PDF of your resume to careers@wisdomgroup.com, and include the words &ldquo;Community Manager&rdquo; in the subject line. We look forward to hearing from you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LinuxBarbados is Global]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/25/linuxbarbados-is-global/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-25T15:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/25/linuxbarbados-is-global</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/LinuxBarbados-tux-logo_300.png' width='' height='' alt='' title=''><span class='caption-text'></span></span>
<a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> is a user group for open source enthusiasts. The group meets monthly, offering solid knowledge for anyone who wants to ramp up their open source skills. For example, yesterday’s meeting featured a presentation on <a href="http://xbmc.org/">XBMC</a> by Michael Layne. The presenter dug deep into the tool, offering tips on how to write plugins in C++ or Python.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Global Reach</h3>

<p>The group is based in Barbados on the campus of the <a href="http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/">University of the West Indies (UWI) at Cave Hill</a>. Enthusiasts who don’t live in Barbados can participate <em>live</em> online. So far the group has used Google Hangout for video. Other video solutions will be considered as the group continues to grow.</p>

<h3>Next Steps</h3>

<p>Organizers <a href="http://www.meetup.com/LinuxBarbados/members/143194822/">Maurice Beckles</a> and <a href="http://www.meetup.com/LinuxBarbados/members/153574612/">Michael Layne</a> have exciting plans for the group. Take a look at the LinuxBarbados calendar, and join <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> online if you want to hear about future events.</p>

<p>Whether you live in the Caribbean or in Antarctica, we look forward to seeing you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CloudCamp Chicago: Developer Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/25/cloudcamp-chicago-developer-night/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-25T15:09:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/07/25/cloudcamp-chicago-developer-night</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://cohesiveft.com">CohesiveFT</a> hosted a CloudCamp Developer Night this week. Speakers were Philip Szalwinski of 8th Light, John Downey of Braintree, Marcy Capron of Polymathic, and me. My presentation, <a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">Citizen Science With OpenROV</a>, was based on the blog post of the same name.</p>

<p>Thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/MargieWalker">Margaret Walker</a> for running a great event. Slides appear below.</p>

<!--more-->


<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="4d87fa90f65e0131729a0a98c369402e" data-ratio="1.29456384323641" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
