<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-31T01:02:44+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Context Changes Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/23/context-changes-everything/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-23T03:48:08+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/23/context-changes-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some cases where time zone information is absolutely critical. For example: When scheduling a video conference that crosses national boundaries.</p>

<p>A few hours ago, Google sent me a reminder about today&rsquo;s <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> meeting. The group meets via video conferencing software over the web. Google&rsquo;s reminder was confusing because it showed the time without the time zone (screenshot below). LinuxBarbados is based in the Caribbean, and some of the members participate from other time zones.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/GH_time_zone_arrow.png' width='' height='' alt='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?' title='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?'><span class='caption-text'>What time is it when the time zone is unknown?</span></span></p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s automated reminder said <code>3pm - 4pm</code> with no time zone reference. How confusing! Members of the group received the same automated reminder with the same information, regardless of time zone. A small change, displaying the time as <code>3pm - 4pm (CST)</code> would solve the problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Other Context Examples</h3>

<p>When people speak with each other directly, context is implied. But when communication happens in printed form, it&rsquo;s helpful to have the context in print, too. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Walking down the street, you see a poster advertising a concert on January 29th. No year is shown. Is this an old poster for a concert that happened last year on Jan 29th? Or is the event happening next week?</li>
<li>A restaurant menu offers delivery service. Just call the number, and order your food. The phone number is seven digits long, with no area code. Most customers would abandon the menu in favor of a restaurant with more complete information.</li>
<li>Following the train of thought in the previous example: Since phone service has fallen in price, many people call internationally on a more regular basis. A complete phone number should include the country code.</li>
</ul>


<p>Context changes everything. Something all of us need to remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chicago Node.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/21/chicago-node-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T03:23:30+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/21/chicago-node-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_at_groupon.png' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.' title='OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV at Groupon. Photo by Michelle Waldorf.</span></span>
The <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Chicago-Nodejs/events/203711262/">Chicago Node.js</a> user group invited me to present <em>Node.js Under Water</em>, an overview of the <a href="http://openrov.com">OpenROV</a> underwater robot, this evening. Slides appear below.</p>

<p>Every version of this talk is tailored to the audience. This version focuses on OpenROV hardware components since this group certainly knows Node.js. Information has been added on hardware gotchas and tether management.</p>

<p>Thank you Chicago Node.js organizers and members for having me.</p>

<!--more-->




<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="b51c86f083270132a7cc1ade27531f87" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Too Soon for Alpha Centauri]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/22/too-soon-for-alpha-centauri/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T12:07:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/22/too-soon-for-alpha-centauri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bad news&#58; I have decided to cancel <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a> for 2015. Ticket sales are insufficient to cover the cost of the event. Every person who bought a ticket will receive a full refund.</p>

<p>Barbados is a beautiful island nation with welcoming people, a university that leads in multiple technical areas, and a thriving economy. The RubyCaribe (pronounced ka-REEB) organizers will make the event happen in some form at some point in the future. Just not now.</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h3>Alpha Centauri</h3>

<p>NASA has launched successful missions to the Moon, Mars, and other bodies in our solar system. NASA would like to visit Alpha Centauri, 4.4 light years away. But they will only launch an Alpha Centauri mission after key prerequisites (maybe the theoretical <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcubierre_drive">Alcubierre drive</a>) are in place.</p>

<p>It’s too soon for Alpha Centauri, right now. But one day, humans will get there.</p>

<p>The RubyCaribe team has achieved eight years of success with <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>, <a href="http://chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a>, and events focused on NoSQL and mobile technologies. With that track record, I believed that we could make RubyCaribe work in 2015. But reality disagrees with me.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s too soon for RubyCaribe, right now. But we will get there.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/LinuxBarbados-tux-logo_300.png' width='' height='' alt='LinuxBarbados.org' title='LinuxBarbados.org'><span class='caption-text'>LinuxBarbados.org</span></span></p>

<h3>Upside: LinuxBarbados</h3>

<p>While planning RubyCaribe, our team began an amazing relationship with the University of the West Indies at Cave Hill (<a href="http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/">UWI</a>). We collaborated with UWI to create <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a>. The monthly LinuxBarbados meetings are an exciting way to grow your open source software and hardware skills. Discussions cover Linux, Parallella, Raspberry Pi, Ruby, Java&hellip; and more.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re in Barbados, you can attend in person on the UWI campus. If you&rsquo;re not in Barbados, you can still participate because every LinuxBarbados meeting includes a live video conference. Sign up at <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados.org</a> if you&rsquo;d like to know more.</p>

<h3>Next Steps for RubyCaribe</h3>

<p>Moving forward, our team will take an Alpha Centauri approach to RubyCaribe. We will get there. And we invite you to enjoy the journey with us.</p>

<p>Do you have thoughts about RubyCaribe? If so, you&rsquo;re welcome to <a href="/contact">share via the contact form</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>What do you like or dislike about RubyCaribe?</li>
<li>What do you think about the content?</li>
<li>What do you think about the price?</li>
<li>What do you think about the location?</li>
<li>Is there anything else you would like to share?</li>
</ul>


<p>Anonymous feedback is fine. Just put dummy values in the appropriate fields.</p>

<p>Thanks for listening. We look forward to seeing you at  <a href="http://chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a> and <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ignite RubyConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T15:01:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/ignite_logo_200.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.' title='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.'><span class='caption-text'>Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.</span></span>
<a href="http://igniteshow.com/">Ignite</a> is a presentation format where the slides advance automatically every 15 seconds whether the presenter is ready or not. Twenty slides, 15 seconds each, five minutes total. Presenters are challenged to present their ideas quickly and clearly before the time runs out.</p>

<p>Ignite is similar to <a href="http://www.pechakucha.org">Pecha Kucha</a>. The two formats differ only in slide duration (20 seconds per slide with Pecha Kucha).</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.sdruby.org/">SDRuby</a> ran an Ignite event on the day before RubyConf 2014. Slides from my OpenROV presentation at Ignite RubyConf 2014 appear below.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="573c89704e88013264a612c8f4a94aec" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>&nbsp;<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
Thanks SDRuby for hosting the Ignite event!</p>

<p>If you like the idea of hacking on Ruby <em>and</em> OpenROV, check out <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to North Shore]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T14:51:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long-time observers of ChicagoRuby know that the group is always striving to achieve more. Latest move: ChicagoRuby is now hosting a monthly meetup on Chicago’s North Shore. The first meeting of ChicagoRuby: North Shore will be held on Saturday, December 6, 2014 at 10:30am. Visit <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/216193202/">Meetup.com</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Why the North Shore?</h3>

<p>Why expand to Chicago’s North Shore? One reason: Several ChicagoRuby members live there, and travelling to meetings downtown and in Elmhurst can be quite a haul.</p>

<p>The bigger reason: Two members have stepped up to manage the north shore operation. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> and <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> have been active in Elmhurst for a long time. They were chosen as organizers because they are vocal and they have already done the preliminary leg work.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how we roll in ChicagoRuby. Many years ago, <a href="https://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> demonstrated that if you push for a new activity in ChicagoRuby (like hack nights) you might end up running it!</p>

<h3>Exciting Year</h3>

<p>2014 has proven to be an exciting year for ChicagoRuby. So far, the group has…</p>

<ul>
<li>Collaborated with the University of the West Indies at Cave Hill, Barbados to form <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a>.</li>
<li>Built alliances with top-notch developers in multiple countries to create <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</li>
<li>Expanded the monthly Chicago-area activities to four per month.</li>
<li>Grown the organizer team to ten (10) members.</li>
</ul>


<p>Looking forward to more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
