<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-01T16:32:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Lambda Jam 2015 Experience]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/07/20/the-lambdajam-2015-experience/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-20T09:41:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/07/20/the-lambdajam-2015-experience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/LambdaJam.png' width='' height='' alt='Lambda Jam 2015' title='Lambda Jam 2015'><span class='caption-text'>Lambda Jam 2015</span></span>
Working in software development is like being the proverbial kid in candy store. Every new language is a shiny and delicious thing. <a href="http://lambdajam.com">Lambda Jam</a> (which bounces between Chicago and Melbourne) is a traveling candy store. And, like the kid in the candy store, I am sometimes distracted by tangential temptation.</p>

<p>Most of my time is spent running <a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup</a>, where we focus on Ruby and Swift. We&rsquo;re object-oriented all the way. Given that, why would I want to attend a functional programming conference like Lambda Jam? For the brain-stretching experience. If your background is anything like mine, you might enjoy it, too. Here’s why.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Motivation: Parallelism and Concurrency</h3>

<p>One immediate reason to explore FP: The impending end of Moore&rsquo;s Law.  For over half a century we&rsquo;ve taken it for granted that we could double the number of transistors on a wafer every 18 months or so. But the laws of physics are catching up to us, and now we need to create new ways to boost computer performance. Two potential performance boosters: Parallelism and concurrency.</p>

<p>And yes, as Rob Pike points out, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cN_DpYBzKso&amp;list=PLOnWKC1gI_OPU8SDIBnCLHsgzNLSbnPJQ&amp;index=8">Concurrency is Not Parallelism</a>. Concurrency enables parallelism.</p>

<p>Certain features of FP reduce the pain of writing concurrent programs.  For example, data immutability will not allow two (or more) instances of the same process to over-write the same data. Developers trained to write serially-executing programs never have this concern. But if we want the benefits of concurrency, we need to acknowledge and attack a new set of challenges.</p>

<p>Side note: <a href="/blog/2014/07/07/parallella-quick-start-guide-with-gotchas/">Parallella</a> offers one way to explore parallelism and concurrency in hardware. What a board!</p>

<h3>FP, Physics, and Calculus</h3>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/conal">Conal Elliott</a> kicked off Lambda Jam by making connections between FP, physics, and calculus. He shared why concurrent models are difficult to reason about. And then he shared methods of abstraction that we can use to overcome the difficulty.</p>

<p>One abstraction tool, mentioned by Elliott and shared by some of the other presenters: Types. Ruby is a dynamically typed language, employing &ldquo;duck typing&rdquo; as needed. The flexibility that comes from duck typing sometimes leads to unintended consequences. A strongly typed language, like Haskell or Clojure, can make certain programming errors obvious before we put our code into production.</p>

<h3>Haskell Tutorial</h3>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/ranjitjhala">Ranjit Jhala</a>&rsquo;s Haskell tutorial offered a chance to put some FP ideas into practice. The idea of attending a Haskell tutorial was intimidating. But I went anyway, and I&rsquo;m glad that I did. Jhala made the material accessible. I left the Haskell tutorial with some hands-on experience and a new appreciation for FP (in general) and Haskell in particular.</p>

<h3>Hallway Conversations</h3>

<p>Serendipity is a huge benefit of any conference. I ran into a <a href="http://devmyndsoftware.com">DevMynd</a> developer, <a href="http://twitter.com/pushcx">Peter Harkins</a>, who uses FP principles to make his Ruby code more robust. To learn more about this approach, check out <a href="https://www.windycityrails.org/videos/2013/#2">Jessica Kerr</a>&rsquo;s FP presentation at WindyCityRails 2013.</p>

<h3>The Venue: South Shore</h3>

<p>Any recap of Lambda Jam 2015 would be incomplete without a description of the venue, <a href="http://www.chicagoparkdistrict.com/parks/South-Shore-Cultural-Center/">South Shore Cultural Center (SSCC)</a>. Some of you will remember SSCC as the venue for WindyCityRails 2012 and 2013. It&rsquo;s in the middle of a golf course, next to Lake Michigan. The retreat-type atmosphere is great for brain work. Hats off to the Lambda Jam organizers for the choice. I look forward to a return visit.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Much of the FP material at Lambda Jam was over my head. And yet a great deal was accessible to me. As developers, we must always stretch ourselves to learn more; that&rsquo;s how we grow. Lambda Jam is great for stretching, and great for growth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With Jekyll]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/24/getting-started-with-jekyll/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-24T16:02:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/24/getting-started-with-jekyll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/jekyll-responsive.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Jekyll, the static HTML generator.' title='Jekyll, the static HTML generator.'><span class='caption-text'>Jekyll, the static HTML generator.</span></span></p>

<p><a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a> is a static HTML generator for web sites that don&rsquo;t require a content management system (CMS). Jekyll sites load quickly, especially when combined with GitHub Pages. <a href="https://twitter.com/bobbyreys">Bobby Reyes</a> and I will present Jekyll at ChicagoRuby: 1871 on Thursday, June 25, 2015. Slides are below.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Why Jekyll?</h3>

<p>You may already know that RayHightower.com is powered by <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> (as of the date of this article). Octopress sits on top of Jekyll. Recently, I discovered that Jekyll offers some advantages that will help this blog greatly, namely:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>A larger community than Octopress. As Linus Torvalds says: With many eyeballs, all bugs are shallow.</p></li>
<li><p>Lots of templates. I am not a designer. Further, since this is a simple blog, an amazing design would be overkill. But the blog must look crisp and professional, right? Jekyll templates that meet my needs are widely available.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Migration Happening Now</h3>

<p>This blog&rsquo;s migration from Octopress to Jekyll is underway. I’ll post when it’s done. In the meantime, take a look at the slides from the Jekyll presentation at ChicagoRuby.</p>

<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="5d549813f5db469a974423257d1c734e" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>&nbsp;<br/>
This 82-second video shows how to launch a Jekyll site with the default template.</p>

<center><iframe width="665" height="420" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2KHQ3o9b2wk?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<p>&nbsp;<br/></p>

<h3>Thanks, Octopress!</h3>

<p>I am grateful to the Octopress community for introducing me to static page generators. Jekyll is the next logical step for me. And, since technology is always changing, it will be exciting to learn what&rsquo;s next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unleash Your Awesomeness at WindyCityRails]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/02/unleash-your-awesomeness-at-windycityrails/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-02T15:09:06-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/06/02/unleash-your-awesomeness-at-windycityrails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/sphere_question.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Do you see yourself?' title='Do you see yourself?'><span class='caption-text'>Do you see yourself?</span></span>
Are you driven to excel? Do you see yourself here?</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>You have already built a successful Rails app</strong>. Now that you&rsquo;re &ldquo;done&rdquo;, you know you can make it better, but you&rsquo;re not sure how. You want to take your skills to the next level.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You recently graduated</strong> from <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">Dev Bootcamp</a>, <a href="http://thestarterleague.com">Starter League</a>, <a href="http://www.mobilemakers.co/">Mobile Makers</a> or another school. You&rsquo;re ready to meet and interact with your next generation of mentors.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You are no longer a beginner</strong>. You have seen <em>advanced</em> developers in action, and you are determined to get there yourself.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>You are a beginner who learns quickly</strong>. Maybe you&rsquo;re a seasoned professional with a track record in another field. You want to meet people (perhaps mentors?) who can help you accelerate through the beginner phase so you can launch something useful on the web.</p></li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Common thread: It&rsquo;s time to unleash the awesomeness in your bones. You want to take your skills to the next level, and you are ready to tackle <em>Big League Problems</em>. <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> is for you.</p>

<h3>What is a Big League Problem?</h3>

<p>Growth-oriented people view big league problems as <em>good</em> problems. For example, the Rails app you built is pulling in customers, and you&rsquo;re bumping into the limits of your software architecture. Who knew that so many people would buy from you!</p>

<p>Now&hellip; How do you scale? Do you buy more hardware, change your architecture, choose a new platform, or some combination of these? The presenters at this year&rsquo;s WindyCityRails have dealt with scaling problems. Scaling an app, scaling a team, scaling a management structure&hellip; If you expect to encounter challenges, it makes sense to learn from the mistakes (and triumphs) of others. Put their experience to work for you.</p>

<h3>Awesome Speakers. Awesome Audience.</h3>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/schedule/">complete list of WindyCityRails speakers</a> and ask yourself what you can learn from each one.</p>

<p>Remember that only 300 WindyCityRails tickets will be sold. Our speakers enjoy interacting with audience members throughout the conference. As professionals, they are always learning, too! So if you want some face time with people who understand Big League Problems (and more importantly, Big League <em>Solutions</em>) WindyCityRails is the place for you to be.</p>

<h3>Get Tickets Now</h3>

<p>Tickets for WindyCityRails always sell fast. <a href="http://www.windycityrails.org/register/">Get yours now</a>. We look forward to seeing you at WindyCityRails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trinity High School: Thank You!]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/29/trinity-high-school-thank-you/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-29T14:51:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/05/29/trinity-high-school-thank-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/trinity_high_school_river_forest.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Tinity High School' title='Tinity High School'><span class='caption-text'>Tinity High School</span></span></p>

<blockquote><p>What is the toughest obstacle you have ever faced in business, and how did you deal with it?<br/>~Student at Trinity High School<br/>&nbsp;River Forest, IL, USA</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.trinityhs.org/">Trinity High School</a> invited me to speak to two of their student groups this morning. The first, <em>Information Technology in the Greater Society</em> (ITGS), is a project-based class where students explore multiple facets of the information technology industry: Web development, digital editing, open source, and related areas. The second group, <em>Students Working to Advance Trinity’s Technology</em> (SWAT), lives up to its name by ensuring that students and faculty make full use of the technology deployed by the school.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The students I met at Trinity High School are intelligent and ambitious. The &ldquo;toughest obstacle&rdquo; question prompted a great deal of thought. My toughest challenge is realizing that WisdomGroup has too many projects for me to know every detail. Therefore, I need to let go and let members of the team handle their areas as expertly as they always do. (The answer sounds good, but this is indeed a struggle, possibly worthy of a blog article.)</p>

<h3>Getting Started in Software Development</h3>

<p>For those students who attended this morning&rsquo;s presentations, here are the links that I promised you:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://education.github.com/pack">GitHub Student Developer Pack</a>.  Professional developer tools, offered for free to students.</li>
<li><a href="http://map.ipviking.com/">Internet attacks</a>. An animated map showing cyber attacks in real time.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.w3schools.com/">w3schools.com</a>. One place to start learning web development.</li>
</ul>


<p>And here are the slides from the presentation.</p>

<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="3c1eebc95b8f4eb4b81ae48826a8ab0e" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>




<br/>


<h3>About the Experience</h3>

<p>Students at Trinity are attentive and engaged. Their questions enable the learning experience to flow both ways, and the presenter learns as much as the audience. Thank you Trinity High School for a great experience!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to BLUE1647 and 1871]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T17:41:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When smart people<br/>
challenge each other to grow,<br/>
great things happen.<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
~The ChicagoRuby Motto</p></blockquote>

<p>If you’re a developer itchin’ to ramp up your Ruby skills, Chicago is a great place to be. The local Ruby user group, <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a>, continues to expand in time, space, expertise, and numbers. The group is over 3,200 strong, with six events each month <em>plus</em> the annual <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> conference.</p>

<p>The newest locations on ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s monthly list are BLUE1647 and 1871.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/blue1647.jpg' width='' height='' alt='BLUE1647' title='BLUE1647'><span class='caption-text'>BLUE1647</span></span>
<a href="http://www.blue1647.com/">BLUE 1647</a> is an amazing maker space on Chicago’s South Side, in the Pilsen neighborhood. The leadership of BLUE1647 invited ChicagoRuby to host our first meeting in the space on March 19, 2015. The presenter, <a href="https://twitter.com/johnnycon">John Contreras</a> of <a href="http://matchup.io">Matchup</a>, took us through the nuances of Rails background processing.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/rmillerwebster">Rebecca Miller-Webster</a> of <a href="http://thoughtbot.com">thoughtbot</a> will present at our next BLUE1647 meeting on April 17, 2015.</p>

<p>Check the <a href="http://meetup.com/chicagoruby">ChicagoRuby calendar</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<h3>ChicagoRuby: 1871</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/1871.jpg' width='' height='' alt='1871' title='1871'><span class='caption-text'>1871</span></span>
<a href="http://www.1871.com">1871</a> was an early player in Chicago&rsquo;s startup incubator industry. Community leaders at 1871 invited ChicagoRuby to lead some Ruby-oriented sessions at the incubator. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> will lead our first 1871 event on April 30, 2015.</p>

<h3>Organizer Team</h3>

<p>Eleven (yes, eleven!) organizers work in concert to make ChicagoRuby run well. Current members of the organizer team are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> &ndash; Started and co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/wondible">Justin Love</a> &ndash; Started in Elmhurst, acts as our liaison with the JavaScript community.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/themccreefiles">Alonda McCree</a> &ndash; Manages downtown video and logistics overall.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> &ndash; Runs Elmhurst and leads intro sessions at 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13059934/">Sarah Cnota</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker, manages the downtown meetups.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/HashtagLaToya">LaToya Allen</a> &ndash; Co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/bobbyreys">Bobby Reyes</a> &ndash; Driving force behind ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s activities at BLUE1647 and 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/185776457/">Dexter Teng</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker and newest member of the organizer team.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/rayhightower">Ray Hightower</a> &ndash; author of this article.</li>
</ul>


<p>ChicagoRuby excels because the work is shared amongst many people. Hats off to our <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org/about/organizers/">Organizer Alumni</a> too!</p>

<h3>Something For You</h3>

<p>As of this writing, ChicagoRuby manages six events per month. You are certain to find something that fits you.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Elmhurst</strong> &ndash; The first ChicagoRuby location. Meeting space provided by one of our members, Lee DeForest of DeForest Group.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Downtown</strong> &ndash; Currently at ThoughtWorks. Added when we merged with Chirb.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Hack Night</strong> &ndash; Currently at Enova. Added when Ginny Hendry said &ldquo;we should have hack nights&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: North Shore</strong> &ndash; Added when Doug Harman and Stu Gerstein said &ldquo;we should be on the North Shore&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</strong> &ndash; Added when Bobby Reyes formed relationships at the BLUE1647 maker space.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: 1871</strong> &ndash; Added when 1871 members asked ChicagoRuby to run some beginner-oriented sessions.</li>
</ul>


<p>Exact dates and locations are on the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/">ChicagoRuby calendar</a>. Come out and collaborate with your fellow learning enthusiasts. You&rsquo;ll be glad that you did.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
