<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-31T23:55:03-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flourish Open Source Conference at UIC]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/31/flourish-open-source-conference-at-uic/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T23:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/31/flourish-open-source-conference-at-uic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://flourishconf.com">Flourish</a> is an open source conference to be held at the University of Illinois at Chicago on Saturday, April 5, 2014. The conference is run by university students and tickets are free.</p>

<p>Thank you, Flourish organizers, for inviting me to speak this year. UIC is where I first learned about open source, Linux, and the web. My appreciation for UIC extends beyond my CS degree.</p>

<p>Why go to Flourish? Because&hellip;</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>You like open source.</li>
<li>You want to know more about open source.</li>
<li>You want to meet people who are passionate about open source.</li>
<li>All (or some combination) of the above.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Not Just Software</h3>

<p>Linux may be the best known open source project, but open source is not just about software. At Flourish 2009 a speaker mentioned a funny little circuit board called “Arduino” during one of the presentations. I turned to my neighbor in the audience, and I asked “What’s an Arduino?”</p>

<p>My neighbor pulled an Arduino out of his backpack and showed it to me. Wow. Open source extends to hardware, too! Since then, the Arduino has become part of the WindyCityRails Youth Program. Beyond microcontrollers, <a href="/blog/2012/12/03/ruby-on-raspberry-pi/">Raspeberry Pi</a>, <a href="/blog/2014/01/02/beaglebone-black-ubuntu-part-1/">Beaglebone Black</a>, and <a href="/blog/2013/06/22/preparing-for-parallella-64-cores-installing-go-on-mac-os-x/">Parallella</a> have joined the open source hardware ranks.</p>

<h3>See You There</h3>

<p>Great things happen when like-minded people come together to exchange ideas. I look forward to seeing you at Flourish 2014!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CocoaConf Chicago Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/10/cocoaconf-chicago-recap/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T11:46:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/03/10/cocoaconf-chicago-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/cocoaconf-2014.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Cool stuff from CocoaConf.' title='Cool stuff from CocoaConf.'><span class='caption-text'>Cool stuff from CocoaConf.</span></span></p>

<blockquote><p>One purpose of a conference is to help you to spot trends while there&rsquo;s still time to reap the benefits of being an early adopter.
&nbsp;<br/>
~Brian Marick at <a href="http://scna.softwarecraftsmanship.org/">SCNA 2013</a></p></blockquote>

<p>Early adopters on Apple&rsquo;s Mac OS X and iOS platforms flock to <a href="http://cocoaconf.com/">CocoaConf</a>, a multi-city conference for developers. Tickets are slightly easier to get than <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wwdc">WWDC</a>; CocoaConf consistently sells out.</p>

<p>CocoaConf&rsquo;s presenters are practicing developers, actively building real software every day. They come to CocoaConf to share their experiences in a wonderful upward-spiral of technical learning. Here are a few highlights from the latest CocoaConf, held March 7-8 near Chicago.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Customers Will Pay for Services</h3>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/justin">Justin Williams</a> kicked things off with a keynote titled <em>10 Things I Think I Think</em>. Williams recently acquired <a href="http://glassboard.com/">Glassboard</a>, so his developer skills are blended with the insights of a business owner. His list of ten included one approach to making money from mobile apps: Forget about selling a million copies in the App Store. Instead, create a service, charge a monthly fee for the service, and give the app away for free so customers can engage with the service. Engaged customers will continue to pay the monthly fee. When customers are served well, they will pay.</p>

<h3>Effective iOS 7 Networking</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/afnetworking-charles.png' width='' height='' alt='Charles shows network connections.' title='Charles shows network connections.'><span class='caption-text'>Charles shows network connections.</span></span>
Customer-focused mobile apps usually communicate with other software via the web. <a href="http://twitter.com/subdigital">Ben Scheirman</a> shared his experiences in building iOS apps that communicate with web services. Several questions are raised when we build apps like this, namely:</p>

<ul>
<li>How do we include communication capabilities without sacrificing performance?</li>
<li>If the mobile app requests information from a web service, and the service is unavailable (or slow) how do we avoid frustrating the user?</li>
</ul>


<p><code>NSURLSession</code>, introduced with iOS 7, lets us upload and download in the background. Users are kept happy because the app continues to function in the foreground. Scheirman&rsquo;s <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/subdigital/effective-network-programming-in-ios-7">slides</a> and <a href="https://github.com/subdigital/mods-2013">sample code</a> give more details.</p>

<p>It is also interesting to note what tools the presenters use in their
daily work. Scheirman uses <a href="http://www.charlesproxy.com/">Charles</a>
to monitor network traffic between machines, and to track down hiccups.</p>

<h3>Xcode Walkabout</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/xcode-git-commit.png' width='' height='' alt='Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.' title='Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.'><span class='caption-text'>Showing Git commit messages in Xcode.</span></span>
Most of my iOS time is spent with <a href="/blog/2013/01/12/why-i-use-vim/">Vim</a> and <a href="/blog/2012/10/29/building-ios-apps-with-ruby-motion/">RubyMotion</a>. I use Xcode mainly to learn things that I can apply to RubyMotion. Still, <a href="http://twitter.com/savinola">Laura Savino</a>&rsquo;s exploration of Xcode proved valuable.</p>

<p>Like many developers on the Apple platforms, Savino has a love/hate relationship with Xcode. She almost titled her talk &ldquo;stupid little buttons that don&rsquo;t even look like buttons.&rdquo; Savino summarized several years of Xcode immersion and pair programming into 60 minutes of little-known tips and tricks. For example, Xcode plays nicely with Git (you can even show commit messages within the IDE). And it&rsquo;s possible to use Vim key bindings while editing files.</p>

<h3>Sprite Kit</h3>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/kognate">Josh Smith</a>&rsquo;s Sprite Kit presentation was full of gotcha-eliminating information. For example, the coordinate systems for Sprite Kit and UIKit are inverted. I&rsquo;m sure this is documented somewhere, but I didn&rsquo;t know about it! The bottom line with Sprite Kit: We can add animation to our apps without doing all of the fundamental work. Saves time.</p>

<p>Slides and code are posted in a single <a href="https://github.com/kognate/presentations">repo on GitHub</a>. Worth looking at.</p>

<h3>Parallel Computing with OpenCL</h3>

<p>The parallel computing talk by <a href="http://twitter.com/hyperjeff">Jeff Biggus</a> was the most mind-blowing session of CocoaConf, for me. The presentation was exciting because it tied our current set of tools (like <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Performance/Reference/GCD_libdispatch_Ref/Reference/reference.html">GCD</a>) with high performance computing work currently underway at universities and at corporations like NVidia. When theory blends with application, great things can be achieved.</p>

<p>Biggus shared some of the work of <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opencl/">OpenCL</a>, a standard designed for cross-platform parallel computing. We care about parallel computing because&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Moore&rsquo;s Law has just about run its course.</li>
<li>Engineers have packed transistors about as tightly as they can on silicon.</li>
</ul>


<p>Unless we can figure out how to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montgomery_Scott">rewrite the laws of physics</a>, the next advances in computing performance will come from making processors work together without stepping on each other&rsquo;s toes.</p>

<h3>The Klein Family</h3>

<p>2014 marks CocoaConf&rsquo;s third year in the Chicago area. The conference is run by Dave and Debbie Klein and their 14 children. <a href="http://cocoaconf.com/family">About The Family Behind CocoaConf</a> gives details.</p>

<p>Thank you, Klein family, for another great CocoaConf!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SGI & Big Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/17/sgi-and-big-data/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-17T14:46:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/17/sgi-and-big-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/sgi-logo-1990s.png' width='' height='' alt='SGI&rsquo;s logo from the 1990s.' title='SGI&rsquo;s logo from the 1990s.'><span class='caption-text'>SGI&rsquo;s logo from the 1990s.</span></span>
<a href="http://sgi.com">Silicon Graphics International Corporation (SGI)</a> computers rendered the special effects for the original <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jurassic_Park">Jurassic Park</a> movie. Computer enthusiasts coveted SGI machines throughout the 1990s.</p>

<p>But success in the computer industry is fleeting. A few years after Jurassic Park, a convergence of tech advances (Moore&rsquo;s Law, x86 architecture, and Linux) made it possible for commodity PCs to perform as well as SGI&rsquo;s premium workstations. Wall Street traders and other power users abandoned workstations in favor of Linux-based PCs. High-end makers like SGI fell on hard times.</p>

<p>Today, SGI is fighting back. The company is blending x86, Linux, and (buzzword alert) big data to attack the high performance computing market. The vision was presented at this month&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.meetup.com/chicagoacm/events/163287562/">Chicago ACM</a> meeting by Brian Freed, VP of Strategy for SGI.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>What is Big Data?</h3>

<p>Freed shared a definition of big data from <a href="http://strata.oreilly.com/2012/01/what-is-big-data.html">Edd Dumbill&rsquo;s O'Reilly Radar article</a>. Big data is characterized by volume (lots of it), variety (it&rsquo;s unstructured), and velocity (the data changes quickly).</p>

<p>In the words of the O'Reilly author&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Big data is data that exceeds the processing capacity of conventional database systems. The data is too big, moves too fast, or doesn’t fit the strictures of your database architectures. To gain value from this data, you must choose an alternative way to process it.</p>

<p>~Edd Dumbill</p></blockquote>

<p>Definitions are fine, but it&rsquo;s more important to understand <em>why</em> a company might care about big data. Here are a few examples that Freed shared during the ACM meeting.</p>

<h3>Example: Fraud Detection with Big Data</h3>

<p>Consider one challenge faced by credit card companies. When a credit card is presented for an online purchase, how does the authorizing body know if the charge is legitimate? Can legitimacy be determined in a timely fashion, before an impatient buyer abandons a slow seller for a quicker seller?</p>

<p>Sellers who decide too quickly will suffer fraud. Sellers who decide too slowly will lose customers. The problem is amplified because millions of shoppers are clicking the &ldquo;buy now&rdquo; button simultaneously, and they all expect an answer <em>right now</em>.</p>

<p>Traditional fraud detection systems could measure just a few potential fraud criteria within the allowed time window. SGI solves the problem with <a href="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Hadoop clusters</a> running on SGI hardware. This big data design is able to examine each transaction deeper, and render a yes/no decision faster. Buyers are happier because they can complete a purchase faster. Companies are happier because fraud is reduced.</p>

<p>Big data helps credit card companies to make better authorization decisions in less time.</p>

<h3>Example: Auto Manufacturing</h3>

<p>Some problems, like credit authorization, require a quick response.  Other problems, like manufacturing, require the problem solver to crunch large volumes of data.</p>

<p>Consider an auto manufacturer. Every system in the modern automobile is controlled by software on silicon. Where software runs, data can be collected. The data piles up rapidly over time.</p>

<p>Manufacturers have discovered some unexpected benefits of collecting so much data. For example, they can identify trends like common failures among components, and use that data to improve future components. They can spot hidden trends, like geographic issues related to extreme cold or heat, and then design parts that are specially equipped for the target environment.</p>

<p>For these particular manufacturing examples, handling huge volumes of data is more important than delivering a quick answer. Insights that lead to quality improvements can be delivered in hours, and that&rsquo;s fast enough for the designers. Before big data, many design decisions were driven by instinct and experience alone. Big data helps auto companies to make more informed decisions.</p>

<h3>Pitfalls of Big Data</h3>

<p>One big pitfall is trying to use the big data <em>hammer</em> for every <em>nail</em> in sight, whether the solution fits the problem or not. It&rsquo;s the same hazard we face with any new technology. We run the risk of using a sledgehammer when a fly swatter would do.</p>

<p>A few ways to avoid the pitfalls: Start small. Have goals. And, like any good agile software developer, iterate. In Freed&rsquo;s words&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p>Successful implementation of big data is not an event. It is an iterative process where we continuously learn over time.</p></blockquote>

<h3>About Chicago ACM</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/chicagoacm/">The Chicago Chapter of the Association for Computing Machinery (Chicago ACM)</a> is on fire. December&rsquo;s meeting featured a supercomputing presentation by <a href="/blog/2013/12/12/high-performance-computing-at-acm/">Sharan Kalwani of Fermilab</a>. The February meeting was all about SGI&rsquo;s push into big data, and next month will focus on the Internet of Things (IoT). The organizers are assembling an exciting combination of events. Looking forward to more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Controversial Coding Topics at 8th Light]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/03/exploring-controversial-coding-topics-at-8th-light/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T12:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/03/exploring-controversial-coding-topics-at-8th-light</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://8thlight.com">8th Light</a> recently hosted a panel discussion on Controversial Coding Topics. I was honored to share the panel with two technology leaders whom I admire: <a href="http://twitter.com/markrickmeier">Mark Rickmeier</a> of <a href="http://tablexi.com">Table XI</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/coreyhaines">Corey Haines</a> of <a href="http://wavetable.com">Wavetable</a>. <a href="http://twitter.com/little_fig">Rachel Feigenbaum</a> of 8th Light organized the event.</p>

<!--more-->


<center><iframe src="http://RayHightower.com//player.vimeo.com/video/84793305" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Topics Covered</h3>

<p>Some of the topics covered during the discussion:</p>

<ul>
<li>Hiring. What do you look for when building a team?</li>
<li>Establishing team standards.</li>
<li>Balancing professional time with personal time. Don&rsquo;t work 12-hour
days!</li>
</ul>


<h3>Gratitude</h3>

<p>Thank you 8th Light for making this happen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Environment of Respect, 2nd Iteration]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/01/28/an-environment-of-respect-2nd-iteration/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T07:08:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/01/28/an-environment-of-respect-2nd-iteration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thank you to everyone who offered feedback on <a href="/blog/2014/01/21/an-environment-of-respect/">An Environment of Respect</a>, which included an early draft of the WindyCityRails Code of Conduct.</p>

<p>The frank and earnest exchange of ideas was educational. Some of the feedback was positive, on the order of &ldquo;we&rsquo;re all colleagues, we treat each other with respect, that&rsquo;s good.&rdquo;</p>

<p>However, I paid special attention to the negative feedback because it surprised me. Surprise happens when I face something that I do not understand. When I encounter something that I do not understand, there&rsquo;s an opportunity for learning.</p>

<p>So I did what I always do when I need to learn more. I spoke with people who know more than me.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Wise Counsel</h3>

<p>Several people in our industry were generous when I asked for advice. One technology veteran summed it up this way:</p>

<blockquote><p>You wrote a code of conduct for an Environment of Respect. 99.9% of the people will know what that means, and they can even function well without a code. But a code of conduct needs to written for an Environment of Hostility&hellip; for the one fool who doesn&rsquo;t know how to act.</p></blockquote>

<p>In a discussion about reducing bureaucracy, one developer offered this view:</p>

<blockquote><p>Think of it less as bureaucracy and more along the lines of “In case of emergency, break glass and help is on the way.”</p></blockquote>

<p>I am grateful to everyone who took the time to share their thoughts.</p>

<h3>Verbose and Draconian? Not Here.</h3>

<p>Some of the advice seemed to point toward a more verbose and draconian code of conduct, like the ones suggested by a few people last week. Not good. If we have a code, it&rsquo;s better to avoid the threatening tone. WindyCityRails is a community of colleagues who treat each other with respect.</p>

<p>Fortunately, one member of our team found a code that works. Every member of the community is treated like an independent-thinking adult who respects the rights of others. Expectations are clear, and the threatening tone is gone.</p>

<h3>Ruby DCamp: Thanks</h3>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/elight">Evan Light</a> wrote the original version of this code of conduct for <a href="http://rubydcamp.org/">Ruby DCamp</a>. When asked for permission to use his work for WindyCityRails, Evan responded with an enthusiastic <em>yes</em>. Thanks Evan!</p>

<p>Here it is.</p>

<h3>Draft: Code of Conduct</h3>

<h4>Preface</h4>

<p>WindyCityRails is and has been an event made up of welcoming, tolerant, compassionate, and loving participants. For several years now, WindyCityRails participants have been respectful of one another in our differences. We have employed those differences to elevate, educate, and celebrate one another at WindyCityRails.</p>

<p>It is in that same spirit that we now adopt this Code of Conduct: Not as a punitive action, but as a measure to protect that which we already have and to signal to all that we are a tolerant and loving community.</p>

<h4>WindyCityRails Code of Conduct</h4>

<p>WindyCityRails is dedicated to providing a harassment-free conference experience for everyone, regardless of gender, gender identity, sexual orientation, disability, physical appearance, body size, race, or religion. We do not tolerate harassment of participants in any form.</p>

<p>If you think your conversation is making another community member uncomfortable, try to make amends and move forward.</p>

<p>Participants asked to stop any harassing behavior are expected to comply immediately. WindyCityRails participants violating these rules may be sanctioned or expelled from the conference at the event organizers' discretion. This applies to all attendees, speakers, sponsors, and otherwise.</p>

<p>That said, silliness, mockery, and general irreverence are welcome, expected, and even encouraged so long as they all come from a loving place.</p>

<p>However, should another participant&rsquo;s behavior be injurious to you, we ask three things.</p>

<h4>1) Give others the benefit of the doubt.</h4>

<p>People are generally decent. It has been our experience, these past several years, that those who attend WindyCityRails are just a cut above in that respect.</p>

<h4>2) Attempt to address the behavior with the other party immediately.</h4>

<p>In the case of intractable situations, we are here to help you (see &ldquo;Ask for Help!&rdquo; below). However, this is where we ask participants to try to behave &ldquo;like grown ups.&rdquo; It is part of the WindyCityRails ethos: If you have a problem with something, don&rsquo;t wait for someone to fix it but instead try to fix it yourself.</p>

<p>If you’re comfortable doing so, let the person know that you found what he or she said or did inappropriate. Attempt to resolve the situation amicably. When addressing it yourself, remember to continue to treat the other party with kindness and respect.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re uncomfortable approaching the other person…</p>

<h4>3) Ask for Help!</h4>

<p>We&rsquo;re all human. While life, and WindyCityRails, expects a good deal of self-sufficiency, we are also a community. If you cannot manage a situation alone, we are here for you. Seek out any member of the conference organizer team. We can be identified with special &ldquo;Organizer&rdquo; lanyards.</p>

<p>~WindyCityRails Organizers Team</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Thanks for reading this through. See you at <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
