<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-19T18:03:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to BLUE1647 and 1871]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T17:41:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/04/10/chicagoruby-blue1647-1871</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>When smart people<br/>
challenge each other to grow,<br/>
great things happen.<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
~The ChicagoRuby Motto</p></blockquote>

<p>If you’re a developer itchin’ to ramp up your Ruby skills, Chicago is a great place to be. The local Ruby user group, <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org">ChicagoRuby</a>, continues to expand in time, space, expertise, and numbers. The group is over 3,200 strong, with six events each month <em>plus</em> the annual <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a> conference.</p>

<p>The newest locations on ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s monthly list are BLUE1647 and 1871.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/blue1647.jpg' width='' height='' alt='BLUE1647' title='BLUE1647'><span class='caption-text'>BLUE1647</span></span>
<a href="http://www.blue1647.com/">BLUE 1647</a> is an amazing maker space on Chicago’s South Side, in the Pilsen neighborhood. The leadership of BLUE1647 invited ChicagoRuby to host our first meeting in the space on March 19, 2015. The presenter, <a href="https://twitter.com/johnnycon">John Contreras</a> of <a href="http://matchup.io">Matchup</a>, took us through the nuances of Rails background processing.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/rmillerwebster">Rebecca Miller-Webster</a> of <a href="http://thoughtbot.com">thoughtbot</a> will present at our next BLUE1647 meeting on April 17, 2015.</p>

<p>Check the <a href="http://meetup.com/chicagoruby">ChicagoRuby calendar</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<h3>ChicagoRuby: 1871</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/1871.jpg' width='' height='' alt='1871' title='1871'><span class='caption-text'>1871</span></span>
<a href="http://www.1871.com">1871</a> was an early player in Chicago&rsquo;s startup incubator industry. Community leaders at 1871 invited ChicagoRuby to lead some Ruby-oriented sessions at the incubator. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> will lead our first 1871 event on April 30, 2015.</p>

<h3>Organizer Team</h3>

<p>Eleven (yes, eleven!) organizers work in concert to make ChicagoRuby run well. Current members of the organizer team are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> &ndash; Started and co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/wondible">Justin Love</a> &ndash; Started in Elmhurst, acts as our liaison with the JavaScript community.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/themccreefiles">Alonda McCree</a> &ndash; Manages downtown video and logistics overall.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/1345203/">Marty Lavin</a> &ndash; Runs Elmhurst and leads intro sessions at 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13059934/">Sarah Cnota</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker, manages the downtown meetups.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/HashtagLaToya">LaToya Allen</a> &ndash; Co-organizes the ChicagoRuby Hack Nights.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> &ndash; Co-organizes ChicagoRuby: North Shore.</li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/bobbyreys">Bobby Reyes</a> &ndash; Driving force behind ChicagoRuby&rsquo;s activities at BLUE1647 and 1871.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/185776457/">Dexter Teng</a> &ndash; ThoughtWorker and newest member of the organizer team.</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.com/rayhightower">Ray Hightower</a> &ndash; author of this article.</li>
</ul>


<p>ChicagoRuby excels because the work is shared amongst many people. Hats off to our <a href="http://www.chicagoruby.org/about/organizers/">Organizer Alumni</a> too!</p>

<h3>Something For You</h3>

<p>As of this writing, ChicagoRuby manages six events per month. You are certain to find something that fits you.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Elmhurst</strong> &ndash; The first ChicagoRuby location. Meeting space provided by one of our members, Lee DeForest of DeForest Group.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Downtown</strong> &ndash; Currently at ThoughtWorks. Added when we merged with Chirb.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: Hack Night</strong> &ndash; Currently at Enova. Added when Ginny Hendry said &ldquo;we should have hack nights&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: North Shore</strong> &ndash; Added when Doug Harman and Stu Gerstein said &ldquo;we should be on the North Shore&rdquo;.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: BLUE1647</strong> &ndash; Added when Bobby Reyes formed relationships at the BLUE1647 maker space.</li>
<li><strong>ChicagoRuby: 1871</strong> &ndash; Added when 1871 members asked ChicagoRuby to run some beginner-oriented sessions.</li>
</ul>


<p>Exact dates and locations are on the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/">ChicagoRuby calendar</a>. Come out and collaborate with your fellow learning enthusiasts. You&rsquo;ll be glad that you did.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep the Fun in Computing]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T20:12:17-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/25/keep-the-fun-in-computing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;I think that it’s extraordinarily important that we in computer science keep fun in computing&hellip; What’s in your hands, I think and hope, is intelligence: the ability to see the machine as more than when you were first led up to it, that you can make it more.&rdquo;
<br/>&nbsp;
~ Alan J. Perlis,
from the Dedication page in SICP</p></blockquote>

<p>Enrolling in the <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Chicago SICP study group</a>, I expected to dive into Lisp. I expected to be challenged. What I didn’t expect: The fun, somewhat irreverent attitude of the SICP authors. And why not? Software development is one of our newest professions. Other professionals are made more effective through our work. Everybody benefits from the increase in productivity.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>If you are a software developer in the Chicago area, be sure to check out <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">the SICP group</a>. As the SICP authors say, you don’t need to know Lisp to embark on this path; you’ll learn Lisp as we travel along. And our brains will be stretched in new and interesting ways.</p>

<p>What an exciting time to be alive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SICP Study Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-18T15:15:25-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/02/18/sicp-study-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/sicp.jpg' width='' height='' alt='SICP' title='SICP'><span class='caption-text'>SICP</span></span>
Veteran developer <a href="http://twitter.com/dastels">Dave Astels</a> is leading a <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/sicp-chicago-w-dave-astels-tickets-15525870296">Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs (SICP) study group</a> for the next ten months. The Massachusetts Institute of Technology uses SICP as the text for one of its early computer science courses. Session one of Dave’s group starts today at 6pm. For any developer who wants to ramp up in skill, the SICP study group is an excellent opportunity to do so.</p>

<p>MIT makes the <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">entire text of SICP</a> available online for free. Or you can buy a paper version of the book at Amazon.</p>

<p>Thank you <a href="http://www.bradsdeals.com/">Brad’s Deals</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/lostghost">Ken Walters</a> for hosting the SICP group.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Installing Scheme on Mac OS X</h3>

<p>Examples and exercises in SICP are written in Scheme, a dialect of the LISP programming language. As of this writing, installing <code>mit-scheme</code> via Homebrew <em>did not work for me</em>.</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
~$ brew install mit-scheme
Error: No available formula for mit-scheme
Searching formulae&hellip;
Searching taps&hellip;
homebrew/x11/mit-scheme</p>

<p>~$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p><em>Update: Some members of the SICP study group had success installing <code>mit-scheme</code> with Homebrew, while others (like me) did not. We did not determine why some of the Homebrew installations were successful. However, the non-Homebrew method described in this article seems to work across-the-board.</em></p>

<p>Alternative solution: Grab a pre-compiled binary from the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/mit-scheme/">MIT/GNU Scheme</a> site. The <code>mit-scheme-9.2-x86-64.dmg</code> disk image was the right one for my early 2013 MacBook Pro. Your system may be different.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/gnu_float.png' width='' height='' alt='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.' title='Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.'><span class='caption-text'>Opening the MIT/GNU Scheme disk image.</span></span></p>

<p>To install, drag the <code>MIT/GNU Scheme.app</code> icon into the Applications folder on the Mac.</p>

<h3>Setting Up Symlinks</h3>

<p>Scheme is run from the command line. In order to make that work, we need to setup two symbolic links.</p>

<p>First, create a symbolic link called <code>mit-scheme-x86-64</code> in your home directory that links to the appropriate executable in the <code>/Applications</code> directory. In other words&hellip;</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ sudo ln -s /Applications/MIT\:GNU\ Scheme.app/Contents/Resources /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64
Password:</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>Next, setup a symlink that will let us simply type <code>scheme</code> when we want to use this version of the language&hellip;</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ sudo ln -s /usr/local/lib/mit-scheme-x86-64/mit-scheme /usr/bin/scheme</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>Confirm that the links are in place by checking the <code>scheme</code> version number.</p>

<p>&#8220;` bash
$ scheme &mdash;version
MIT/GNU Scheme microcode 15.3
Copyright &copy; 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions. There is NO warranty; not even for
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</p>

<p>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
  Release 9.2 || Microcode 15.3 || Runtime 15.7 || SF 4.41 || LIAR/x86-64 4.118 || Edwin 3.116</p>

<p>Moriturus te saluto.</p>

<p>$</p>

<p>&#8220;`</p>

<p>If you are like me, you will laugh at the gladiator message at the end of the version info.</p>

<h3>Better Way to Symlink?</h3>

<p>Why not create a single symbolic link directly from the <code>Resources</code> directory to the <code>scheme</code> command in <code>/usr/bin</code>? I am not certain, but I suspect it has something to do with expectations within the Scheme interpreter. The interpreter may be expecting certain files to be in certain directories. I’ll update this article when I learn more.</p>

<h3>Running Scheme</h3>

<p>To start the Scheme read-evaluate-print-loop (REPL)&hellip;</p>

<p><code>`` bash
$ scheme
MIT/GNU Scheme running under OS X
Type</code>^C&#8217; (control-C) followed by `H&#8217; to obtain information about interrupts.</p>

<p>Copyright &copy; 2014 Massachusetts Institute of Technology
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions. There is NO warranty; not even for
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</p>

<p>Image saved on Saturday May 17, 2014 at 2:39:25 AM
  Release 9.2 || Microcode 15.3 || Runtime 15.7 || SF 4.41 || LIAR/x86-64 4.118 || Edwin 3.116</p>

<p>1 ]=></p>

<p><code>``
Exit the REPL by typing</code>CTRL-D`.</p>

<p>Looking forward to SICP tonight!</p>

<h3>Acknowledgement</h3>

<p>Thanks <a href="https://jacksonisaac.wordpress.com/2014/03/25/installing-scheme-on-mac-os-x/">Jackson Isaac</a> for the information about symlinks as used with this version of scheme.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WindyCityRails and You]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/31/windycityrails-and-you/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T06:11:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/31/windycityrails-and-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have ever attended <a href="http://windycityrails.org">WindyCityRails</a>: Thank you for helping to make the event more exciting every year. Organizers strive to give developers actionable technical information in a conference format. So far, it&rsquo;s working!</p>

<!--more-->


<p>2015 marks our first year with a pre-conference survey. Length: Four questions. Answer as many as you like via the quick <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/XHF85YN">online form</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li>What web-related technologies are you most excited about this year?</li>
<li>What web-related technology is giving you the biggest headaches right now?</li>
<li>Are there any particular speakers you&rsquo;d like to see at WindyCityRails 2015?</li>
<li>What social networks do you actively use?</li>
</ol>


<p>Please <a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/XHF85YN">stop by and fill out the survey</a> when you can.</p>

<p>We look forward to hearing from you. And we look forward to delivering another strong year at WindyCityRails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Context Changes Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T17:48:08-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some cases where time zone information is absolutely critical. For example: When scheduling a video conference that crosses national boundaries.</p>

<p>A few hours ago, Google sent me a reminder about today&rsquo;s <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> meeting. The group meets via video conferencing software over the web. Google&rsquo;s reminder was confusing because it showed the time without the time zone (screenshot below). LinuxBarbados is based in the Caribbean, and some of the members participate from other time zones.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/GH_time_zone_arrow.png' width='' height='' alt='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?' title='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?'><span class='caption-text'>What time is it when the time zone is unknown?</span></span></p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s automated reminder said <code>3pm - 4pm</code> with no time zone reference. How confusing! Members of the group received the same automated reminder with the same information, regardless of time zone. A small change, displaying the time as <code>3pm - 4pm (CST)</code> would solve the problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Other Context Examples</h3>

<p>When people speak with each other directly, context is implied. But when communication happens in printed form, it&rsquo;s helpful to have the context in print, too. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Walking down the street, you see a poster advertising a concert on January 29th. No year is shown. Is this an old poster for a concert that happened last year on Jan 29th? Or is the event happening next week?</li>
<li>A restaurant menu offers delivery service. Just call the number, and order your food. The phone number is seven digits long, with no area code. Most customers would abandon the menu in favor of a restaurant with more complete information.</li>
<li>Following the train of thought in the previous example: Since phone service has fallen in price, many people call internationally on a more regular basis. A complete phone number should include the country code.</li>
</ul>


<p>Context changes everything. Something all of us need to remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
