<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Community | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/community/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-18T21:56:43-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ignite RubyConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T15:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/11/16/ignite-rubyconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/ignite_logo_200.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.' title='Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.'><span class='caption-text'>Ignite. 15 seconds per slide.</span></span>
<a href="http://igniteshow.com/">Ignite</a> is a presentation format where the slides advance automatically every 15 seconds whether the presenter is ready or not. Twenty slides, 15 seconds each, five minutes total. Presenters are challenged to present their ideas quickly and clearly before the time runs out.</p>

<p>Ignite is similar to <a href="http://www.pechakucha.org">Pecha Kucha</a>. The two formats differ only in slide duration (20 seconds per slide with Pecha Kucha).</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.sdruby.org/">SDRuby</a> ran an Ignite event on the day before RubyConf 2014. Slides from my OpenROV presentation at Ignite RubyConf 2014 appear below.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="573c89704e88013264a612c8f4a94aec" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>&nbsp;<br/>
&nbsp;<br/>
Thanks SDRuby for hosting the Ignite event!</p>

<p>If you like the idea of hacking on Ruby <em>and</em> OpenROV, check out <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ChicagoRuby Expands to North Shore]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T14:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/30/chicagoruby-expands-to-north-shore</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long-time observers of ChicagoRuby know that the group is always striving to achieve more. Latest move: ChicagoRuby is now hosting a monthly meetup on Chicago’s North Shore. The first meeting of ChicagoRuby: North Shore will be held on Saturday, December 6, 2014 at 10:30am. Visit <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/events/216193202/">Meetup.com</a> for details and to RSVP.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Why the North Shore?</h3>

<p>Why expand to Chicago’s North Shore? One reason: Several ChicagoRuby members live there, and travelling to meetings downtown and in Elmhurst can be quite a haul.</p>

<p>The bigger reason: Two members have stepped up to manage the north shore operation. <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/61690512/">Doug Harman</a> and <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ChicagoRuby/members/13463131/">Stu Gerstein</a> have been active in Elmhurst for a long time. They were chosen as organizers because they are vocal and they have already done the preliminary leg work.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how we roll in ChicagoRuby. Many years ago, <a href="https://twitter.com/ginnyhendry">Ginny Hendry</a> demonstrated that if you push for a new activity in ChicagoRuby (like hack nights) you might end up running it!</p>

<h3>Exciting Year</h3>

<p>2014 has proven to be an exciting year for ChicagoRuby. So far, the group has…</p>

<ul>
<li>Collaborated with the University of the West Indies at Cave Hill, Barbados to form <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a>.</li>
<li>Built alliances with top-notch developers in multiple countries to create <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</li>
<li>Expanded the monthly Chicago-area activities to four per month.</li>
<li>Grown the organizer team to ten (10) members.</li>
</ul>


<p>Looking forward to more!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geekfest &amp; OpenROV]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T09:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/21/geekfest-and-openrov</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/geekfest.png' width='' height='' alt='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.' title='Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.'><span class='caption-text'>Geekfest: Tuesdays at Groupon.</span></span>
<a href="http://www.meetup.com/Geekfest/events/207936312/">Geekfest</a> is a weekly event hosted by Groupon&rsquo;s engineering team. Every Tuesday at lunchtime, the company invites members of the tech community to present topics that are interesting to a technical audience.</p>

<p>I wish to express my thanks to Groupon for inviting me to present <a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> at today&rsquo;s Geekfest.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Slides appear below. Video will be posted as soon as it becomes available. Special thanks to <a href="http://chelseatroy.com/2014/10/21/geekfest-ray-hightower-dumps-a-robot-into-lake-michigan/">Chelsea Troy</a> for creating a real-time blog post about the presentation.</p>

<center><iframe src="http://RayHightower.com//player.vimeo.com/video/112204897" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>




<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="e8ed21a03b5d013274bd1297e85160ca" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UWI Computer Science Club &amp; LinuxBarbados]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/10/uwi-computer-science-club-and-linuxbarbados/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-10T03:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/10/10/uwi-computer-science-club-and-linuxbarbados</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Members of the <a href="http://cavehill.uwi.edu/">University of the West Indies (UWI)</a> Computer Science Club and <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> just finished a joint session this afternoon. I am grateful that the group invited me to present. Outline (prepared in advance):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>30 minutes: Overview of Ruby, Rails, and some alternatives to both. What are the advantages and disadvantages of building web apps with Ruby? Can you build a business with this stuff?</p></li>
<li><p>30 minutes: Questions and Answers. This will be a highly interactive time. Anything discussed earlier is fair game. We can explore technical specifics if you like.</p></li>
<li><p>60 minutes: Deep dive into anything the group wants to explore related to technology, business, or the combination of the two. If the group doesn&rsquo;t choose a topic, we will end early. But if the group is interested and engaged, we will continue.</p></li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Slides from the presentation are posted here.</p>

<center><script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="ba46e5b032a001322feb4edc433df659" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://RayHightower.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script></center>


<p>Thank you UWI for the invitation!</p>

<p>If you want to know more about these subjects, and if you would like to study this material in a hands-on lab environment with experts guiding the way, you might enjoy <a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RubyCaribe: Ruby Gets Hotter in January]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/23/rubycaribe-ruby-gets-hotter-in-january/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T18:23:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/09/23/rubycaribe-ruby-gets-hotter-in-january</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://rubycaribe.com">RubyCaribe</a> (pronounced ka-REEB) is a conference for intermediate and advanced software developers who use Ruby. The conference will be held January 27 &ndash; 31, 2015 in Barbados. January is a beautiful time to visit the Caribbean, especially if you’re coming from a colder part of the planet.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/barbados_caribbean_map.png' width='' height='' alt='Barbados. You could be here in January.' title='Barbados. You could be here in January.'><span class='caption-text'>Barbados. You could be here in January.</span></span>
Intermediate and advanced software developers will find RubyCaribe valuable because&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li>Each RubyCaribe session features a 30- to 45-minute presentation followed by a <em>2-hour deep-dive lab</em>. Learning is reinforced throughout.</li>
<li>The venue, <a href="http://www.hiltonbarbadosresort.com/">Hilton Barbados Resort</a>, sits right on the ocean. Need a stretch break? Take a walk on the beach!</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<h3>Ramp Up Your Ruby Skills</h3>

<p>Each RubyCaribe lab will be led by experts in machine learning, mobile app development (iOS and Android), web development, and functional programming. The inventor of <a href="http://rubymotion.com">RubyMotion</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/lrz">Laurent Sansonetti</a>, will lead the RubyMotion lab. If you already have experience with Ruby or Rails, RubyCaribe will take your skills to the next level.</p>

<h3>Bonus: OpenROV and Node.js</h3>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/openrov_rubycaribe.jpg' width='' height='' alt='OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.' title='OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.'><span class='caption-text'>OpenROV. Linux and Node.js.</span></span>
<a href="/blog/2014/06/16/citizen-science-with-openrov/">OpenROV</a> is an open source underwater robot running Linux and Node.js. During two evening sessions, you and your RubyCaribe colleagues will hack on OpenROV. The best developers are polyglot, right? On Friday afternoon, we will grab a boat for live ocean testing with a few OpenROV units. If you ever wanted to experiment with Node.js and IoT, RubyCaribe offers a great opportunity.</p>

<h3>University Collaboration</h3>

<p>On Saturday, the final day of RubyCaribe, we will visit the <a href="http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/">University of the West Indies at Cave Hill</a>. Faculty and students from the UWI community will demo their work with solar energy and other areas touched by software. Who knows, maybe you’ll give a lightning talk about something you learned at RubyCaribe!</p>

<h3>Make Your Brain Sweat</h3>

<p>RubyCaribe will work you hard. RubyCaribe will make your brain sweat. So be sure to schedule a few days before or after the conference for sight seeing and relaxation. Rum was invented in Barbados.</p>

<h3>Where Will You Be in January?</h3>

<p>If you had to choose between the Caribbean and the cold regions of the northern hemisphere, where would you rather be? RubyCaribe offers the chance to ramp up your skills and enjoy yourself at the same time. What an opportunity.</p>

<h3>Only One Hundred Tickets</h3>

<p>Only one hundred tickets will be sold. Be sure to get yours. <a href="http://www.eventbrite.com/e/rubycaribe-2015-registration-10051344843">Register now</a>. See you at RubyCaribe!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
