<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Business | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-31T12:57:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Controversial Coding Topics at 8th Light]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/03/exploring-controversial-coding-topics-at-8th-light/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-03T12:11:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/02/03/exploring-controversial-coding-topics-at-8th-light</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://8thlight.com">8th Light</a> recently hosted a panel discussion on Controversial Coding Topics. I was honored to share the panel with two technology leaders whom I admire: <a href="http://twitter.com/markrickmeier">Mark Rickmeier</a> of <a href="http://tablexi.com">Table XI</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/coreyhaines">Corey Haines</a> of <a href="http://wavetable.com">Wavetable</a>. <a href="http://twitter.com/little_fig">Rachel Feigenbaum</a> of 8th Light organized the event.</p>

<!--more-->


<center><iframe src="http://RayHightower.com//player.vimeo.com/video/84793305" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Topics Covered</h3>

<p>Some of the topics covered during the discussion:</p>

<ul>
<li>Hiring. What do you look for when building a team?</li>
<li>Establishing team standards.</li>
<li>Balancing professional time with personal time. Don&rsquo;t work 12-hour
days!</li>
</ul>


<h3>Gratitude</h3>

<p>Thank you 8th Light for making this happen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Henry Ford's Faster Horse]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/01/15/henry-ford-faster-horse/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-15T13:49:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/01/15/henry-ford-faster-horse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/ford-model-t-1910.jpg' width='' height='' alt='1910 Ford Model T' title='1910 Ford Model T'><span class='caption-text'>1910 Ford Model T</span></span></p>

<blockquote><p>If I had asked people what they wanted, they would have asked for a faster horse.</p>

<p>~Henry Ford</p></blockquote>

<p>The above Henry Ford quote is often cited in presentations about innovation. The point of the quote: An inventor who listens to customers too closely, without observing customer behavior, will reap tiny improvements at best. Ford ignored the request for &ldquo;a faster horse&rdquo;, and that is how the Ford Motor Company became a leader in the early auto industry.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s one way to interpret Ford&rsquo;s quote. Last night, I was introduced to another view.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Parse the Quote Differently, Don&rsquo;t Ignore it</h3>

<p>Last night&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.ixdachicago.org">IxDA Chicago</a> meeting featured a presentation by <a href="http://chris-holmes.com">Chris Holmes</a>, who shared a different view of the Ford quote. If we focus on improving the speed of horses (perhaps through nutrition or better horse shoes) very little improvement can be achived.</p>

<p>But something interesting happens when we parse the quote differently. The adjective <em>faster</em> reveals the customer&rsquo;s true need. The noun <em>horse</em> is the customer&rsquo;s &ldquo;solution&rdquo; based on what they currently know about the world. For the innovator, <em>faster</em> stands out. Focusing on <em>faster</em> leads to innovation.</p>

<h3>Focus on Faster</h3>

<p><em>Faster</em> tells us that we can stretch beyond our current thinking and consider other modes of transportation. Focusing on <em>faster</em> led to the beginning of the automobile industry.</p>

<p>Customers are communicating their desires all the time. We need to listen carefully and parse well. Thanks IxDA Chicago and Chris Holmes for the lesson.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disposable Electronics in Wired Magazine]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/28/disposable-electronics-in-wired-magazine/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-28T14:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/28/disposable-electronics-in-wired-magazine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What can we build with disposable electronics? An ad in the January 2014 issue of <a href="http://wired.com">Wired Magazine</a> lets the reader change the color of a Moto X smartphone by pressing a colored circle on the page. This 20-second video shows the ad in operation followed by a glimpse of the inner workings.</p>

<center><iframe width="640" height="480" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/MkphhEu44sA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<!--more-->


<h3>Inner Workings</h3>

<p>Taking the ad apart required one simple tool, a pair of scissors. Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s inside:</p>

<ul>
<li>Four 3-volt CR2025 lithium coin batteries. This kind of battery is commonly used to power the remote key fob for an automobile. Walgreens sells these batteries.</li>
<li>One tiny circuit board, about 1-inch square. I see nine resistors, four capacitors, one diode, and one application-specific integrated circuit (ASIC). The designation <code>C0010-V1</code> is printed on the board. Nothing shows the board&rsquo;s manufacturer.</li>
<li>Eleven switches in one switch assembly. The switches are connected to the circuit board via seven leads.</li>
<li>Three LEDs, pointed to shine light on a 3.5" x 6.5" reflecting panel.</li>
</ul>


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/moto-x-wired-ad.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.' title='Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.'><span class='caption-text'>Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.</span></span></p>

<p>This assembly is more expensive than a typical full-page ad, but probably not by much. Mildly amusing to play with, and fun to take apart. Yes, the advertisers succeded in grabbing my attention.</p>

<h3>Advertising ROI?</h3>

<p>A famous ad expert once remarked, &ldquo;Half the money I spend on advertising is wasted. The trouble is I don&rsquo;t know which half.&rdquo; Is the Moto X ad useful or wasted?</p>

<p>An observation: I played with this paper gadget for a good ten minutes and I took the thing apart <em>before</em> I considered reading the ad copy. Maybe the color change is too distracting for the ad to be effective? Maybe the temptation to disassemble the ad is too distracting, too.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I&rsquo;m still talking about the ad. And blogging about it. Ultimate test: How will an ad like this influence buying behavior?</p>

<p>Beyond advertising, what else can we do with disposable electronics?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon's Guerrilla Marketing]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/02/amazon-guerrilla-marketing/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-02T20:03:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/02/amazon-guerrilla-marketing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night&rsquo;s episode of 60 Minutes featured an interview with Jeff Bezos, CEO of Amazon. The timing was perfect for Amazon. Black Friday was a few days ago. Cyber Monday is today. Online retailers want to be top-of-mind when people are inclined to spend money.</p>

<h3>Amazon&rsquo;s Surprise: Drones</h3>

<p>Bezos unveiled a surprise for interviewer Charlie Rose: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/b?ref_=tsm_1_tw_s_amzn_mx3eqp&amp;node=8037720011">Amazon Prime Air</a>, a service that will deliver most Amazon products in thirty minutes or less using a fleet of octocopter drones.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/amazon-prime-air-drone.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.' title='Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.'><span class='caption-text'>Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.</span></span></p>

<h3>Guerrilla Marketing</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.gmarketing.com/">Jay Conrad Levinson</a>, author of <em>Guerrilla Marketing</em>, would applaud this move by Amazon. Amazon Prime Air is two years away at the earliest. The flying drones require Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) approval, and that takes time. By unveiling the drones now, before approval, Amazon reaps several benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Buzz. Everybody is talking about Amazon on Cyber Monday.</li>
<li>Political influence. Some of the people feeling the buzz are FAA officials.</li>
<li>Continued top-of-mind awareness. Long after Cyber Monday, the excitement of the drone idea will carry on.</li>
</ul>


<p>Congrats to the Amazon team for a well-executed Guerrilla Marketing move.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Specialized Knowledge and the Courage to Execute]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/30/specialized-knowledge-and-the-courage-to-execute/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T10:35:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/30/specialized-knowledge-and-the-courage-to-execute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Teenagers are a tough audience. If you have ever spoken to a youth group, you know the challenge: Speak about something important without putting the youth to sleep. Tall order.</p>

<h3>Three Stories</h3>

<p>Boy Scout <a href="http://troop534.org">Troop 534 &ldquo;Hey!&rdquo;</a> asked me to speak at the Troop’s annual reunion breakfast this year.  I approached them with three stories centered around the theme of <em>Specialized Knowledge and the Courage to Execute</em>. What a boring title! But the three stories appealed to the group. Here’s a summary of the first story:</p>

<blockquote><p>A tractor maker takes drastic action when when Enzo Ferrari (creator of the Ferrari sports car) pisses him off.</p></blockquote>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&rsquo;s the 11-minute video:</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/tWdFhEI6JiM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Gratitude</h3>

<p>This event was a big deal for me because I grew up in Troop 534 &ldquo;Hey!&rdquo;, I currently serve as one of the adult leaders, and the breakfast organizers normally invite an outsider to speak. Why listen to a speaker who you see all the time?</p>

<p>I took the speaking invitation as an opportunity to assemble some new material. Thank you scouts, parents, and leaders for having me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
