<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-28T16:16:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon Dash and Instant Gratification]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/31/amazon-dash-and-instant-gratification/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-31T15:44:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/31/amazon-dash-and-instant-gratification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/amazon_dash_combo_cc_600.png' width='' height='' alt='Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.' title='Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.'><span class='caption-text'>Amazon Dash innovates by building on existing technologies.</span></span></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/oc/dash-button">Amazon Dash Button</a> is for customers who crave instant gratification. We might think of Dash as a brilliant blend of the Staples Easy Button, WiFi, and Amazon&rsquo;s existing database of credit card numbers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>When a customer runs out of a consumable item, they press a button. The order is sent immediately via WiFi to Amazon, where the customer&rsquo;s credit card number is on file. Delivery can happen within 24 hours, depending on the item. No more standing in line at the store. In fact, no more walking a few feet to a computer to type in an order. Instant gratification, satisfied.</p>

<h3>Video Summary</h3>

<p>This 1-minute video explains the service with just a few words, and plenty of images.</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NMacTuHPWFI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Innovation for You</h3>

<p>Kudos to Amazon for combining some existing pieces to create something new. Most inspiring for anyone who needs to innovate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apple Car? Not Likely.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/12/apple-car-not-likely/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-12T16:42:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/03/12/apple-car-not-likely</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>You have to figure out what your own aptitudes are. If you play games where other people have the aptitudes and you don’t, you’re going to lose. And that’s as close to certain as any prediction that you can make. You have to figure out where you’ve got an edge. And you’ve got to play within your own circle of competence.
<br/>~Charlie Munger, Vice Chairman, Berkshire Hathaway</p></blockquote>

<p>Some journalists speculate that <a href="http://9to5mac.com/2015/02/19/apple-electric-car-team/">Apple is building a car</a> because they recently hired some automotive engineers away from Tesla. My prediction: Apple is <em>not</em> building a car. Apple might build a device that plays a major role in the automotive marketplace. But a fully assembled automobile is too far outside the company&rsquo;s <em>circle of competence</em>, as Charlie Munger might say. Apple succeeds because the company maintains disciplined focus within its circle of competence.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>AppleTV as an Example</h3>

<p>Case in point: AppleTV. Pundits predicted an AppleTV with a large LCD display, in a form factor that might be built by Samsung or Sony. But instead, Apple created a black set-top box about the size of a hockey puck. Apple focused on those parts of the television ecosystem that are most closely tied to their circle of competence:</p>

<ul>
<li>User experience</li>
<li>Internet connectivity</li>
<li>Content delivery</li>
</ul>


<p>Apple entered the television marketplace while remaining within its circle of competence. Even better: Content delivery is a cash flow engine that generates revenue for as long as Apple can push bits down the wire.</p>

<h3>iPhone Example</h3>

<p>When Apple entered the mobile phone market, they focused within their circle of competence.</p>

<ul>
<li>User experience for computing devices, using a subset of Mac OS X.</li>
<li>Internet connectivity via WiFi.</li>
<li>Content delivery (iTunes).</li>
</ul>


<p>In the area where Apple lacked experience, mobile network management, they partnered with an industry veteran (initially AT&amp;T). By focusing within its circle of competence, Apple was able to negotiate aggressive terms with AT&amp;T, terms which included <em>no carrier branding on the physical device</em>. Later, Verizon, T-Mobile, Sprint, and all of the other major players begged for the same deal as AT&amp;T.</p>

<p>And, as with AppleTV, content delivery is an engine that prints money for as long as Apple can push bits over the radio waves.</p>

<h3>Apple&rsquo;s Automotive Entry</h3>

<p>Apple will not build a fully assembled automobile. They&rsquo;re more likely to create an auto-related device that leverages their existing circle of competence. Something that shows off their skills with user experience, Internet connectivity, and content delivery.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s automotive content delivery offering will be interesting. The company currently offers maps and directions. What&rsquo;s next&hellip; maintenance data? Entertainment? How about a &ldquo;find my car&rdquo; serivce for those of us who forget where we park at the shopping mall.</p>

<p>Apple&rsquo;s automotive device will fit well within the company&rsquo;s circle of competence. And Apple fans will line up around the block to buy it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Context Changes Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T17:48:08-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/22/context-changes-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are some cases where time zone information is absolutely critical. For example: When scheduling a video conference that crosses national boundaries.</p>

<p>A few hours ago, Google sent me a reminder about today&rsquo;s <a href="http://linuxbarbados.org">LinuxBarbados</a> meeting. The group meets via video conferencing software over the web. Google&rsquo;s reminder was confusing because it showed the time without the time zone (screenshot below). LinuxBarbados is based in the Caribbean, and some of the members participate from other time zones.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper middle'><img class='caption' src='/images/GH_time_zone_arrow.png' width='' height='' alt='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?' title='What time is it when the time zone is unknown?'><span class='caption-text'>What time is it when the time zone is unknown?</span></span></p>

<p>Google&rsquo;s automated reminder said <code>3pm - 4pm</code> with no time zone reference. How confusing! Members of the group received the same automated reminder with the same information, regardless of time zone. A small change, displaying the time as <code>3pm - 4pm (CST)</code> would solve the problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Other Context Examples</h3>

<p>When people speak with each other directly, context is implied. But when communication happens in printed form, it&rsquo;s helpful to have the context in print, too. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>Walking down the street, you see a poster advertising a concert on January 29th. No year is shown. Is this an old poster for a concert that happened last year on Jan 29th? Or is the event happening next week?</li>
<li>A restaurant menu offers delivery service. Just call the number, and order your food. The phone number is seven digits long, with no area code. Most customers would abandon the menu in favor of a restaurant with more complete information.</li>
<li>Following the train of thought in the previous example: Since phone service has fallen in price, many people call internationally on a more regular basis. A complete phone number should include the country code.</li>
</ul>


<p>Context changes everything. Something all of us need to remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Windows. Stronger Planes.]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/02/no-windows-stronger-planes/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-02T23:34:04-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2015/01/02/no-windows-stronger-planes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is always good to start the new year with something inspirational. <a href="http://www.technicondesign.com/">Technicon Design</a> created a 3-minute video to demonstrate their IXION Windowless Jet Concept. Worth watching full screen.</p>

<center><iframe name="windowlessjet" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/78458486" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<p>How can a plane with no windows offer better views for passengers?</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Windows vs Fuselage Strength</h3>

<p>When we add a window to the fuselage of an airplane, we reduce the strength of the fuselage. Glass is weaker than aluminum. So aircraft engineers need to make up for the lost strength. The engineers might add a support structure, thicken the aluminum, or try a different alloy.</p>

<p>But when windows are eliminated, structural integrity is maintained. And the weight of the plane can be reduced because we can eliminate the extra supports.</p>

<h3>How Do We See Without Windows</h3>

<p>As shown in the Technicon video, views can be better without windows!  Cameras are mounted at strategic points on the outside of the plane. And the inner surface of the plane, the part that passengers can see, is covered with a display material. Computers take the images captured by the external cameras, and they translate that into images for display on the inner walls of the plane.</p>

<p>The result: Passengers feel like they&rsquo;re flying in a glass plane. That&rsquo;s an idea best communicated through the Technicon video.</p>

<h3>Applying Tech Across Industries</h3>

<p>Processing power continues to fall in price. Flat panel monitors get less expensive each day. The window-less plane shows us what can happen when advances in one industry are applied to another. Blend these advances with a high-speed internet connection delivered via satellite, and the Internet of Things (IoT) takes a great leap forward. Cross-discipline engineering is exciting.</p>

<p>Happy New Year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OWC Thinks Ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/30/owc-thinks-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-30T17:44:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2014/12/30/owc-thinks-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/owc_ssd.jpg' width='' height='' alt='MacBook Pro SSD, next to a nickel.' title='MacBook Pro SSD, next to a nickel.'><span class='caption-text'>MacBook Pro SSD, next to a nickel.</span></span>
Every computer user has to deal with this at some point. Your machine runs out of storage space: hard drive, SSD, or whatever mass storage you happen to use. In my case, the 512GB SSD in my early 2013 MacBook Pro was over 90% full. Time for an upgrade.</p>

<p>Fortunately (and contrary to what the Apple literature says) it is possible to upgrade the SSD in a MacBook Pro. RAM is different because the MBP&rsquo;s RAM is soldered to the logic board. But the SSD plugs into a socket. The SSD upgrade path is well-documented on YouTube and elsewhere.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Ordered from OWC</h3>

<p>Ordering an SSD from Amazon would have saved a few bucks, but I chose <a href="https://www.macsales.com/">Other World Computing</a> instead. Past experience with OWC has been outstanding. The company consistently offers high-performance gear. It was all a matter of trust.</p>

<p>On the day my 960GB SSD arrived, I smacked myself on the forehead. I realized (too late) that I forgot to order a screwdriver for the special pentalobe screws that hold the MacBook Pro together.</p>

<h3>Screwdrivers Included</h3>

<p>But&hellip; When I opened the SSD box from OWC, I was pleasantly surprised. A pentalobe screwdriver was included in the SSD kit, along with a six-point Torx screwdriver. Both screwdrivers are needed for the installation. Thanks to OWC’s forethought, my upgrade plans moved forward undisturbed.</p>

<p>The hardest part of the SSD upgrade was waiting <em>patiently</em> for the Time Machine restoration to complete.</p>

<p>OWC thinks ahead.</p>

<h3>Lesson Learned</h3>

<p><a href="http://wisdomgroup.com">WisdomGroup</a> turned twenty years old today. Whenever I experience outstanding service from a company, I pause to think about how to apply the lesson to WisdomGroup and all of our related ventures. The lesson in this case: Think ahead. Anticipate the needs of the customer. And fulfill those needs.</p>

<p>Thanks OWC for making the SSD upgrade process as seamless as possible. And thanks for the business lesson, too!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
