<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Business | RayHightower.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://RayHightower.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-28T21:39:58-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://RayHightower.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Raymond T. Hightower - Chicago Ruby on Rails & iOS Developer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disposable Electronics in Wired Magazine]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/28/disposable-electronics-in-wired-magazine/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-28T14:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/28/disposable-electronics-in-wired-magazine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What can we build with disposable electronics? An ad in the January 2014 issue of <a href="http://wired.com">Wired Magazine</a> lets the reader change the color of a Moto X smartphone by pressing a colored circle on the page. This 20-second video shows the ad in operation followed by a glimpse of the inner workings.</p>

<center><iframe name="moto-x-disposable-electronics" width="640" height="480" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/DuU2_-AINVU?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<!--more-->


<h3>Inner Workings</h3>

<p>Taking the ad apart required one simple tool, a pair of scissors. Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s inside:</p>

<ul>
<li>Four 3-volt CR2025 lithium coin batteries. This kind of battery is commonly used to power the remote key fob for an automobile. Walgreens sells these batteries.</li>
<li>One tiny circuit board, about 1-inch square. I see nine resistors, four capacitors, one diode, and one application-specific integrated circuit (ASIC). The designation <code>C0010-V1</code> is printed on the board. Nothing shows the board&rsquo;s manufacturer.</li>
<li>Eleven switches in one switch assembly. The switches are connected to the circuit board via seven leads.</li>
<li>Three LEDs, pointed to shine light on a 3.5" x 6.5" reflecting panel.</li>
</ul>


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/moto-x-wired-ad.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.' title='Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.'><span class='caption-text'>Internal workings of Wired Magazine&rsquo;s Moto X ad.</span></span></p>

<p>This assembly is more expensive than a typical full-page ad, but probably not by much. Mildly amusing to play with, and fun to take apart. Yes, the advertisers succeded in grabbing my attention.</p>

<h3>Worth the Expense?</h3>

<p>An observation: I played with this paper gadget for a good ten minutes and I took the thing apart <em>before</em> I considered reading the ad copy. Maybe the color change is too distracting for the ad to be effective? Maybe the temptation to disassemble the ad is too distracting, too.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I&rsquo;m still talking about the ad. And blogging about it. Ultimate test: How will an ad like this influence buying behavior?</p>

<p>Beyond advertising, what else can we do with disposable electronics?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon's Guerrilla Marketing]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/02/amazon-guerrilla-marketing/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-02T20:03:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/12/02/amazon-guerrilla-marketing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night&rsquo;s episode of 60 Minutes featured an interview with Jeff Bezos, CEO of Amazon. The timing was perfect for Amazon. Black Friday was a few days ago. Cyber Monday is today. Online retailers want to be top-of-mind when people are inclined to spend money.</p>

<h3>Amazon&rsquo;s Surprise: Drones</h3>

<p>Bezos unveiled a surprise for interviewer Charlie Rose: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/b?ref_=tsm_1_tw_s_amzn_mx3eqp&amp;node=8037720011">Amazon Prime Air</a>, a service that will deliver most Amazon products in thirty minutes or less using a fleet of octocopter drones.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/amazon-prime-air-drone.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.' title='Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.'><span class='caption-text'>Amazon Prime Air. Octocopter drone ready for take-off.</span></span></p>

<h3>Guerrilla Marketing</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.gmarketing.com/">Jay Conrad Levinson</a>, author of <em>Guerrilla Marketing</em>, would applaud this move by Amazon. Amazon Prime Air is two years away at the earliest. The flying drones require Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) approval, and that takes time. By unveiling the drones now, before approval, Amazon reaps several benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Buzz. Everybody is talking about Amazon on Cyber Monday.</li>
<li>Political influence. Some of the people feeling the buzz are FAA officials.</li>
<li>Continued top-of-mind awareness. Long after Cyber Monday, the excitement of the drone idea will carry on.</li>
</ul>


<p>Congrats to the Amazon team for a well-executed Guerrilla Marketing move.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Specialized Knowledge and the Courage to Execute]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/30/specialized-knowledge-and-the-courage-to-execute/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T10:35:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/11/30/specialized-knowledge-and-the-courage-to-execute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Teenagers are a tough audience. If you have ever spoken to a youth group, you know the challenge: Speak about something important without putting the youth to sleep. Tall order.</p>

<h3>Three Stories</h3>

<p>Boy Scout <a href="http://troop534.org">Troop 534 &ldquo;Hey!&rdquo;</a> asked me to speak at the Troop’s annual reunion breakfast this year.  I approached them with three stories centered around the theme of <em>Specialized Knowledge and the Courage to Execute</em>. What a boring title! But the three stories appealed to the group. Here’s a summary of the first story:</p>

<blockquote><p>A tractor maker takes drastic action when when Enzo Ferrari (creator of the Ferrari sports car) pisses him off.</p></blockquote>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&rsquo;s the 11-minute video:</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/tWdFhEI6JiM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<h3>Gratitude</h3>

<p>This event was a big deal for me because I grew up in Troop 534 &ldquo;Hey!&rdquo;, I currently serve as one of the adult leaders, and the breakfast organizers normally invite an outsider to speak. Why listen to a speaker who you see all the time?</p>

<p>I took the speaking invitation as an opportunity to assemble some new material. Thank you scouts, parents, and leaders for having me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You Can Build Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/09/02/you-can-build-things/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-02T20:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/09/02/you-can-build-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From a video interview with Steve Jobs:</p>

<blockquote><p>When you grow up you tend to get told that the world is the way it is, and your life is just to live your life inside the world. Try not to bash into the walls too much. Try to have a nice family life. Have fun. Save a little money.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a very limited life. Life can be much broader once you discover one simple fact.<!--more--></p>

<p>Everything around you that you call life was made up by people who are no smarter than you. And you can change it. You can influence it. You can build other things that other people can use.</p>

<p>Once you learn that, you&rsquo;ll never be the same again.</p></blockquote>

<p>Check out the video:</p>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://RayHightower.com//www.youtube.com/embed/GHAJhosbWiM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Age vs. Ability]]></title>
    <link href="http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/08/05/age-vs-ability/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T06:34:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://RayHightower.com/blog/2013/08/05/age-vs-ability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/Benjamin-Franklin.jpg' width='' height='' alt='Benjamin Franklin: Statesman &amp; Scientist' title='Benjamin Franklin: Statesman &amp; Scientist'><span class='caption-text'>Benjamin Franklin: Statesman &amp; Scientist</span></span>
Age has little to do with ability. Every profession has examples of people who achieve goals even though others consider them <em>too young</em> or <em>too old</em>. People who excel in the face of stereotypes are exciting to watch.</p>

<p><em>The Wall Street Journal</em> listed some examples in a 1980s-era ad for United Technologies Corporation.</p>

<!--more-->


<blockquote><p>It&rsquo;s what you do &ndash; not when you do it.</p>

<ul>
<li>Ted Williams, at age 42, slammed a home run in his last official at bat.</li>
<li>Mickey Mantle, age 20, hit 23 home runs in his first full year in the major leagues.</li>
<li>Golda Meir was 71 when she became Prime Minister of Israel.</li>
<li>William Pitt II was 24 when he became Prime Minister of Great Britain.</li>
<li>George Bernard Shaw was 94 when one of his plays was first produced.</li>
<li>Mozart was just seven when his first composition was published.</li>
<li>Now, how about this? Benjamin Franklin was a newspaper columnist at 16, a framer of The United States Constitution at 81, and a scientist throughout his life.</li>
</ul>


<p>You&rsquo;re never too young or too old if you&rsquo;ve got talent. Let&rsquo;s recognize that age has little to do with ability.</p></blockquote>

<p>Now&hellip; let&rsquo;s get back to work!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
